Here's the transcript for the provided video.
-00:12)
This is Kim Ou-joon from Wolmal.
Fashion!
Kim Chul-su, Kim Chul-su.
Pastor Kim from Fashion Gaecheok Church.
Yes. I'd like to take this opportunity to thank Wolmal Kim Ou-joon instead.
Amen!
No, something like that happened. I received calls from two chairmen of large fashion companies who said they heard about the Dior segment.
People who could be called chairmen?
Yes, because their sales exceed 1 trillion won.
Oh.
They said they listened to it well. They said it was interesting.
Chairman.
I think they listened to it on YouTube. I actually went to consult with a certain company, and the chairman told me to come and see him for a moment. Suddenly, he started talking about Kim Chul-su. He said he listens to Dasveida. He's someone who always says he's a hardcore conservative. I was actually a little surprised that he said that.
Are you trying to report him?
No. But he said to me, "Mr. Kim, I live in Seocho, right? Hmm? I'm a third-generation wealthy person and my assets are hundreds of billions. I have several companies, right? But people living in Seocho have a very biased perception. Yes, I know. I know you think I'm a hardcore conservative, but, hmm? I actually hate being too much of a hardcore conservative, so I started listening to Dasveida by Kim Ou-joon to gain some balance. But while listening to it, at the end, I heard a familiar voice."
Haha.
He asked me, "You talked about the Dior segment, right?" and he said, "Man, that Shamanism part was so interesting," and he kept talking and said he would continue to listen carefully.
Chairman, it only costs 10,000 won a month.
That's right. For all the employees, if they do the whole thing, would there be a 10% discount for bulk purchases or something like that?
No, a premium for the chairman.
A premium? Do I have to pay a premium? Usually, they give me an acquaintance discount.
In my opinion, we should sell one company ID for a thousand people.
Oh.
Everyone listens to it.
That's good. Someone like the chairman should do that. Where does the chairman live?
That place that was flooded. Yes, well, anyway.
Then I should make a comment for the chairman. Chairman, we will create a company ID. Please contact us.
I was really surprised. He even knew about making a statistics company and he was commenting on it. Among people who say they're hardcore conservatives, there are more open-minded people than you'd think.
That person isn't a hardcore conservative. The fact that he thinks his world is so biased already means he's not a hardcore conservative.
I guess so.
Chairman! I'm looking forward to hearing from you.
Okay.
Well, where are we going today?
We talked about Chanel, Dior, and Saint Laurent, didn't we? Today, let's go to Italy.
Oh, there are many in Italy.
When people talk about Italy, they often talk about Prada or Gucci, but much earlier than them, between World War I and II, there was a legendary designer. When talking about Saint Laurent, Saint Laurent's boyfriend wrote something. Great designers like Balenciaga or Schiaparelli might have climbed to the temple of aesthetics, but they couldn't move society. Today, we're going to talk about a designer named Schiaparelli. To evaluate this person as just being aesthetic, he was a designer who approached clothes with a sensitive perspective on society.
Is this person Italian?
Yes, an Italian person. From Rome.
It seems like it left a mark on my brain cells somewhere.
The movie "The Martian." There was a movie where someone falls on Mars and grows crops. The male protagonist, while driving a car that can travel on the surface of Mars, says something like "I'm passing through the Schiaparelli crater."
Did I hear it then?
The person who discovered the Schiaparelli crater was Schiaparelli's great-uncle. It's a very intellectual family. Or maybe you heard it because of Elsa. It's Elsa Schiaparelli. I wonder if you thought of Elsa from Frozen.
I didn't know Elsa was attached to the front.
I see. Well, anyway. But fashion people often hear about this person while studying costume history, which is a special history. Oh, Schiaparelli is close friends with a painter named Salvador Dali.
It came to me. Yes. That shrimp, lobster.
That's right. Oh, you know that. Yes.
He drew a lobster on a dress.
Yes, yes.
Edward VIII.
Yes, that's right.
His wife.
Yes, yes.
His wife, what was it? Wallis Simpson.
Wallis Simpson. Duchess of Windsor. Yes.
That's all I know.
Oh, that's a lot. An American divorcee went to England.
That's right.
And fell in love with a prince.
Yes.
He wore that dress then.
Marriage of the century, something something.
Yes. The man gave up his throne.
Yes, yes.
That's because he was a bit lacking.
Is that so? People call it the romance of the century, but if you look closely, that prince was a bit lacking.
Oh.
Yes, that's right.
Duchess of Windsor. He was a playboy. He's like the 20th-century version of Prince Harry and the woman who married him and left the British royal family, what was her name? Meghan Markle.
Meghan Markle, yes.
But while selecting Schiaparelli, I was a little worried. Even if I talk about someone people recognize, it's not enough...
Exactly.
This person has been forgotten since World War II.
He was forgotten for a while but has been restored. The brand is active again.
Oh, really?
Yes. But why did I bring this up? This person's life itself is shocking. Really.
Really? I like shocking.
He was someone comparable to Prada. There was an exhibition about this person in the US. It compared Prada and Schiaparelli.
Aren't their eras different?
Yes. Because their eras are different, the title of the exhibition was "Impossible Conversation," meaning a dialogue between two people who could never meet. The clothes of the two people were very similar. Morphologically, they are very similar and look alike.
Schiaparelli sounds like a food name.
You must be hungry. Since the "D" is long, let's call it "Schiap." Between Schiap and Prada, there was an exhibition comparing the two?
Yes, it was a hot exhibition. While comparing the two, Schiaparelli's clothes look like Prada's, and Prada's clothes look like Schiaparelli's.
Oh.
There is a spiritual overlap. Schiaparelli was someone who fought against fascism. And he also went head-to-head with Stalin. The 1930s was a period full of despair and depression. After the Great Depression, the Spanish Civil War broke out, and it was a dark time historically. In that era, he always kept in mind whether fashion could give people some laughter and hope, joy, and so on, and made clothes. And Prada was surprisingly a doctor of political science.
Oh, really?
Yes. And he was a deputy leader of the Communist Party.
I knew that.
Prada left many sharp and penetrating remarks about political issues, especially in the 1980s. It was the conservative era, right? It was the era of President Reagan.
I like Prada.
Because of those aspects, I thought it would be interesting to talk about Schiaparelli as a sort of prequel to introduce Prada.
The part I like about Prada is that there's a Prada factory outlet near Florence.
Oh, there is.
Among factory outlets, this one is the best.
Just for that?
They have the most stuff at the factory outlet.
It was satisfying. I expected a cool mention, but then let's do Schiaparelli this time and Prada next time?
Oh, Prada is good. Yes, it's good.
For your information, to go there, you can take a taxi from Florence Station.
Haha.
Or you can rent a car. I sent a car from Prada, on that condition.
I see.
I rented a car at Lyon station in France and drove from there. I'll search all the outlets in southern Italy.
You're amazing.
It's fun.
That's also a great pleasure. The joy of getting a good deal.
Outlets are all on the outskirts. How can I hit all these outskirts at once? So I crossed the Alps and all...
Incredible.
Now, Schiaparelli is a 19th-century person. He was born in 1890. Similar to Chanel. The designer Schiaparelli is only known to people who major in costume history. This person wrote an autobiography called "Shocking Life." I know it well because I translated this book.
"Shocking Life"? The color, "Shocking Pink."
That's right! That's it.
Oh, that word comes to mind. Shocking Pink.
Really? Now we can unravel it a bit.
Is "Shocking Pink" Schiaparelli?
It's the color of this person's perfume.
Everything is fragmented in my head.
No, why is Shocking Pink famous? It's famous for a perfume bottle modeled after a Hollywood actress's breasts. But the perfume bottle and the wrapping paper were Shocking Pink, a deep pink color. From 1927 to 1954, he was very active. This was a time when the Great Depression hit the US, World War I, the Spanish Civil War, and World War II happened. He was a person who was at the center of all the rapidly changing events in modern history. Actually, if he wanted to live a comfortable life, he could have. His father was the dean of Rome University, a man of reputation.
Oh.
He was from an intellectual family.
That's why Chanel felt more inferior.
Oh, was he a rival with Chanel?
Chanel hated him the most. He made dolls out of straw and stuck pins in them, hating him so much.
Openly?
He hated him a lot. Because what Chanel wanted most was that well-educated people talk without being conscious, but something comes out...
The choice of words is different.
Like Pastor Kim.
Even if the assets are with the aunt.
Haha.
When speaking, the intellectual aura should be revealed, but Chanel didn't have that. He was that kind of person. His father was the president, and he also served as the head of the library of Lincei, which has a very classy library of a university founded in the 1600s, like the scientist Galileo, you know Galileo Galilei. This woman started frequenting this library from a very young age. He read Spinoza's books, political philosophy books, and was armed with culture from a very young age. However, his outsider personality was so strong that his nannies couldn't stand him.
If they said something, he would talk back and argue logically.
There were many such things. He was intellectually precocious.
That's right. The expression "precocious" doesn't seem wrong.
But his liberal arts background is rich.
Rich. Besides, his father was an Orientalist. He was very familiar with Arabic and Sanskrit. And how good would the study be? He was a daughter who was allowed to enter the study since he was a university professor. From a young age, he was a troublemaker. When parachutes were first developed during World War I, he saw them and jumped from the second floor of his house with an open umbrella.
There are kids like that.
He was a bit of a troublemaker, but his mother always teased him for being ugly.
Is that why he became like this?
He was compared to his sister, who wasn't as good-looking. Schiaparelli said he had this daydream when he was young. "Is there a way to make flowers bloom on my face?" So he got seeds from a gardener, put them in his nostrils and ears, and fell asleep. But they actually bloomed.
Haha.
It probably swelled up. So doctors had to pull seeds out of his nose and things like that.
He wasn't ordinary.
His imagination was rich. At the age of 14, he wrote an erotic book.
At 14?
He wrote erotic poems and was kicked out by his father.
I see. His imagination was rich, and he was intellectually precocious, and he was outstanding in every way.
But he was ugly.
Haha.
Actually, as an adult, Schiaparelli's appearance, in my opinion, is better than Chanel's.
No, we have to look at the appearance of the sisters in that family.
Oh, that's right.
He overcame his complex like this when he grew up.
That's right. The expression "overcoming" is correct because he brought those childhood memories exactly as they were when he made clothes. He sewed with seeds in the pockets, like a gardener's clothes.
Thinking his face would become pretty after putting them in when he was young.
Exactly.
Hoping flowers would grow from his nose.
Yes, he put petals in.
He put that imagination into his clothes.
Exactly. It's amazing when you think about it now.
His fantasy is very strong.
He's a person with strong fantasy. But he was a single mom. Schiaparelli. His husband was a scammer, but he must have been handsome. He had a strong relationship with Isadora Duncan... I'll stop here. Anyway, because of that, he got divorced and had a daughter, but the daughter suffered from polio. After the divorce, he came to Paris alone and started his career as a designer.
He's Italian, but he came to Paris and started his career as a fashion designer.
To put it another way, he was an outsider. He had the sensibility of an outsider, he was a single mom, and his daughter was sick. It was a shackle. And he didn't have a professional degree.
Ah.
He got married at 20. His father was really against it. He wanted him to study.
Of course.
Since he's a person with strong fantasy, he married a person like a scammer pastor.
A scammer pastor.
Theosophy, which means studying knowledge about God, but actually the same feeling as Shincheonji. They're heretics who interpret eschatology.
Cults, things like that.
Exactly. But he was so handsome. So he fell in love at first sight and got married five days after they met.
So he married because of his fantasy.
He regretted it greatly.
Then when he got married, he must have spent all the money his father gave him.
His husband spent all the dowry money on gambling and slept with Isadora Duncan and so on. From this man's point of view, he sucked the woman dry, and this woman became penniless. Exactly. He was embarrassed and felt he should live a new life, so he went to Paris.
Exactly.
But how did he get into fashion?
That's very mysterious.
He has no background.
That's a good question. We have to keep in mind that Schiaparelli is a 19th-century person, and professional institutions for designers were starting to emerge, and even without a degree, career experience was necessary, right? He was someone who succeeded as a designer in a process where these things were completely non-existent. So when he succeeded in Paris, a fandom was formed. "You're Italian, how did you come to Paris and succeed as a designer?" "No professional knowledge, no degree." These questions started pouring in.
The person who first scouted him had a good eye.
That person was Poiret. A designer named Paul Poiret, who was called the "King of Paris Fashion" in the early 20th century. He was much higher than Chanel. Later, he became a competitor with Chanel, but when Chanel was starting to do well, he met him on the street. I mentioned that Chanel made a little black dress. Seeing that, Poiret teased him and asked, "Whose funeral are you going to?" So Chanel retorted, "Your funeral, man!" and went on his way.
I like Chanel's personality.
Truly great. Saying "Your funeral." Chanel succeeded with his personality.
But this person named Poiret was also amazing. Even if we don't know art history today, even if we don't know the name Fauvism, we've heard of names like Henri Matisse. He was the first person to collaborate and do a collab between art and fashion.
Okay.
And he was the first person to open a fashion show in Paris.
He's like the founder of the fashion industry.
Exactly. Before that, they didn't introduce clothes by dressing models. He held a garden party with live models wearing clothes.
Before, they used to dress mannequins.
They had a party and presented a collection by dressing models. Oh. What's amazing is that the people who modeled then were celebrities. People who corresponded to famous entertainers of that time.
André Kim got his motif from there.
Oh, exactly. So the people who modeled were dancers. Isadora Duncan, who is called the founder of modern dance. He just made clothes for her for free. He made clothes that would suit a dancer and told her, "Just come to my party and walk around." He was the first person to start something like this.
He's like the founder of modern fashion marketing.
Exactly. He had poets write advertising copy.
Oh.
What's amazing is that people who studied French literature know these names. Rimbaud or Baudelaire. People who have done some literature will know these names. Surprisingly, this person wrote fashion advertising copy. When releasing perfume, he even wrote poems to introduce it.
He's also the founder of the literature collab.
Exactly. More importantly, you know labels attached to clothes, brand labels.
The tag on the back of the neck.
This label was born because of this person. Designers didn't have labels on their clothes before. Oh. But Poiret was annoyed. He spent 200 hours making an evening dress, and 80 hours making a dress for daytime use. All those numerous artisans made it stitch by stitch.
Since he collaborated with artists, even if they draw a picture, they sign it.
Exactly. Why isn't that on these clothes? Oh. Why can't I leave my signature? When we look at paintings by Renoir or Impressionists, there's Renoir's signature with the date. Why doesn't fashion receive such treatment as an artist?
There was no such thing before?
No. He broke this and started making these labels.
"I must put my name on my clothes like a signature on a painting." Almost all of modern fashion started here.
You pointed out that it's the start of fashion marketing, and that's a very good insight. He made things like limited edition magazines. Do you know that magazines also come out from Dior?
I only know Wolmal as a magazine.
Fashion brands make very high-quality magazines for their customers. Companies like Celine too.
It seems like everything being done now was already done then.
He did it all then. He's the founder of founders. Oh. The name of the magazine is also cool, "Gazette du Bon Ton," meaning "the journal of good taste." He was a designer who first started using the concept of lifestyle, centered on taste. Surprisingly, he did textile and fabric designs with Fauvist painters and even did sofa designs.
So it didn't end with clothes.
You know shops like Muji or Jaju. It's the same for Hermès. It's called a maison. From home wear worn at home to interior accessories and furniture design. He was the first person to do that.
He's the father.
He brought art into fashion.
Schiap worked under this person. You asked what the trigger was. He came to Paris penniless, but because he was well-educated, he had high standards. He couldn't just pass by Paul Poiret's store, as a single mom holding a child.
He was a customer at first.
He was hesitating whether it would be okay, and he met Poiret in the store. "Mademoiselle, try on what you want to wear. Don't hesitate, you don't have to buy it. If there's an outfit you really like and are attracted to, try it on and just tell me a word or two about why you're attracted to it."
He must have said a word or two excellently.
He said a word or two coolly and confessed that he really wanted to wear it. But Poiret just gave him the clothes for free.
Poiret is cooler.
Really? Than Schiap? It's not "Schiapy." Let's stick with Elsa. But actually, Schiap, Schiap, you said that. The Italian pronunciation "Schiaparelli" was difficult even for French people. So they called him by a nickname, and I was surprised that you said it. They called him "Schiap."
I'll go with "Schiap."
Then Poiret said, "Try making a sketch of the clothes you want."
Poiret, who had an eye for art, at first felt sorry for him as he was holding a baby and gave him clothes, but after listening to him talk, his style was educated. He knew. Hearing him talk, "Oh, this person is more than just someone to feel sorry for, I might be able to use him somewhere." That's how it started, so to speak.
Poiret established a free art school called Atelier to raise artists at that time. Fauvist painters were teachers. It's amazing if you think about it now. He made people learn under them, and the condition was not to learn traditional fashion education, but to think about fashion completely anew. He chose girls from poor backgrounds without prejudice and taught them for free. Because he was that kind of person, there might have been such an aspect. So Schiap sold sketches to this person as a trigger.
"What can you do?"
He must have said something like, "I like sculpture and art, can I try drawing clothes that I can realize?" At that time, many artists supported themselves by selling their fashion sketches like that. Dior did that too.
It happened because of a chance meeting.
It's serendipity. But it happened. So he sold one or two, and Poiret really liked them. He told him to try going independent and that he would support him, "Why don't you try having your own shop?" and told him to try his first collection. Professors in Korea also do this, but this is actually spitting on my own face, but many people point out that a problem with Korean fashion education is that when designers become professors, the limit is that they keep making replicas of themselves. They instill the designs and thoughts they were good at into students, so these disciples cannot get out of the teacher's shadow. Actually, such things are called limits. Poiret goes beyond this.
"Do what you want to do."
Actually.