Here is the transcription for the provided audio:
**Kim Eui-soo**: Welcome back to "Monthly Kim Eui-soo." I'm Kim Eui-soo. Today, we've invited the mid-to-lower-level flying object of classical literature—
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: He resides on the 4th floor of an apartment but aims to fly high in the sky. Professor Yoo Kwang-soo is here. Hello.
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: I'm UFO Yoo Kwang-soo.
**Kim Eui-soo**: Let's add an "M" in front.
**Speaker 3**: An "M"?
**Kim Eui-soo**: A "Middle-aged." (Laughter)
**Kim Eui-soo**: Where are we flying today?
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: Today, we're flying to the late Joseon Dynasty, around the time of King Yeongjo. This is a very clear record, so it's a true story from the 18th century under King Yeongjo.
**Kim Eui-soo**: A true story.
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: Probably very few people have heard this. The translator is a professor at another university, but it hasn't been researched much. Exploring its meaning in such detail might be a first in Korean history, or even worldwide.
**Kim Eui-soo**: Who is this person?
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: There was a real person named Yi Jae-un during King Yeongjo's reign. He was from the lineage of Yi San-hae, a leader of the Buk-in (Northern) faction. He was from a prestigious Yangban family, but he was a son of a concubine. This man said something very unusual: "Yangban, you should do business."
**Kim Eui-soo**: He wrote a book about that?
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: Yes, he did. He said, "You Yangbans only try to become officials, but you shouldn't just do that. You need to do business and make money." He wrote a whole book about this.
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: This was quite revolutionary because Joseon was a class-based society. Those below the middle class made their own living, but Yangbans only had one way to survive: becoming an official and receiving a salary. If they had land from their ancestors, as I explained in the "Hungbu-jeon" episode, they could manage it. But land was fixed. Early on, under King Taejo Yi Seong-gye, when they redistributed land after driving out the Goryeo elite, there was some dynamism. But as the number of Yangbans grew, they reached a limit. The only way left for them to survive was receiving a salary as an official. So, he told them to do business. This was a direct challenge to the authority of the Yangban.
**Speaker 3**: From the perspective of that era, it was an incredibly subversive statement.
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: It's quite unique. It talks about the birth of the Korean bourgeoisie. The book is called "Haedong Hwasikjeon." "Haedong" refers to Korea. "Hwasik" means increasing wealth. It's a collection of stories about making money in Korea.
**Kim Eui-soo**: A "rags-to-riches" story.
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: Exactly. He explains why people need to make money and includes short stories about nine wealthy individuals. For example, the most dramatic and interesting one is about a man named Yi Jin-uk.
**Kim Eui-soo**: So, the author is Yi Jae-un, but it's not an autobiography; it's a collection of cases of contemporary wealthy people.
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: It's like a "Wealth Report." This is probably the first time this is being explained in Korea. I'm 99.9% sure. Even among classical literature researchers, very few have read this. It's that kind of writing.
**Kim Eui-soo**: Then we can talk about it however we want. (Laughter)
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: Alright. In the Joseon Dynasty, there was a man named Yi Jin-uk who was incredibly wealthy. It's a true story. Not just wealthy, but like a top 5 conglomerate chairman of today. Extremely wealthy. But Yi Jin-uk was poor in his youth and of low status.
**Kim Eui-soo**: Otherwise, there's no story. If his father was rich and he was rich, that's the end.
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: But it's not easy for a child to be as rich as their wealthy father. They tend to take what they have for granted. Social sciences have researched this a lot.
**Speaker 3**: (To Yoo) Why are you apologizing? You're not a conglomerate heir either. (Laughter)
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: Right. Anyway, he was poor and low-born, and his parents died early. He lived with his uncle. The text says he lived like a ghost in a corner room, barely noticed. His uncle wasn't necessarily a bad person, but usually, kids in that situation are put to work. He wasn't made to work, but he wasn't given an education either. His uncle's children were educated, but he was neglected. So, when they studied, he would watch from afar and learn characters on his own. He managed to find a book and memorized it thoroughly, figuring out the meanings himself. He realized how the world worked. He had nowhere to go, but an old man living nearby noticed him. He saw the boy was bright. One day, the old man called him and gave him 1,000 yang.
**Kim Eui-soo**: How much is 1,000 yang?
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: In "Simcheong-jeon," 300 seok of rice could buy a house. 1,000 yang is much more than that. It's a huge sum. One yang is 100 pun. A bowl of soup would cost about 2 pun back then. So, he gave him 1,000 yang and said, "Take this as seed money and try to increase your wealth."
**Speaker 3**: This is a huge leap. (Laughter)
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: In a novel, there'd be more explanation, but this is a brief report of facts. The old man saw the boy was special. That intermediate process is skipped.
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: After agonizing over it for a few days, the boy left home and went to Dongnae, which is now part of Busan. Back then, Busan was a small place within Dongnae.
**Kim Eui-soo**: It's a port.
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: Foreigners were there. There was a place for trade called Waegwan. He went there with the money. Still a teenager, he observed people and noticed a grimy Japanese laborer doing menial work. He went up to him and spoke. "You're working so hard. This work is lowly and difficult, but more importantly, there's no future in it. Why not do business with me?" He picked this man out. The man was surprised. He was young, after all. The man said, "I'm not lowly by birth, but I'm poor and have to work as a servant here to survive. I've worked here for many years, but you're the first person to speak to me like a human."
**Speaker 3**: He noticed something special there. Usually, people would look down on a grimy laborer, but he judged the man's character and work ethic. He didn't care about status.
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: That's the key today. Should we just end it here? (Laughter)
**Kim Eui-soo**: As I get older, I notice things about myself. One thing is that I realized other families don't eat a whole plate of fried eggs at every meal. (Laughter) My mother used to fry five or six eggs for each of us in our family of four. I thought that was normal. When I went to a friend's house, they gave me just one egg. I was like, "Are you kidding me?"
**Kim Eui-soo**: Another thing I realized in college was the way people treat service workers. There's a subtle look of downplaying them. I noticed it and thought, "Why are they doing that?" I don't treat them particularly kindly, but I don't think I'm better or worse than them. Whether it's a janitor or a president, it's all the same.
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: That's exactly how I think.
**Kim Eui-soo**: Really? But those people change their tone and attitude when they're in front of someone powerful. I found that so strange. It wasn't intentional on their part; it was just... ingrained. I wondered where that came from. It was the second thing I realized after the fried eggs. As I grew older, I realized it's a very important difference. It's not that I have a high sense of human rights; it's just...
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: I'm the same way.
**Kim Eui-soo**: I don't see a hierarchy. It's not about being rude, but I just don't see it. If someone has a high academic background, I joke about it. If they don't, I joke about that too. I'm comfortable with people who have that kind of self-esteem. Otherwise, it's tiring.
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: That's exactly the point of today's story. Titles and status don't make a person. Strip all that away, and we're all the same.
**Kim Eui-soo**: Maybe I grew up in a family without much "breeding." (Laughter)
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: I also agree, maybe because I'm religious. One of the core ideas of Christianity is when Jesus told people to "cast the first stone" at the woman caught in adultery. It means everyone is a sinner. It's not about feeling guilty, but about everyone being on the same level.
**Kim Eui-soo**: I used to go to church but stopped. I didn't like that part—everyone being a sinner. (Laughter)
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: It's about having the same "default value." Anyway, Yi Jin-uk didn't care about status, nationality, or appearance.
**Kim Eui-soo**: Appearance is important, though.
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: Well, yes. (Laughter) When I went back to school after the military, there was a girl at a coffee shop. Every time I asked for coffee, she'd put a mountain of whipped cream on it if I asked for a little extra. That's just business. (Laughter) Anyway, Yi Jin-uk had no barriers. He approached people differently.
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: So, he gave the 1,000 yang to the Japanese laborer.
**Speaker 3**: He's crazy! (Laughter)
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: The laborer was shocked. He said, "It's hard to trust people. Even close friends don't easily go into business together. But you just met me, and I'm grimy and work in a kitchen, and I'm a foreigner. Why do you trust me?" Yi Jin-uk smiled and said, "I already know everything."
**Kim Eui-soo**: He eventually became a tycoon. So he must have realized that with his limited resources, trade was the only way. He watched the foreigners at the port for a long time and picked this man. He probably checked his reputation, too. The story skips that, but he must have done his homework before giving him 1,000 yang.
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: Exactly. Records are often brief. He gave the money and said, "I'll see you in two years."
**Speaker 3**: Maybe he said, "Leave your daughter as collateral." (Laughter)
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: The laborer didn't even have a family! Anyway, two years passed. The laborer returned with 3,000 yang. He tripled the money. Yi Jin-uk took 1,000 yang back—
**Speaker 3**: He took 2,000 yang! (Laughter)
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: No, the record says he gave it all back for the laborer to go back to Japan and do more business. The laborer was touched and said, "You're not even married yet. You should build a house first." He gave Yi Jin-uk 300 yang to buy a house and took the rest to trade between Korea and Japan.
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: A few years later, there was a rumor that a Tongsinsa (diplomatic mission) was going to Japan. The Japanese man told Yi Jin-uk to buy up all the ginseng in the country. Yi Jin-uk had a lot of capital by then, so he bought all the high-quality ginseng from the northern regions. He then gave it to the man to take to Japan.
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: When the mission was about to leave, the government needed ginseng to take as gifts. Usually, they'd get it from "Gwan-byeon" merchants who had a monopoly. They'd overcharge the government. But this time, the merchants couldn't find any ginseng. The officials were furious and jailed the head of the merchants. That's when Yi Jin-uk appeared and said, "I'll provide the ginseng." He had already sent high-quality ginseng to Japan. He told the officials, "I've already prepared it in Japan. If I'm lying, you can have my head."
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: In Japan, the grimy laborer presented the best ginseng to the mission. Everyone was amazed. Yi Jin-uk was rewarded and became incredibly wealthy.
**Kim Eui-soo**: Did he sell it for a much higher price?
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: No, he sold it at the official price. It wasn't a malicious monopoly. He didn't harm the state. He just took the profit that the greedy merchants would have taken. He became a high official and a legendary figure.
**Kim Eui-soo**: It's like a futures trade based on information. Some might say he hoarded ginseng and hurt the common people, but this was high-quality ginseng for gifts. If the mission hadn't gone, he would have been in trouble. He took a huge risk.
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: Exactly. The merchants were waiting for their cut, but Yi Jin-uk saw the gap.
**Kim Eui-soo**: I've been in business for 30 years. Luck is huge. They say 70% luck, 30% skill, but I think it's 90% luck. Skill is the ability to endure until luck arrives. People think it's all their own ability, like Chairman Chung Ju-yung. If he did the same thing today, he'd be stuck in a one-room apartment. His talent met the right era. Yi Jin-uk was the same.
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: He made a fortune and met the Japanese man again. He gave him half of the profit. The man made a long speech about how Yi Jin-uk helped him when he was a lowly servant and how he worked hard to repay that trust. He credited everything to Yi Jin-uk's "fortune."
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: Yi Jin-uk insisted on giving him a third of the wealth, saying he wouldn't be a man of integrity otherwise. Both became extremely wealthy.
**Kim Eui-soo**: How did he grow his wealth from there?
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: He bought land and houses, but he stopped doing business himself. He lent money to others to do business. He became a "Gaekju" (broker). This is similar to the financial systems in Venice or the Dutch East India Company. While the Catholic elite back then looked down on money, these systems allowed for credit and banking to develop.
**Kim Eui-soo**: It's like a holding company. He became a venture capitalist. It sounds a lot like Jewish business practices. They couldn't own land, so they focused on finance and trade.
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: He learned from the international traders at the port.
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: He gathered his relatives and friends who were struggling and taught them business, providing them with capital. His network grew across the country and even to China and Japan. 70-80% of traders were using his money. He became a true tycoon. If someone failed, he didn't scold them; he invested double the amount until they learned. He wanted to help others succeed.
**Kim Eui-soo**: He invested in education and gave people a second chance. The author of the book was struck by this system.
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: Another thing was women. He supported Gisaengs (female entertainers) who were aging and had no future. He dressed them well and supported their arts. He was like a Medici of the Joseon arts scene. He created a social welfare system for them and connected them with successful traders. He became a patron of Hanyang's (Seoul's) culture.
**Kim Eui-soo**: It was his leisure activity, which created an ecosystem and generated more wealth.
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: Once, a high minister's son passed the civil service exam. There was a huge party. At the same time, a general's son passed the military exam and wanted to throw a party too, but all the performers were at the minister's house. The general wrote to Yi Jin-uk.
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: Yi Jin-uk sent a note to the minister's house. As soon as the Gisaengs saw the note, they all stopped performing and went to the general's house. The minister was shocked. The Gisaengs said they couldn't refuse Yi Jin-uk's request. The minister realized Yi Jin-uk's influence was greater than his own.
**Speaker 3**: He was the "Godfather." (Laughter) He resolved conflicts that officials couldn't.
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: Another time, an official from the Uigeumbu (investigation bureau) was looking for a plasterer. He found one working at Yi Jin-uk's house and forcibly took him, even beating him. Yi Jin-uk was furious and had his men catch the official and flog him. Then he sent a message to the head of the Uigeumbu. The head official, instead of being angry at Yi Jin-uk, beat the underling for being disrespectful at Yi Jin-uk's house.
**Kim Eui-soo**: Yi Jin-uk then sent 50 yang and some cloth to the official he had flogged to comfort him. He knew how to handle people's hearts. tycoons who are respected by the public. People often worry about a company like Samsung, even though it's none of their business. (Laughter) It's because they hope some of that success might trickle down to them. Yi Jin-uk was humble and never showed off, so people naturally respected him.
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: He lived until he was 70 and had many descendants. When he died, people from all over Hanyang came to his funeral. Gisaengs stood along the road with torches and scrolls to mourn him. People from Beijing and Japan also came. The final evaluation was that he was a man who could "push open the palace gates and bring the dead back to life."
**Kim Eui-soo**: He had incredible management skills and was thorough with his records. He wasn't just a "nice guy"; he had a solid system that lasted. His descendants couldn't maintain it, though. It was his unique ability.
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: Exactly. It was the man, the era, and the luck.
**Kim Eui-soo**: Professor Yoo's lesson is that Joseon-style business is still applicable today. My lesson is: "Don't expect favors." If you don't expect anything from anyone, you can live however you want. I don't care about Samsung or anyone else. (Laughter)
**Kim Eui-soo**: That's all for today. Thank you.
**Yoo Kwang-soo**: Thank you. (Applause)