This is the transcript for the provided audio:
**Host:** I’m Kim Eo-jun, from World-end Kim Eo-jun. I’ve traveled around Europe, Asia, South America, North America, and Africa alone or as a couple by bicycle, bike, or car. But isn’t that all on land? This time, we’re going to the sea. Cruise. I have four people with me. Gi Da-yong, who was a crew member on the Royal Princess in the United States.
**Gi Da-yong:** This is Gi Da-yong, a former crew member of Princess Cruises.
**Host:** You wrote a book, didn’t you? I’ll call you Author Gi.
**Gi Da-yong:** Yes, thank you.
**Host:** And Cho Seon-ju, who was a crew member on the Costa Serena.
**Cho Seon-ju:** Hello. I’m Cho Seon-ju, a former crew member.
**Host:** I’ll call you Author Cho. You wrote a book too, right?
**Cho Seon-ju:** Yes, I did.
**Host:** And Lee Se-guk, who was the executive chef for Korean food at Costa Cruises. Hello.
**Lee Se-guk:** Nice to meet you. I’m Lee Se-guk, the former executive chef for Korean food at Costa Cruises.
**Host:** I’ll call you Chef Lee.
**Lee Se-guk:** Yes.
**Host:** And the one who boarded the guests on your ship is me. Lee Yong-ho. You run a travel agency, right?
**Lee Yong-ho:** Yes, I’m running a cruise travel agency.
**Host:** I’ll call you CEO Lee. Now, is Princess an American line?
**Gi Da-yong:** Yes, it’s an American cruise line.
**Host:** Is Costa Italian?
**Cho Seon-ju:** Yes, it’s an Italian company.
**Host:** We did a good job casting. I’ll start with how the four of you got involved with these cruises. Author Gi, how did you end up on a cruise?
**Gi Da-yong:** I used to work as a hotelier in the Maldives. A Japanese friend I worked with in the Maldives posted a photo on SNS wearing a white uniform. That’s when I first learned about cruise crew members. Back then, the Maldives was an island life. If you have 15 minutes, you can walk around.
**Host:** I know the Maldives is an island.
**Gi Da-yong:** Ah, the Baros Island where I was, was an island that you could walk around in 15 minutes. If you go snorkeling for 30 minutes to an hour, you can go all around the island. After living on such an island, when I heard about cruise crew members, I thought, “Now I can go out to the United States.” And cruise crew members are similar to hoteliers. Many people describe the job itself as a floating hotel. It’s also often called an inclusive hotel. At that time, the cruise line that was trying to cross over to Asia was Princess Cruises.
**Host:** You wanted to escape from the island. In short. Okay. How about Author Cho?
**Cho Seon-ju:** Oh, I was so surprised that it sounded like you were telling my story. I was in Bali. Bali is an island. I need to escape from here too. I worked at a resort in Bali for about two years. Cruises occasionally float in the sea in Bali. My Romanian friend said she wanted to get on a ship like that if she escaped from Bali. So that friend posted a picture of her on the ship on Facebook.
**Host:** You went along with your friend.
**Cho Seon-ju:** Yes, that’s right. It just happened to be when they were recruiting Korean crew members, so I was lucky.
**Host:** We should look into the previous lives of crew members. Are they all people who escaped from islands?
**Cho Seon-ju:** That’s right.
**Gi Da-yong:** We meet people who worked in the Maldives occasionally. They like cruises.
**Host:** Okay. I understand the two of you, but you were cooking on land, so why did you think you should cook on a ship?
**Lee Se-guk:** It’s been my dream since I was young. I wanted to try cooking on a cruise. But at that time, when I was working as a head chef at a Korean restaurant in the Czech Republic, a chef came for an interview from Korea. This guy submitted resumes for the cruise and the Korean restaurant. But what he said was that he failed the cruise chef position and got accepted here, so he came here.
**Host:** You mean he did? Tell me clearly.
**Lee Se-guk:** So I was working as a head chef in the Czech Republic. I needed a Korean chef, so I posted a recruitment ad on the internet.
**Host:** You were the head chef and recruited chefs.
**Lee Se-guk:** Yes. That chef put resumes in two places, one was a cruise ship and the other was the Korean restaurant where I was working.
**Host:** You recruited him and you left?
**Lee Se-guk:** Oh, that’s right. I hadn’t thought about it until then, but through this friend, my long-forgotten dream came back. “Oh, right, I wanted to work on a cruise.” “I’ll pass everything on to you, so you take over here. I’m going my way.”
**Host:** So, Costa? Italian too, right?
**Lee Se-guk:** Yes, this is also an Italian cruise line.
**Host:** But did Costa Cruises originally recruit Korean chefs?
**Lee Se-guk:** Korean chefs are more valuable than you think abroad.
**Host:** Really?
**Lee Se-guk:** A chef who can cook Korean food but can also make other countries' dishes with high quality. Ah, a Korean chef is someone who not only knows how to cook Korean food but also knows how to make other countries' food with high quality, at least from my perspective.
**Host:** Is it different from a Chinese or Japanese chef?
**Lee Se-guk:** The difference between a Chinese chef making Korean food and a Korean chef making Chinese food is huge. Ah, Korean chefs do Chinese and Japanese food, too.
**Lee Se-guk:** For foreigners, it’s a bit difficult to do Korean food. So basically, the way they see Korean chefs abroad is someone who can speak English, who is good at Korean food, and who can also do international food to some extent.
**Host:** So they are highly utilized.
**Lee Se-guk:** They recruited someone saying they could do Korean food, and they were making it in a way that didn't make sense.
**Host:** When you travel abroad, there are Korean restaurants run by Chinese people occasionally. If you go and eat there...
**Other Speaker:** What are these guys doing?
**Lee Se-guk:** And cruise ships tend not to use Japanese chefs.
**Host:** Ah, because they only know how to do Japanese food.
**Lee Se-guk:** Yes, they are only good at Japanese food. But Korean chefs are good at everything.
**Host:** Now, CEO Lee. CEO Lee, how did you get into this? This isn't a market that's active in our country.
**Lee Yong-ho:** That’s right. I’m a bit different from the three of them. I worked as a guide in Rome for about eight years.
**Host:** You started as a guide.
**Lee Yong-ho:** Yes, so around 2004, I went to Livorno, Italy, as a guide.
**Host:** You were working as a guide in Italy and then led a cruise trip? Were those people Korean?
**Lee Yong-ho:** Yes, that’s right. So they came to Italy to take an Italian cruise.
**Host:** Ah, so that’s what a cruise is like. That was your first experience too.
**Lee Yong-ho:** Yes, I only did tours for the guests who got off.
**Host:** And then you thought, “I want to ride it too.”
**Lee Yong-ho:** Yes, I wanted to ride it, and I thought, “That’s where the money is.” So I ended up running a cruise travel agency. In the beginning, there were no cruises starting from our country and going around the world, right?
**Lee Yong-ho:** Yes, it’s the same now. You have to take a plane to the first port of departure. And then you board there. Since I was in Italy, about 80% of Mediterranean routes are there.
**Host:** You saw the potential for business. Usually, you see guests who fly in or come by train and guide them locally. But this time, guests came by ship.
**Lee Yong-ho:** Yes, that’s right. And they tipped well too. When the guests got off at the port of Livorno, I would take them on a tour of Florence and Tuscany and then take them back to the port, and they would board the ship. I would just wave goodbye from below, and the escorts would board the ship and give a simple briefing. “Today, we’ll meet at the ice rink at what time.”
**Host:** So CEO Lee only escorted them on land and when they moved to the ship, the escort on the ship explained everything. “I want to do that too.”
**Lee Yong-ho:** Right. I was like, “Wait, there’s an ice rink on a ship?” So that was the first time I learned about it, which is a bit different from the three of them.
**Host:** That sounds similar. So how many times a year do you go on a ship as an escort?
**Lee Yong-ho:** As of 2019, for Mediterranean cruises, I went about once a month.
**Host:** Now, instead of ending on land, you go into the ship with the guests.
**Lee Yong-ho:** Yes, that’s right. I’m with them from Incheon Airport until we return to Incheon Airport.
**Host:** I’m jealous. Okay, so these are the people we’re talking to. If you board a ship, don’t you stay for a few months?
**Gi Da-yong:** Crew members stay for six months and rest for two months. Once you start working, it’s for six months. We don’t just stay on one route. For example, the Alaska season is from June to September. Then you’re in the Alaska season for June, July, August, and September, and then for the remaining two months, you move toward Canada or New York, then the route changes.
**Host:** Do you change ships?
**Gi Da-yong:** Yes, the route changes. Canada has the foliage season in September and October, and the Caribbean has it in January and February.
**Host:** Ship foliage tour? Lobster too. Is there such a thing as getting off work? Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday, Thursday, Friday, and then resting on the weekend?
**Lee Se-guk:** It’s Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday, Thursday, Friday, Friday, Friday.
**Host:** You don’t have a day off.
**Lee Se-guk:** That’s why we rest for two months at once.
**Host:** You take it all at once. Is it the same for Europe?
**Cho Seon-ju:** I usually worked for eight to ten months. As you said, we work seven days a week. It’s quite intense. My department was Guest Services, like the front desk in a hotel.
**Lee Se-guk:** And I worked in the back office.
**Host:** What does the back office do?
**Lee Se-guk:** You can think of it as working in an office.
**Host:** Is the chef the same?
**Lee Se-guk:** I usually worked for eight to ten months. As far as I know, the maximum under international law is ten months. They can’t make you work longer than that.
**Host:** So you’re basically trapped on the ship once you board.
**Gi Da-yong:** Yes, that’s right. For Princess Cruises, when we say 140,000 to 160,000 tons, there are 3,000 passengers and 2,000 crew members, a total of 5,000 people. Many people call it a floating hotel.
**Host:** The reason I asked this question is that you work for six months straight. Then the system has to run like a city. Is there a police officer?
**Other Speaker:** Yes, there is.
**Host:** A doctor?
**Host:** So you’re saying all the personnel needed for a city to function are there. It’s one world.
**Gi Da-yong:** Yes, it feels like Alice in Wonderland. When you go in there, the Wi-Fi is cut off too.
**Host:** It’s cut off?
**Gi Da-yong:** Yes, so we have to pay for it. It feels like you’ve come to another world. We communicate with each other using walkie-talkies.
**Host:** Then, for example, cell phones don’t work?
**Lee Se-guk:** It’s called Ship Wi-Fi, so you can use it if you pay. It’s expensive, that’s the problem. It’s not that it doesn’t work. So when we arrive at a port of call, everyone is just looking at their phones. Since it’s expensive, they can’t contact their families on the ship.
**Host:** So it’s like a city with its own rules. Its own schedule. So who is the mayor? The Captain?
**Other Speaker:** Yes, the Captain.
**Host:** Is the Captain absolute?
**Other Speaker:** Absolute. Truly absolute.
**Host:** Does the Captain decide all the rules?
**Gi Da-yong:** All the rules. For example, if the weather gets bad, whether to continue on this route or not, he makes all those small decisions.
**Host:** Even if it’s a city they were originally supposed to go to, if the Captain says no, it can change.
**Gi Da-yong:** It changes. It’s not just the Captain’s whim, it’s because of the weather conditions. But the Captain makes the decision. He’s a capable Captain. The weather doesn’t have a mind of its own.
**Host:** CEO Lee. You said you were fascinated because there was an ice rink. What else is in there? You’ve been on the most ships, haven’t you?
**Lee Yong-ho:** Yes, I’ve been on about 100 times. Other people only been on the ships they worked on, but I’ve been on many different ships. There’s an ice rink, and you can think of it as the 63 Building lying down. There are bumper cars, a water park, and a pool where you can surf. Indoor surfing too. An artificial pool, where you can ride waves. I’ve seen an artificial rock climbing wall. You can also do Ifly. It’s like wind blowing from below and you fly up. There’s a lot. They even take you on a helicopter from the ship. You take a helicopter and look at the ship you were on, going around the scenery. I haven’t tried it yet.
**Host:** There must be a theater, of course.
**Lee Yong-ho:** Large theaters, small theaters, they are diverse for each concept. There are various restaurants like Western food, Oriental food, fusion food, and even a carousel. There’s everything. There’s even a zipline. It’s really just there. Everything in an amusement park or a hotel is there. When it’s 180,000 to 200,000 tons, it’s over 300 meters long and nearly 30 meters wide. So it’s much bigger than the 63 Building lying down.
**Other Speaker:** There’s even a sauna. Korean guests love it. And there’s also an acupuncturist.
**Host:** So it’s a city. A city that runs on its own logic and system.
**Other Speaker:** And almost all of that is free. Basically, it’s free to enjoy. If it’s something people particularly like or if it costs a lot to operate, then there’s a fee.
**Host:** What about the food? In the early 90s, I went on a backpacking trip to Northern Europe and there was something called the Silja Line from Sweden to Finland. The Eurail Pass applied, so you could ride it for free. But the buffet was free. Word got out among early Korean backpackers. So these hungry Korean backpackers packed food in their bags when they got off. So after a few months, they stopped accepting Korean guests. The memory of a big ship in my head is that food is free. I’m curious. How about the food?
**Lee Se-guk:** If Korean guests packed food and got off, it would be a disaster on the ship. We calculated how much food would be used for how many days and loaded it, but they took it all. We prepared food thinking this many people would eat this much, but the food kept running out, so we kept refilling it. So there was a gap.
**Host:** So is the food free? Or is some free and some paid?
**Gi Da-yong:** That’s a good question. There’s paid and free. One thing you must do is try as much food as possible on the cruise. Since there’s everything, I tell people to enjoy it all before they get off. But there are also paid ones. There are people who look for fine dining restaurants.
**Host:** Fine dining is paid. Then how is the basic free food provided? Buffet?
**Gi Da-yong:** Yes. And there’s a formal restaurant. Korean guests don’t know this well, but you can keep ordering and eating. Some people like eating at the buffet, and the formal restaurant where you sit at a table and order from a menu is also operated. You can think of it as a course meal. Simply put, you can eat all day. From 6 AM to 10 AM, the buffet serves breakfast, and from 12 PM to 3 PM, it serves lunch, and from 6 PM to 9 PM, it serves dinner. The buffet is always open.
**Host:** The buffet is always free.
**Lee Yong-ho:** You can go whenever you want, and then you have a designated table in the formal restaurant. There, you order and eat a more properly prepared meal. You have your own seat. You can order everything from that seat, and they say you can eat up to seven meals a day.
**Host:** For free. That’s also free.
**Lee Yong-ho:** Yes.
**Host:** But there are so many foods provided in so many ways. You might not know what food is provided when. How do you know?
**Gi Da-yong:** You have to look at the ship’s newspaper.
**Host:** A newspaper? It really is a city.
**Gi Da-yong:** Is a newspaper published on the ship?
**Gi Da-yong:** Yes.
**Host:** Is the newspaper delivered to your room in the morning?
**Gi Da-yong:** Yes. It comes in the night before. Today’s ship news.
**Host:** Is there a word from the Captain?
**Gi Da-yong:** Yes, it’s all there. A word from the Captain, what the weather is like. From the dress code to the programs on the ship, everything is specified by the minute. So you look at the newspaper and plan your schedule from morning to night. Someone might go to the buffet at that time, someone else to the formal restaurant. As you wish. At what time, there’s a barbecue party at the outdoor pool. And at what time, what kind of dessert comes out for tea time. For a Hawaii cruise, Hawaiian food comes out. For an Alaska cruise, Alaskan food comes out.
**Host:** Author Gi, you have a lot to say. Once you start, it’s just flowing out. Some people might just follow those around and eat from morning to night.
**Lee Se-guk:** There are many.
**Gi Da-yong:** I did too.
**Lee Yong-ho:** The quality of the food is very high. Hotel level. And as mentioned, the traditional food of each port of call, or food with local sauces added, all those programs are integrated.
**Host:** I want to go on a cruise.
**Lee Yong-ho:** You like traveling, so eating new food every day for a week and then getting off with a stomach ache.
**Lee Yong-ho:** You get off with weight gained.
**Gi Da-yong:** That’s right. Guests really gain weight. That’s why there’s a gym on the cruise. You can run on a treadmill while looking at the sea.
**Host:** Then what kind of foods are paid?
**Lee Se-guk:** The purpose of creating paid restaurants is to provide another experience. Rather than trying to sell more expensive things at a higher price, it’s for when you want to feel special today. A new experience. You can also propose.
**Lee Se-guk:** That’s right. If it’s a wedding anniversary, instead of having the same meal, it’s for that kind of experience. I cooked barbecue at the outdoor pool, and then I went to the paid restaurant and made the same thing. You’re paying for a special atmosphere, not necessarily for a different quality of food.
**Other Speaker:** The quality is definitely different. Making for 1,000 people at once versus making one plate is different. It must be. They even promote Michelin chefs. They also promote paid restaurants like that. But the cost is only about $20 to $40 extra per person. It’s not that expensive. Cruises are not that expensive.
**Host:** It’s not as expensive as people think.
**Lee Yong-ho:** Basically, feeding and housing you are all covered. But if you want to go to the pool for free and then surf, you might have to pay a bit. I see. So you can enjoy it from start to finish without paying a single penny extra. Some frequent travelers don’t even go sightseeing when they arrive at a port of call. They don’t get off? They just like being on the ship.
**Host:** I went to the Mediterranean once, and I went three times in a month, and each time I saw the same elderly couple. They were so cool, matching their dress codes. People like that don’t even get off. They just enjoy it on the ship. And ships have much better mileage benefits than airlines, so they just enjoy it every time.
**Gi Da-yong:** There are people who have been on 600 times. We have parties. Welcome back parties. Let’s talk about events then. We hold parties for people who have been on a cruise more than twice. Then when we call out the person who has been on the most, some people have been on this ship 600 times.
**Host:** How many years do you have to ride to do that 600 times? What kind of events are there? When you first board the ship, is there a welcome party? Does the Captain come?
**Other Speaker:** He comes to say hello. Since it’s a hotel with a 10-day schedule, there are all sorts of scenarios. Some days the Captain comes out, some days they invite only VIPs for a party. From the first day’s welcome party to the last day’s farewell. So you check the ship’s newspaper the night before and plan your schedule from morning to night. Aerobics in the morning, pool games in the afternoon, a show in the evening. Or if there’s an event where you can take photos with the Captain, you wait in line to take a photo. You completely leave your daily life behind and enter a different world where they feed you, house you, and entertain you.
**Gi Da-yong:** So when three generations come, the children go to the kids’ club, the parents go bowling or play games, and the grandparents go for a walk or exercise. Cruises are great for three generations.
**Host:** Don’t people get lost?
**Lee Se-guk:** They do. When I’m cooking in the kitchen, sometimes someone walks through the kitchen. They’ve 100% lost their way.
**Host:** With a ship that big and that many people, 3,000 passengers and 2,000 crew members, are there ever missing person cases? Like “I don’t know where my family went.”
**Gi Da-yong:** There are. We take photos of everyone when they board. So we print those photos and go around looking for them. Children might not know their room number. Up to that point, it’s expected, but extreme situations. It was on the news too, about a Korean person who went missing. Did they fall overboard? It was reported as missing.
**Cho Seon-ju:** When I was on the ship, there was a missing person case. A crew member. A crew member just disappeared? A passenger died. But when a passenger dies, the most important thing is not to let others know. Quietly. It could be a heart attack. Then what if people get into a bad mood and fight and the police have to be called?
**Lee Yong-ho:** I know the Captain’s authority is legally very high.
**Lee Se-guk:** Security personnel who act as police are given that authority in such cases. For example, “We will use this place as a detention center if something like this happens.” I heard there’s a space for that. Have you been in there?
**Lee Se-guk:** Since it’s a society too, small and large incidents happen. People’s moods change completely when they go on a trip. They go to a world that has nothing to do with the rules they followed in Korea.
**Lee Yong-ho:** But the cruise travel culture is still unfamiliar to us, so people are a bit cautious. Most of them are Westerners, and Koreans are a minority. So they are careful. What are the characteristics of Korean passengers?
**Lee Se-guk:** Korean passengers eat really well and complain a lot. They eat a lot first and then complain? They have many requests, eat well, and enjoy themselves well. Japanese passengers are quiet and then go to the front desk and complain quietly. But Koreans complain on the spot and eat well.
**Host:** What are the requests?
**Lee Se-guk:** “Give me more of this.” “When is this coming out?” “This is delicious, give it to me quickly.” “Palli-palli.” They directly state their requests. Chinese passengers are usually fine as long as there’s food. “I came to eat, so if there’s food, I’m good.” But Japanese passengers want to see all the ingredients in a vegetable stir-fry if the menu says it has carrots, onions, and cabbage. Koreans just eat even if only one or two vegetables are there.
**Host:** What else?
**Gi Da-yong:** They bring Hanbok and wear it. Foreigners really like it. They heard there was a party, so they prepared Hanbok. When they appear in Hanbok, they get everyone’s attention. On Western cruises, it’s a bit different. Generally, the characteristics are similar to usual Korean travelers. For first-timers, it’s more about experiencing the cruise culture than just traveling. By the second or third time, they can enjoy it fully. They come to a new country and a new civilization, but they don’t know the rules. So they are a bit intimidated at first. Out of 3,000 passengers, if there are only about 20 Koreans, they don’t know what they can and cannot do. So the role of the escort is very important. How the escort helps them adapt quickly is key.
**Host:** That’s a message for CEO Lee.
**Lee Yong-ho:** Yes, it’s important to tell them about the culture. For the Mediterranean, there’s an eight-hour time difference, so they wake up at 3 AM. They have to utilize that time too. We give them maps. With the map, they walk around the 18-story ship all night.
**Host:** So there’s a 3 AM program for them.
**Lee Se-guk:** And that leads to the kitchen. Oh, the ship’s kitchen runs 24 hours? 24 hours. Koreans don’t sleep in the morning. They think they have to enjoy it since they paid for it. So even if they aren't hungry, they come and take a sandwich. Even if they aren't hungry? Compared to other foreigners, we prepare more food assuming it’ll run out.
**Host:** They ask if Koreans don’t sleep.
**Lee Se-guk:** When the buffet restaurant dings at 6:15, Koreans are the first to be there. I was like that too. Because it’s a waste. They have to try everything. But basically, since there’s someone awake 24 hours a day, there has to be food. Wherever it is, if I want something, I can eat it. That’s the basic premise.
**Host:** Any difficult guests?
**Cho Seon-ju:** I remember a passenger who was on a 100-day cruise. 100 days? That’s really long. Three months. There were about 20 Koreans. Since it’s 100 days, you run into each other at least once and become friendly. You become like neighbors. One passenger wanted to get close to some Japanese passengers. He kept approaching them, but the Japanese person felt burdened. Their social boundaries were different. You should know that. When you’re on a Japanese ship, don’t do that. Each person takes things differently, so it’s better to be careful.
**Host:** Chef, any difficult guests?
**Lee Se-guk:** I didn’t have many complaints from Korean guests about food. Our people stand in line really well. And if there are five left, they think of the person behind them and only take one. On other ships, we would roast pork belly and serve it piece by piece, but some people just take the whole tray with tongs and walk away. Really? We follow the rules much better. Even the staff are surprised at how polite and orderly Koreans are, but they have many requests. But I think it’s just the culture of Chinese passengers. There are no lines, it’s scary. For example, if we bring a truckload of fruit for guests to eat while swimming and tell them to line up, they all rush in at once. “Mine, mine!” and take it all. The chefs said it was dangerous. The head chef told all the chefs to step back. That’s how different it is.
**Host:** When a Korea-China-Japan route was first established and companies were invited for an inspection, I thought, “We shouldn't do Korea-China-Japan.” When I first experienced a ship boarding from Shanghai, people would come into the formal restaurant wearing Adidas slippers. Even though there’s a dress code? Yes, slippers. You can feel a lot of cultural differences on a cruise. When I first went to the Shanghai terminal, it was as good as an international airport, but the way people lined up was like a bus terminal in the 80s. It took three or four hours for that procedure. In other regions, it takes 30 minutes to an hour. So I thought we shouldn't sell this product.
**Host:** You mentioned the procedures. Every time you get off, there must be immigration and customs. Is it like a plane? Exactly the same. It’s the same as a plane? But these people get off the ship and then get back on shortly after. So is the procedure simplified? In the past, if the boarding and disembarkation days were fixed, you couldn't board in the middle. Brief tours were possible. Recently, they allow check-ins in the middle. From the day before disembarkation, the system assigns an order. For example, people getting off at 8 AM, gather in the large theater. People getting off at 9 AM, gather in the small theater. All those processes are systematized. Don’t worry.
**Host:** What about currency? Card, exchange.
**Lee Yong-ho:** It’s all possible on the ship. Since it’s a resort. You have to use the casino too. And in some cases, you need a visa for that country. All that can be covered by the procedure. The fees are a bit expensive. If you turn on a PC and enjoy internet surfing, it’s actually more expensive. On the ship. It doesn't cost money to go to a show, play, or eat.
**Host:** Then are there cases where people fall in love? Between passengers. Romance. Romance is fine, but affairs, divorces. Or meeting and getting married. Are there many episodes like that?
**Lee Yong-ho:** I should talk about this. Since they are trapped and have nowhere to go and food is kept being provided. I don’t know the level of this story. Tell us the highest level. No, not that. Personally, it’s the highest level. The color of the trip can fade. No, they can do that. Many things happen. I go on escorts often, and the crew members' lives on the ship are very limited. Not everyone is like that, but there were many cases where they were restricted. The crew? To CEO Lee? For example, I’m not trying to say this, but I was talking about romance between passengers. Romance can start anywhere. Love Boat. Love Boat. You know it. It was a famous American series. That was Princess Cruises. That’s why Princess Cruises became famous. All sorts of love stories unfold there. So you were curious. So many people are trapped in one space. They have no other worries. But looking at the sea is only good for a day or two. That’s why there are parties for 20-somethings at 11 PM.
**Host:** What’s the age group?
**Gi Da-yong:** There are cruises like Alaska where many elderly people go. For 30-somethings and 20-somethings, I recommend the Caribbean cruise. The age group varies greatly depending on the route. For the Caribbean, there are many young people, so they go on short 3- to 5-day cruises. It’s possible for $179 per person. That cheap? The reason cruises haven't developed much in Korea is that image of a filial piety trip. Let’s break that prejudice. As mentioned, there are cruises for kids run by Disney. But those are for kids. If you go to Singapore, they only operate the casino for 2 or 3 days, or they have a club on the ship. They even planned things like that. For two days, an EDM party, a party ship.
**Host:** Then let’s divide it broadly. Three generations going on a family trip. You can inquire with CEO Lee. What I’m curious about is individuals. I’m single. I want to try it. Starting from our country. What kind of routes are there?
**Lee Yong-ho:** There are many inquiries from singles. A cruise from Busan is possible for 4 nights and 5 days. Depending on the cabin condition, whether there’s a window or a balcony, the cost is around 1.2 to 1.9 million KRW. Is that for a double room? Yes, you have to pay at least 80% even if you're alone. Even for one person. So the price is based on a double room. For that route, where does it go? From Busan to several cities in Japan for 4 nights and 5 days. Then on a ship of that size, can you enjoy all the things you mentioned? In Asia, it’s about 70,000 tons. 70,000 tons is a bit more than twice the Titanic. If it’s 70,000 tons, it has everything mentioned. Just the scale is different. Whether the theater is one floor or three floors. Is food served 24 hours? Exactly the same. Where does this depart from? Busan? For Busan departure, it’s 4 nights and 5 days, 50,000 to 70,000 tons. If you go to Singapore, you can board an 180,000-ton ship for a week. So Singapore cruises are the closest place where you can ride a good ship. You have to fly to Singapore to ride those big ships. All together with the flight, it’s about 2.5 million KRW. Then how many days is this ship? It’s 5 nights and 7 days. Where does it go from Singapore? Usually, it goes from Singapore to Malaysia and Thailand and back to Singapore. It’s a Southeast Asian route.
**Host:** Then for 30-somethings to 50-somethings, if they want to experience the Caribbean, they take a plane and go to the United States. In North America, what are the recommended routes? You mentioned the Caribbean. You don’t necessarily have to go through a travel agency. You can take a flight and book a hotel yourself. Cruises are the same. Like hotel comparison sites, there are cruise comparison sites. You can search from the lowest price. For example, if I want to go on a cruise for $500. Then you set the price and find a route. The Caribbean I mentioned is possible for $179 even on famous cruise lines. And the Alaska cruise is $309. But what I’m saying is excluding the airfare. In this case, you buy the ticket, go to the port where the ship departs, and check in yourself. People who have traveled a bit, for a 10-day trip, for a Europe trip, many people use cruises as a mode of transportation instead of a train or a plane. Among young people, if they are going from this country to that country, they take a cruise for two days. They set that as part of their trip. Instead of starting and ending there, they use it as a mode of transportation. So for travelers in Europe, they might think, “Should I go by ship instead of train, bus, or plane?” and find out it’s not expensive. That’s also a good way. To put it simply, a foreigner flies to Japan, enjoys Japan, and then takes a cruise to arrive in Busan. You could do that. You could take a month-long trip to the US or Europe, and then take 10 days for a cruise. That makes sense. That’s possible.
**Lee Yong-ho:** Actually, it’s the most ideal system for young people to travel. There are some misconceptions. I really wanted to talk about that. As mentioned, there are cruises for kids by Disney. But those are kids. For example, if you go to Singapore, they only operate the casino for 2 or 3 days, or they have a club on the ship. They even planned things like that. For two days, an EDM party, a party ship. I actually went on a 100-day cruise, and there were many passengers who did that in the middle. Where do you go on a 100-day cruise? Is that the longest cruise? There are longer ones. Six months. Six months? A world cruise. It has a name. A 6-month world cruise goes to all the major ports in the world. How much is that? 35 to 40 million KRW per person for three months. It’s not just one ship going all the way. You keep changing ships for the world cruise. Going around the world, being fed and housed for three months for 35 million KRW. But if you just look at the numbers, 35 million KRW for one trip seems a lot. But if you break it down, it’s not that expensive. I did a 100-day cruise on the same ship. It was 35,000 tons, so there were about 1,000 passengers. Depending on the passengers, they might do it for a month or ten days.
**Host:** From where to where?
**Cho Seon-ju:** Starting from Japan, through Singapore, Colombo, through the Suez Canal, through the Mediterranean, then Iceland, the US, and even the Panama Canal. It went around the Northern Hemisphere. A 100-day trip. How much is that? For a cabin that’s not an ocean view, the lowest price was about 20 million KRW. 20 million KRW for 100 days? That’s not bad. Per person. But practically, it’s 128 days, and I remember about 60 ports of call. For a passenger, the time spent on the ship is too long. Sea days, the journey on the high seas for 4 or 5 days at a time. That’s probably why it’s hard to book in Korea. Then do you have to finish within 128 days? Or if you have a pass, can you use it all year? It’s up to you. Is it possible to say, “I’ll stay for 3 days or a week and then take the next ship”? If the departure schedule matches.
**Host:** I might try this when I get older.
**Lee Yong-ho:** But the time on the ship is too long. When you get old, the time at home is also long. As a side note, I was offered a world cruise escort once. World cruises don’t have 20 or 30 people going. 4 or 6 people. But even if the conditions are good, escorting 4 or 6 people for three months is really... no matter how good the conditions are... Speaking of which, what’s the episode you remember most from the cruise? It’s nothing special, but Westerners are very proactive. It’s just about responding to them. You got hit on. Yes, just eating together, and then eating at a restaurant after getting off. You must have just eaten. You almost had an international marriage. My wife doesn't know this story.
**Host:** Have you ever told her? “I was popular when I was an escort.”
**Lee Yong-ho:** But even when I was a guide before, I thought of it as an extension of work. What part of it was an extension of work? Okay, then what do you think is the advantage of a cruise?
**Lee Se-guk:** I think the mindset changes a lot. Mindset about life. How? It goes really deep into life. In living life, I came to feel more that every single moment is precious. I thought about that a lot on the ship. For example, I’m on that ship for several months, so it doesn't matter to me if it rains for a week. But for a passenger, they might think, “It could be like that, this is also an experience I can have on a cruise.” Or some might think, “I’m ruined, why is my life like this? There’s nothing to see. Even on a ship, I’m following the rain.” I met many people like that, and it made me look back on my own life. I realized I had a lot of time. So if I were to travel three times in my life, I would try going out to the sea twice. That’s how much I recommend it. Did your attitude toward life change? It changed a lot. How? I really value every moment. The difference between before and after the ship is huge. This moment right now. When people get off the ship, they say, “Thanks to the chef, I ate well. See you again next time.” But among them, I haven't seen anyone again. That moment is precious. That relationship ends then. I have to focus then. Every moment is precious.
**Host:** That’s why you opened your own restaurant after getting off the ship.
**Lee Se-guk:** Yes, originally I thought about being a chef on a ship for 10 or 20 years. Because I liked riding the ship and it suited me. But I gained that realization and got off. It became very earnest. When those guests said, “Chef, see you again. I want to eat your food again. I’ll come again next time.” I have to be somewhere for them to come. But on a cruise, I keep moving ships. They can’t find me. I wanted to meet my customers, so I got off. So the ship changed the course of your life significantly.
**Host:** Originally, when you first boarded the ship, you thought it would be your last job. Because it was good. And you even had a romance there?
**Lee Se-guk:** It’s in the past. Every day was enjoyable and romantic, so it’s more memorable. But the reason I decided to get off was that I had to prepare a place for my customers to return to. That was the biggest reason, and after I actually got off, quite a few customers exchanged contact info and came to my restaurant.
**Host:** Among the things you said today, that’s the most poignant. It touched me. Suddenly, our chef became philosophical. Pros?
**Cho Seon-ju:** I think a cruise is a combination of a hotel, an amusement park, and luxury culture. Something you can’t experience all at once in another world. You experience it all at once in a compressed way. And the space called a ship, when you’re floating on it, you can’t see anything around you. Looking at the deep blue sea, I think I became a lot more humble personally. I thought about how I could disappear from here and no one would know. I’m nothing. I’m just a dot in this world, but I should live more enjoyably and diligently today. You think like that on a ship. It’s fun. It’s never boring. Because there are programs for every hour.
**Host:** Author Gi?
**Gi Da-yong:** I describe a cruise as Alice in Wonderland. There are ports of call that only a cruise can go to, so you must try a cruise. For example, Alaska has Glacier Bay National Park, which is only accessible by cruise. You can see glaciers falling there. You can see icebergs melting and falling. It’s like looking at the Milky Way. Secondly, I also recommend Hawaii. Hawaii is made of several islands, so on a cruise, as soon as you open your eyes, you’re at Honolulu where Waikiki Beach is, the next day at Kauai, the next day at Hilo. 15-day Hawaii cruises were possible for $1,099. You take a plane and go there and try a cruise like that. And another one is the Eastern Mediterranean cruise where Santorini is. Santorini is an island. You have to go by ship anyway from Athens. So take a cruise to Santorini, and the next day you’re in Athens, then Italy. Instead of just going to Santorini, take a cruise route and see the surrounding islands too. Try it yourself. Then you’ll know a cruise is good. You’ll know what I mean.
**Host:** CEO Lee. How many times have you been on a ship at most in a year?
**Lee Yong-ho:** I’ve been on about 20 or 30 times. Once I go, it’s for 10 to 15 days. In terms of frequency, it might be few. Once you go, it’s 10 to 15 days, and you do that 30 times. You did it all year then. When I was really busy, I went a lot. So as I said, for Costa Cruises, I’m at the highest level. Because I rode it so much.
**Host:** You lead guests and ride often, and even had a romance during your breaks. As such a person, what’s the advantage of a cruise?
**Lee Yong-ho:** They explained it well, but first is cost-effectiveness. My favorite Mediterranean cruise is only $100 per night. A cruise is actually more cost-effective. Within that $100, all the services mentioned are provided. Simply put, a cruise is better. And as mentioned, you can go to new places that are hard to reach by land. You could go from Paris to Nice by train. But if you go by cruise, you can stop at various port cities in Western and Southern France and reach Nice. And if there’s no land product to go to Aix-en-Provence, or if you want to go to Rhodes Island, there’s no land product. Those are the places you can only go by cruise. It’s cost-effective, there are routes inaccessible otherwise, and you can get off and on in between. And there are many small cities that are hard to find with general products.
**Host:** Lastly, the most easily accessible cruise is the Japan route. Is the Japan route worth it?
**Lee Yong-ho:** I don't recommend the Japan route. Why? As a businessman. You have to have a good first cruise experience to come back. It’s not the best experience. I always say Mediterranean cruises are number one. The best recommendation as an expert is the Mediterranean. Why? It’s the most efficient way to utilize cruise travel. Moving is easy and you can utilize your time twice over. Where does the Mediterranean go? Western Mediterranean, Eastern Mediterranean. Spain, France, Italy are Western. Italy, Slovenia, Croatia, Greece, Turkey are Eastern. And there’s the Aegean Sea. You could move by train, but if you move by ship, all the advantages of a cruise are there. A Korea-Japan cruise, if a cruise line official hears this, it’ll be bad. People have a vague romantic idea about cruises. But when you board, the Japan route isn't enough to fulfill that cruise fantasy. If you experience a Japan route and think this is all a cruise is, you might not ride again. There’s something better. And you board with high expectations, but Young-hee from the front house is there, and Cheol-su from the back house is there. It’s not special. Everyone is Korean. On a Singapore cruise, people who came through a funeral service company are all there. The fantasy isn't fulfilled. Of course, I recommend Korea-Japan cruises as a second choice. Families can go in a short time. It’s practical, and to properly feel the cruise fantasy, the Mediterranean is the place.
**Host:** I’m completely opposite. Why? Because I cook. Food is half of a cruise. For Korea-Japan cruises, it’s familiar, so it’s more comfortable. But in the Mediterranean, Koreans are a tiny minority, so they don't prepare food for Koreans. So from a chef’s perspective, it makes sense. Cruises are as much as you know. The Korea-Japan route doesn't have much of a sense of heterogeneity. Everyone is Asian, many are Korean, and you can communicate. And since there are many of them, the food and programs are tailored to them. So after experiencing that lightly, if you think a cruise suits you, then going to a Mediterranean route like this... you can enjoy it more when you know how to enjoy it. I say this because I’ve seen people struggling too much. They come to the kitchen a lot. They look for gochujang and sesame oil. They ask for kimchi, gochujang, and soju.
**Host:** Lastly, what if there’s a typhoon on the ship?
**Lee Se-guk:** Even if there’s a typhoon, we eat. Even if there’s a typhoon, the restaurant stays open and I cook. No matter how big the ship is, it’ll shake if there’s a typhoon. Passengers might feel fear.
**Lee Yong-ho:** There’s a system called a stabilizer that holds the center, and the navigation timing considers all the dates very calculatedly. And the refrigerator seats are very strong, and the desk drawers are also made of strong magnets. When it shakes a lot, the Captain will tell you to stay in your room. And the ship will try to leave that area as quickly as possible. They quickly change the course. Change the course immediately, refund all tours, and head toward a sunny area. They take refuge. They don't push through a typhoon. They avoid it as quickly as possible and go elsewhere. This is a sightseeing ship. Even if they have to change the course, they go to a safe place. Safety is the most important, so they don't stay in a typhoon for 2 nights and 3 days. People have fantasies but also fears. They don't even operate the ship during that season. You don't need to be that afraid.
**Host:** Okay. That’s all for today. Where is the first site to visit? A cruise price comparison site. vacationtogo.com. This is a comparison site. And kayol.com. And CEO Lee, go to his company. Columbus. Columbus. Chef Lee, where is your restaurant? You have to come to the restaurant. It’s called Yumsori Eumjuyul in Yeomni-dong, Hongdae. Come for a company dinner. What’s the main menu? There’s Spanish food, steak, pasta. People call and ask for goat meat quite often, but there is no goat meat. Author Cho recently wrote a book.
**Cho Seon-ju:** I recently published a book called ‘Fell for the Sea, Cruise Crew Member’ through my one-person publishing company. ‘Fell for the Sea’. For people who want to be a cruise crew member? Yes, that’s right.
**Host:** Author Gi also published a book.
**Gi Da-yong:** The title is ‘Real Cruise Travel’.
**Host:** What’s it about?
**Gi Da-yong:** Cruise travel tips.
**Host:** Okay. What I’m most sorry about today is not hearing CEO Lee’s love story. We’ll have you on separately for that.
**Host:** Okay, that’s all. Thank you.