The following is a transcript of the provided video:
- ** - 00:19 (Kim Eo-jun):** Monthly Kim Eo-jun’s Kim Eo-jun. Fashion, Pastor Kim Hong-gi is here. Hello.
- ** - 00:52 (Kim Hong-gi):** Hello. No, I was really surprised that some people said they got eternal life because they were moved by the sermon last time. Ten years ago, I gave a lecture to Dior Pendants, and there was no reaction at all. The times are different, and the audience is also different. The audience of Monthly is sensitive to these things.
- ** - 01:29 (Kim Hong-gi):** And my voice impersonation of the pastor was fine, wasn't it? I was scolded by my senior pastor. He said, “Don’t make a mockery of a deacon like this.” Depending on the era, there are words that we know well, and then suddenly our heads get clear. There’s a word that’s been on my mind lately. I saw in the comments that someone called me a pastor who rebukes Satan. It’s the word ‘Satan.’ If you look up the meaning of the word ‘Satan’ on portal sites, it says things like ‘one who opposes God’ or ‘evil spirit.’ But that’s a religious interpretation. Etymologically, it means ‘accuser’ or ‘prosecutor.’
- ** - 02:00 (Kim Hong-gi):** Satan. Etymologically, it’s a being with the power to prosecute. So, he sits with his belly right in front of an individual. We often talk about a ‘demon's den.’ That word means the belly. He sits with his belly firmly on the ground, watching for any mistakes this guy might make. He’s determined to prosecute him if he catches even a small slip.
- ** - 02:35 (Kim Hong-gi):** Because the belly is so prominent, the pants always sag like hip-hop pants. As an expert, were those pants worn backwards or forwards? I really don't know. But from a tailoring perspective, it’s very difficult for such a line to come out unless they are worn backwards. I tried it at home because I’ve tailored pants before. That wrinkle pattern wouldn't appear on the thigh area if they were worn normally. So, I kept thinking about that. Many important words came up: Satan, belly, pants. I just shared the etymology.
- ** - 03:52 (Kim Hong-gi):** Okay. Who is it today? It’s Saint Laurent, Yves Saint Laurent. For my generation, Saint Laurent means socks. YSL socks. I wonder if they still have them. They don't these days. They took back all the licenses. Since we talked about Dior last time, let’s talk about the unmatched designer who became Dior’s successor at 21 after he passed away. So young.
- ** - 04:30 (Kim Hong-gi):** He became the head designer for Dior? Yes, head designer at 21. But what’s amazing is that he won first place in a fashion competition at 18 in the dress category. The person who came in second was Karl Lagerfeld, who later revived the legend of Chanel. The guy who wore the high collar? Yes, the one who always wore sunglasses and a ponytail. He didn't look good at all. He looked like a turtle. He was called the dandy of modern times.
- ** - 05:30 (Kim Hong-gi):** When he came in second, Saint Laurent came in first. Dior was already a big house. At that time, Brunhoff, the editor of the Paris edition of Vogue, recommended him. He told Dior to scout and nurture this guy. A 21-year-old? Yes. But when Dior saw him, he fell in love. A genius recognized another genius. What was truly surprising was that after Dior died, he became the head designer at 21. But ‘head designer’ is an American term. In French, they used the term ‘Premier d'Atelier.’ There are dozens of sewing rooms in the Dior house in Paris. He was the head person responsible for inspecting every piece of clothing. I watched a documentary on Lagerfeld before.
- ** - 06:18 (Kim Hong-gi):** He would do all the stitching, and finally, Lagerfeld would say, “This is no good,” or “Raise the hem.” That was his role. But to become a Premier, it usually takes 20 years. You have to do a collection every year and be strictly evaluated to barely become one. But he reached that position at lightning speed. Dior chose him. Dior even called Saint Laurent's mother to his office and said her son would likely be his successor. And amazingly, about 40% of the clothes in the collection Dior did just before he died were already made by Saint Laurent. So, as soon as Saint Laurent entered Dior, he became the head?
- ** - 07:42 (Kim Hong-gi):** A year later. A year after entering. But shortly after, Dior died. And there was no one with his level of skill and aura to succeed him. In the midst of that, the CEO named Boussac, the wealthy guy I mentioned before, held a press conference and officially selected him as the successor. The story that will unfold from now on is that although Saint Laurent was Dior’s successor, he didn't inherit Dior’s philosophy. He began to reject the clothes that looked like flower buds, with corsets, made like a house whose structure could never be changed. He believed the future of fashion for our era was in the streets. He started to declare that he was tired of making grandma's clothes. Dior, who rose to fame with his corsets, was different. Saint Laurent thought the line was no longer necessary. For us humans, style is more important. Fashion revolution comes from the attitude of wearing clothes. Therefore, clothes should become cheaper. So he decided to make ready-to-wear. Will they just leave him alone?
- ** - 08:35 (Kim Eo-jun):** Let me share one thing I know. Yves Saint Laurent changed to Saint Laurent about 10 years ago. Yes, they rebranded. So, I once went to a Saint Laurent store in Paris. I didn't like it. Because there were no sizes. You have to be fit. You need the limbs of an elementary schooler. Your shoulders are wider than I thought. They don't fit. There are no sizes. Each brand has different lines of clothing they focus on. Still, how can they make clothes only for middle schoolers? It’s very skinny. I was quite displeased. That's all I know about this brand.
- ** - 10:18 (Kim Hong-gi):** Saint Laurent is an innovator who brought about a revolution in fashion. Actually, the reason I decided to talk about Saint Laurent this time is that there is something that overlaps with the recent political situation. Since Saint Laurent was an innovator, he had to make his philosophy known. He had to hold many press conferences. Saint Laurent and his same-sex partner, Pierre Bergé, who ran the business on his behalf, were the masters of doorstepping in fashion history. Truly, the way he answered the major French media like Le Monde or L'Observateur, his style, his attitude, and his gaze were so different from a certain vague person lately.
- ** - 11:41 (Kim Hong-gi):** They both liked doorstepping, but the content was very deep. Many words are coming up today: Satan, belly, pants, doorstepping. Let’s look at his early days. The place where Saint Laurent was born wasn't France. It was Oran, a beautiful port city in Algeria, which was a North African colony. He was born into an extremely wealthy family. His father, Charles Saint Laurent, owned a company equivalent to Dongbu Fire & Marine Insurance and also had a nationwide chain of movie theaters. How rich must he have been? He was born as the son of such a family. He had an older sister and received lots of love from his mother. He would rip his mother's clothes to make clothes for dolls. But he was gentle, soft-spoken, and introverted. And he was gay. There’s a unique sentiment among Europeans from Algeria. They were called ‘Pieds-Noirs.’ What does that mean? ‘Black foot.’ I don't remember why they were called that. But the novel ‘The Plague’ by Camus is set in this city, Oran. It's like Busan for us. He must have had the sentiment of colonial Africa. The colors or the designs. But he was super rich.
- ** - 12:44 (Kim Hong-gi):** In his early days, he lived with his identity as a gay man hidden, and he came out in 1991. He must have had the sentiment of a social minority from the start. As you said, Saint Laurent was a designer who could interpret clothes from the perspective of a minority because he was one. He was able to express his philosophy because of that. Actually, Dior paid a lot of attention to the use of models in fashion shows. If you look at fashion shows even now, they are mostly white women. There are Black and Asian models, but they are still very rare. You said you were displeased with Saint Laurent because it was too skinny. He demanded his models be very skinny. As a result, models died of anorexia, so they eventually made a law not to put such pressure on them. Not long ago. Surprisingly, Saint Laurent already addressed social minority issues, racial diversity, and respect for people with diverse bodies in the 70s by using Black models, twins, and female models with alopecia on the runway. He can be seen as a very progressive person.
- ** - 14:00 (Kim Hong-gi):** He was a minority and progressive. He knew how to empathize with the weak. He grew up in Algeria and came to Paris at 18. He won first place in a competition and was scouted immediately. Before being scouted, he did attend a school. It's the most famous fashion school in Paris, the Chambre Syndicale de la Haute Couture. Those who make traditional couture learn tailoring techniques there. It’s an educational institution that teaches tailoring techniques accumulated over hundreds of years. But when Saint Laurent went there, he found it too boring and uninteresting. He dropped out after three months. Formal education didn't suit him. His skills were so outstanding that the Vogue editor picked him up. That must have played a part. Established patterns and order didn't educate him. He only spent three months there and just went with the sentiment he absorbed from his hometown during his childhood.
- ** - 15:42 (Kim Hong-gi):** However, Dior is the top fashion house. Could one individual change that organization and shatter the tradition that had been followed until then overnight? It must have been incredibly frustrating. In the process, he looked for an outlet. Saint Laurent did many interesting things. He wrote and illustrated a comic book, a French version of ‘Crayon Shin-chan.’ The title was ‘La Vilaine Lulu.’ Lulu is a 10-year-old girl. Fashion companies often have a lot of overtime. At that time, there was a fellow designer named Praille. When the bell for overtime rang, it was boring, so he would roll up his suit pants to his knees and wear a tutu, a ballet skirt, even though he was a man. And he would wear a straw hat, commonly called a ‘canotier,’ like the gondoliers in Venice, and dance. For those working overtime, it was a relief. I know that feeling well. He got the idea from that and created the character Lulu. Surprisingly, this comic book was translated in Korea. It came out in Korea around 2006 or 2007.
- ** - 16:51 (Kim Hong-gi):** He saw his colleague working overtime, messing around in designer clothes, and expressed his whimsical imagination in a comic book because he had no other outlet. But it’s not at the level of ‘Crayon Shin-chan.’ It’s almost Satanic beyond being whimsical. It’s bizarre. At that time, the relationship between a teacher and a student was very hierarchical. We also wore black school uniforms in the past. We see it in movies, “What does your father do?” and then the teacher would hit the student. It was no different in Paris. It was very hierarchical. He overturned that in the comic. Lulu would punish the teacher, making him stand with his hands up, and embarrass him. The existing social order was completely overturned, at least in this comic. He was introverted, but he wanted to resist the violence and norms demanded by the social order of the time. He couldn't do it in reality, so he poured his resistance, subversion, or the cruelty and revenge within him into the comic. It must have been interesting. But there were scary parts too. When her friends ostracized her, she would set things on fire. He expressed what he couldn't do in reality.
- ** - 17:58 (Kim Hong-gi):** The content was interesting and touched the sentiments of the oppressed youth of that time. So, Françoise Sagan, who wrote novels while taking drugs and moved female college students in Korea in the 80s, recently came back into the spotlight. She went to Dior and persuaded them not to leave the manuscript alone and to publish it. In 1967, the book finally came out, and the following year, the May 68 revolution broke out in France. It was in line with that trend. It was a comic that fit the trend of the younger generation resisting the established order after the World Wars.
- ** - 18:40 (Kim Hong-gi):** He became the head after only a year. But Christian Dior passed away. How did he manage alone? He had the skill to do it. He was the head. I mean, what about the direction? That's the most important thing. For the first two years, from '57 to early '59, he stayed at Dior. He made some small changes to Dior’s traditional lines. He took out things like shoulder pads and the stiff parts, similar to corsets, but still maintained Dior’s flower-like lines to some extent. Then, a major incident occurred. In the 1960 Spring/Summer collection, the collection’s name itself was ‘Beat.’
- ** - 20:10 (Kim Hong-gi):** What was it? He was inspired by the clothes of the rebellious youth living on the outskirts of Paris, who felt abandoned and frustrated by the highly industrialized society. They wore black leather jackets and rode motorcycles, like bikers, and wore boots. He made a collection inspired by those ‘Beatnik’ youth. Christian Dior was originally a place for the wealthy. Since he did that, what would the elegant and sophisticated ladies of that time think? “What is this? How am I supposed to wear this?” They were very flustered. Imagine how many complaints poured in. The management immediately thought, “This won't do.” This guy was too focused on street fashion and trying to give the lead in fashion to those street youth. They felt that letting him continue his philosophy at Dior would threaten the existence of their house.
- ** - 21:06 (Kim Hong-gi):** Sales must have dropped significantly. Of course, they plummeted. The CEO called him. He couldn't fire him right away because they had a contract. They gave him a tenure, a period of time. He was allowed to stay during that period. He couldn't fire him, so he made another proposal. At that time, the independence war broke out in Algeria, which was a French colony. The Algerian War. He suggested, “How about participating in the war?” He meant enlistment. If he joined the war, he could show some patriotism that Dior had to the French people. He was from Algeria, and they told him to join the Algerian War? The mental damage must have been huge. As soon as he was dragged to the military training center, he suffered a nervous breakdown. He grew up there, and his friends were there, and many people were killed then. And hundreds of thousands of French soldiers were drafted there. He couldn't have been in his right mind. So, he was hospitalized at Val-de-Grâce psychiatric hospital as soon as he went in. He received electroconvulsive therapy and drug treatment.
- ** - 21:58 (Kim Hong-gi):** Now, they had a very good reason to fire him even though he had a contract. Due to mental illness. Like someone who looked for an excuse and a reason to prosecute. They finally found a reason. Boussac fired him using that excuse. And at that time, it was really unfortunate. Because of that war, Saint Laurent struggled with drugs all his life. Killing so many people was not something that was in his mind at all. The Algerian War was very brutal. The French soldiers from Algeria fought for France, but the French army was killing their brothers and sisters. As they became independent, it was initially a protest, but it turned into a war. France didn't recognize it as a war because they considered Algeria French territory. They called it an ‘operation,’ a suppression operation, while the other side called it an independence war. Their perspectives were completely different.
- ** - 23:36 (Kim Hong-gi):** It was similar to the Vietnam War. Was it a national liberation war or the defense of freedom? It was also similar to Indochina. 250,000 people were injured, 25,000 died, and 2.7 million French soldiers went to Algeria. This is unimaginable. A million Algerians died. Moreover, there was the Paris Massacre, which the French tried to hide. Many Algerians were already living in France at that time. They protested in the middle of Paris, and about 10,000 people were killed. I’ve researched that incident. An apology for that was only made very recently. Saint Laurent, who grew up in Algeria and knew the language, must have been shocked. French soldiers fought against Nazis and returned, only to find themselves being Nazis in Algeria. So, some French soldiers even joined the Algerian side. Then, De Gaulle appeared and said, “Algeria's fate belongs to Algerians.” That was the turning point.
- ** - 24:40 (Kim Hong-gi):** Returning to the story, they fired him using his hospitalization as an excuse. Then, his lifelong partner, Pierre Bergé, appeared and sued. For wrongful termination. He filed a lawsuit against Dior. They received 680,000 francs in settlement. And those who knew about Saint Laurent's idea for ready-to-wear were the Americans. A private financier in the U.S. who made a lot of money in the used car business invested heavily. Mark J. This guy invested, and finally, in 1961, the Yves Saint Laurent fashion house was established. Thus, Saint Laurent finally gained a foothold to liberate himself from the philosophy of clothes dominated by Dior and the monopoly of Haute Couture.
- ** - 25:30 (Kim Hong-gi):** He brought liberation from Haute Couture fashion. But this is very important. Most people don't think much about clothes. Haute Couture is a garment made with the highest level of stitching. You must invest at least 200 hours to make an evening dress. To be such a house, you must have your headquarters in Paris and hold at least four fashion shows a year to be qualified. Clothes are made within that institutional framework. The problem is the concept of Couture itself. He announced the bud line, the A-line, the H-line. What is this? It's like a thematic garment that condenses the designer's thoughts. The problem is that Couture's influence was so strong that the designer made the clothes in a complete state, from top to bottom, even the coat. People had to buy them and wear them exactly as they were, without any change. You couldn't touch them. It was a complete set. “Wear it exactly as I made it.” “How dare you touch the clothes our master made!” “Wear it exactly as our master designed each stitch.”
- ** - 26:35 (Kim Hong-gi):** How uncomfortable is that? And it's very expensive. Saint Laurent thought, “I'm bored and uninterested in making clothes for the rich. And I saw many contradictions in the fashion industry in Couture. Shouldn't clothes be popularized? I want to give people the right to edit their own clothes.” He declared at a doorstepping that his ultimate dream was to design clothes that could be worn together. He was very smart. This became a big deal. When he announced this philosophy in Le Monde, it was an act of completely destroying the foundation of the Haute Couture industry, which was the ultimate vested interest. “How dare you not wear the clothes our master designed as they are and try to edit them as you wish?” This is ‘mix and match’ in the fashion world. “How dare you have the right to edit?” This is ‘Power to the People.’ Give people the power to wear clothes in the mix they want. This is great. Saint Laurent's greatest achievement was giving the power to those who wear the clothes.
- ** - 28:50 (Kim Hong-gi):** He gave the power that used to belong to producers to consumers. The optimal consumer Saint Laurent thought of was someone who could object to the producer. Someone who could ask for a new design. He dreamed of the democratization of fashion. Correct. But after Saint Laurent died, why did they make the sizes so small? That's because your size is too big. Why did they imprison people in small clothes? Saint Laurent's spirit was completely the opposite. He liberated fashion from oppression. He continued the path of liberation. He didn't follow the clothes of the high-class bourgeoisie or aristocrats. He thought about the coats that farmers or sailors, who were inseparable from our daily lives, wore in harsh weather conditions. Pea coats with snap buttons, or trench coats. He thought, “If we can change these so that women can wear them, wouldn't we be able to achieve women's liberation through clothes?” He announced this at a doorstepping too. It was a huge sensation. Men's work clothes for specialized jobs? Yes. The lower class. Ordinary people. He said in Le Monde that the elegance of our era should flow from high to low and be democratized.
- ** - 30:20 (Kim Hong-gi):** He’s a cool guy. He took the dirty work clothes of the lower class and turned them into women's fashion. In 1966—note this down, you must remember this—Le Smoking. It’s not a cigarette. It’s a tuxedo suit. Traditionally, it was a suit for men. He transformed it into evening wear for women. Tuxedoes were for men with power. They gathered together and smoked cigars. The smell of cigars is very strong. They wore tuxedoes to prevent the smell from getting on the clothes underneath. That's why they called it ‘Le Smoking’ in France. How do I know this? It’s amazing. Le Smoking wasn't just a garment; it was a kind of text that explained the revolutions that would follow. Those who study humanities use the word ‘text’ a lot. What does that word really mean? It means a well-woven fabric. So, the innovative garment made of well-woven fabric became a mirror reflecting the era. People might ask, “What’s so great about women wearing pants?” Pants suit.
- ** - 31:41 (Kim Hong-gi):** Feminists would have supported it, but I also think that when women wear men's suits in a feminine way, they look very sexy to men. That's right. Because he was a sexual minority, he might have had the eye to see that. Women might have felt differently, but from a man's perspective, a well-designed women's suit is very sexy. He saw that. Tuxedoes also emphasize the shoulder line. Why do men's clothes emphasize the shoulder line so much? Because the shoulder line symbolizes a man's power and rational ability. Women who have seen men with wide shoulders and back say they are sexy. That’s not learned; it’s instinctive. Saint Laurent saw the sexiness in women wearing tuxedoes, which people before him couldn't see.
- ** - 33:16 (Kim Hong-gi):** He saw that sexiness. And he had an ideal image of a woman. A woman who drives to work in the morning. A woman who reads the morning paper, understands the flow of the era, and can object. A powerful woman with authority. He imagined a woman who tries to win the power that men had monopolized. Most men would think, “Oh, she’s so successful, she’s wearing the clothes I wear, I can’t have her.” They feel intimidated. So they don't want it. But Saint Laurent, as a gay man, could just see such a woman as she was. He thought it was cool. Sexy. He didn't think he couldn't have her if she reached a higher position; he just thought she was cool. Being a sexual minority and being born in Algeria contributed to this. Saint Laurent said in an interview that he hoped to create a new image of a woman through Le Smoking, and most of all, he wanted to discard the traditional values that claimed eroticism was the virtue of women's clothing. For him, a woman was not an object of sexual desire. In this era, announcing such a philosophy through doorstepping caused a lot of controversy but also gained a lot of sympathy. Two years after announcing Le Smoking in '66, the May 68 revolution broke out. But the May 68 revolution didn't happen out of nowhere. Various tensions in society were already rising. I’m surprised that French women felt political power later than I thought. It was only after World War II that they gained it. Later than us. It was only in 1965 that they could open a bank account in their own name, and in 1967 they could finally buy birth control pills to control their own bodies. It was only in 1970 that women could claim rights for child-rearing. It was like that throughout Europe. In the midst of that, Le Smoking appeared. It was truly surprising.
- ** - 34:58 (Kim Hong-gi):** So, he wanted cool women. But within that word ‘cool,’ there’s sexiness. He could see that. There was even a role model for Le Smoking. People don't know this, but those who like modern art know this painter's name, Niki de Saint Phalle. She was a close friend of Saint Laurent. She always wore pants, a white shirt, a large tie, and a jacket. That was her signature look. Saint Laurent saw that and thought it looked cool, which led to Le Smoking. It must have been a sensation. It was a society where people couldn't imagine women wearing pants. At the Louvre Museum, there’s a glass pyramid made by a company called Saint-Gobain. Even until 1969, women were forbidden from wearing pants in that company. They could wear pants to and from work when it was very cold, but once in the office, they had to change into a skirt. Pants were considered a completely inappropriate item for women. It was considered disrespectful. Like coming out in your underwear. But Saint Laurent announced this Le Smoking and kept varying it every year. As a result, in 1971, the ban on women teachers wearing pants in French schools was lifted, and an era of freedom where they could stand on the platform in pants began.
- ** - 36:35 (Kim Hong-gi):** He was a person who had a lot of social influence. Not just in fashion. I like him. You used to hate Saint Laurent clothes. Make them a bit bigger. He was a fashion revolutionary. Dior’s clients lived in the 16th Arrondissement of Paris, the wealthy bourgeoisie. Saint Laurent's sentiment was not there. It was with the poor students and scholars, and those who protested against the Vietnam War and listened to jazz music in the Odéon Theatre. The Left Bank of Paris. ‘Rive Gauche.’ From the Middle Ages, scholars had classes in Latin at universities. So, the place where they had classes was called ‘Rive Gauche’ (Latin Quarter). He decided to set up his sewing room there. Not on the Right Bank or Montparnasse. Rive Gauche. In 1966, he opened the first ready-to-wear boutique in Rive Gauche, where people could buy individual items and combine them. His idea was truly revolutionary.
- ** - 37:37 (Kim Hong-gi):** “You guys match and wear the clothes.” To the people on the Right Bank, they were just poor kids. But from the late 60s to the 70s, the youth emerged as the main characters of history. Fashion and the era coincided. “Let’s make clothes for them.” Those poor students wore turtlenecks, which became a symbolic garment of existentialism. Their way of dressing and their attitude became a lifestyle and entered the fashion scene. This was a huge change. It's similar to how Ivy League fashion became mainstream. The student's way of dressing became a lifestyle. Just as we see Sinchon or Hongdae as the birthplaces of fashion. And then he said at a doorstepping, “Couture is the clothes of those who lack the courage to face reality and look for comfort under the name of tradition. Now their clothes will go into museums.”
- ** - 38:50 (Kim Eo-jun):** He spoke like a pastor. I thought about doing it in that tone. But Saint Laurent has no connection with pastors. However, looking at the sentiment of the youth at that time, during the May 68 revolution, the employment rate was very low, and the era offered very little compared to their expectations. Society was already full of established powers, and these young people were too weak to cause a crack. They wanted a soul, but they couldn't have one in that era. They worked mechanically as the organization wanted. A certain woman’s rap, which captured this sentiment, is very popular lately. ‘Soulless Jo.’ I imagined what it would be like if her rap was performed at the Rive Gauche boutique in 1966. Doing a rap this time? This rap actually contains the deep sentiment of Saint Laurent for the youth of that time.
- ** - 41:00 (Kim Hong-gi):** I’ll try to capture the sentiment of ‘Soulless Jo’ and express the frustrated heart of those youth after the 1968 revolution. “Everything's wet, from head to toe, it's all wet. Wet with Saint Laurent. Gingham check, denim jeans, it's all here. Pick and choose, you are the protagonist of fashion here. This is probably Rive Gauche-che-che-che-che! Bang!” This is from Everland. “Everything's wet! This is probably wet! This is here!” I’m not good at rapping, but it perfectly matches Saint Laurent’s sentiment. The sorrow of the youth of that era. The word ‘Soulless’ itself is how youth live today. They do what the established generation asks. They give guidance at the amusement park. They do the guidance, but if they put their whole soul into it, they’ll get burnt out soon. They’ll be exhausted. They do the rap. They do the job they’re told to do, but they say, “I’ll do it my way. But I won't give my whole soul.” That subtle point. People in their 40s and 50s find it hard to understand this sentiment of the young. In the 70s, Saint Laurent's fashion captured this. Follow Saint Laurent's guidance. You just need to wear those clothes.
- ** - 42:40 (Kim Hong-gi):** I understand now. He was a fashion revolutionary. When we talk about the May 68 revolution, it was a failed revolution, but it was a global revolution. I read the records of the May 68 revolution very closely while studying Saint Laurent. Because his clothes were inseparable from that revolution. Through the May 68 revolution, the structure of French society didn't change. The existing power wasn't completely overturned. It was a failed revolution, but people say it advanced culturally. Many progressive scholars in Korea say that today. The May 68 revolution didn't just happen in Paris. It happened in London, Berlin, throughout Europe, Japan, Panama, Venezuela—it was a huge event that sparked 1,681 student movements across the globe. Although they couldn't bring down the established system, the discriminatory relationship between men and women was readjusted by 80%, and over 70% agreed that labor unions should have more power. Finally, sexual liberation occurred, and democratic relations between parents and children were readjusted, affecting over 64%. Our ‘386 generation’ missed this. They had a social and cultural change, but we only had political change because we were fighting against the regime.
- ** - 43:57 (Kim Hong-gi):** Someone wrote an article about why Korea skipped the May 68 revolution. It was because of our participation in the Vietnam War. With 320,000 young people there, it was almost impossible for the new leftist thoughts to penetrate the ‘Red Complex’ society. It was the Park Chung-hee regime. The world that the May 68 revolution created finally arrived in Korean society 50 years later. We were in a hurry. We were fighting against the regime. So, while fighting against the regime, our internal culture became more conservative instead. They couldn't overturn the system, but they created a social and cultural change. Philosophers like Lacan, Deleuze, Foucault, and Roland Barthes weren't able to get positions in universities until the May 68 revolution. It was the same in fashion and architecture. I must talk about Chanel again. There was an architect who had a huge influence on Chanel, Adolf Loos. He wrote an essay. “I want to build a minimal house, but the world only wants houses full of decorations. No matter how much I shout, I can’t win against this era, but I believe that what must come will come.” In 1931, he published a book titled ‘Trotzdem,’ a German conjunction meaning ‘nevertheless.’ It’s the same conjunction that Professor Park Gu-yong mentioned before. The world changes through people who bump into it like that, ‘nevertheless.’
- ** - 45:10 (Kim Hong-gi):** Saint Laurent did that. He did it within the established fashion business. And there was one man who remained Saint Laurent's lifelong partner. I must talk about this man. Saint Laurent's life was more than 50% about this man. When the May 68 revolution broke out, Saint Laurent did a doorstepping again. “I saw the revolution on that street. I believe the young people are right, and I believe society will go in the direction of their thoughts. Fashion must be a revolution. Vive la jeunesse!” It meant “Long live the youth!” Saint Laurent was able to have such a broad understanding of culture and art and respond sensitively to social phenomena because of his partner, Pierre Bergé.
- ** - 47:11 (Kim Hong-gi):** He was a fashion ideologist. Why does he make clothes so small? Partner. Bergé was his lifelong business partner and lover. He was the head of the Opéra National de Paris, a close aide to President François Mitterrand, the major shareholder of the newspaper Le Monde, and collected art pieces with Saint Laurent throughout his life. They were sold at an auction, and it's recorded as the greatest auction in history. I have the catalog, which costs 150,000 won. He was a great partner in many ways. The auction value was 729 billion won. Half of that was donated to AIDS research and the other half to their foundation. He was a person who practiced ‘noblesse oblige.’ Saint Laurent was successful because of Bergé. What he said about Saint Laurent explains everything about him. Saint Laurent died in 2008. Bergé wrote a diary for two years after his death, like a mourning diary. His evaluation of Saint Laurent is very good. Chanel did something bad here again. Saint Laurent respected Chanel. His role model was Chanel, not Dior. If Chanel gave women freedom, I would give them power. This was Saint Laurent. He understood his role exactly. As Saint Laurent's business went well, Chanel didn't stay still. She secretly approached Pierre Bergé and offered him three times his salary to work for her. Bergé didn't tell Saint Laurent about this until he died. He only wrote it in his diary. Bergé was a good man. As a lover.
- ** - 47:42 (Kim Hong-gi):** I’ll finish the talk about Saint Laurent today by reading a passage from his letter. Even if you miss everything we talked about today, just hearing this passage will help you understand Saint Laurent. Can I do it in a Gyeongsang-do accent? I must do it. I’ll read this and wrap up. It's so good. I hope some soft music plays. “I sincerely respected Chanel. You followed her, but you went further. Do you know that stepping out of the land of aesthetics to reach the social sphere is your greatest achievement? As people say, if Chanel gave women freedom, you gave them back power. You knew their power was being suppressed by men, and by making them wear your clothes, you gave strength to their shoulders. This is what you did. Le Smoking, the safari jacket, and the trench coat are the evidence. Every step toward androgyny was there. Just by wearing clothes and going out, women developed their femininity and removed the hurdle of eroticism. Therefore, Yves, you were the one and only genius in the fashion world along with Chanel. Other great designers like Dior, Balenciaga, or Schiaparelli only stayed in their aesthetic temples and didn't achieve social leaps. You did it. If clothes only remain the exclusive property of wealthy women, fashion will be boring. Eventually, you invented ready-to-wear. It's truly a revolution in fashion history. Bravo, Monsieur Saint Laurent.”
- ** - 47:47 (Kim Eo-jun):** He was a very smart man. I almost cried reading this. His affection was great, and his evaluation was accurate. You were moved by the lover. He wrote a mourning diary after sending his lover away for eight months. That book is out with the title ‘Letters to Saint Laurent.’ They were an intellectual couple. They knew the value of each other's existence. He was like his alter ego. Having such a person makes a huge difference. I’m envious of having such a lifelong lover, friend, and comrade. Lover, friend, business partner, supporter, and critic. It's a blessing to have one such person.
- ** - 48:42 (Kim Hong-gi):** While there is such a person, there is also someone who causes trouble. I’m a deacon, everyone. I’ll finish with a five-minute sermon. My dear believers, how have you been? I was leading the early morning prayer, and Deaconess Jennifer was there. After the prayer, I went to greet her. “Deaconess, I love you. Hello. Hello.” But she said ‘Hell’ to me. I was so surprised. I said ‘Hello,’ and she said ‘Hell.’ I went to her and asked what happened. She said she heard ‘Hello,’ but she misheard the ‘o’ sound. But at that time, I suddenly heard the voice of God in my ear. How can there be such a small difference between ‘Hello’ and ‘Hell’? We are living in such a society after the election. I didn't want to talk about that bar. It was made in a bar, at the Athénée Plaza. It's a bar! Why is he so obsessed with bar jackets? The word I want to share with you today is Galatians 6:9. It's a one-line verse. “Let us not become weary in doing good, for at the proper time we will reap a harvest if we do not give up.” We achieved political democratization, but we didn't achieve cultural democratization. We were still patriarchal fathers and older brothers. We didn't learn how to understand women's perspectives. Through this verse today, God is telling us that doing social good is nothing else. When we decide to become better democrats than yesterday, our lives change, and even if we are sometimes discouraged, if we don't give up, God will give us the true democratic republic that we want. Believe it! Hallelujah! That's all.
- ** - 48:44 (Kim Eo-jun):** He just blurted it out. That was Pastor Kim. Next service will be next month. Next month.