**Kim Eeo-jun:** Good morning, this is Kim Eeo-jun's World's End. This is Kim Eeo-jun. Adventure. Antarctica, the North Pole, Everest, the Bering Strait, and Greenland—all of which I have walked.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** I have crossed the five oceans in a yacht without power and flown over the Himalayas in a hang glider, and today, we are going underwater.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** I'm joined by Jang Ji-hoon, the Korean record holder in four freediving categories. Hello.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Hello, I'm Jang Ji-hoon.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Also, pro diver and instructor Park Ga-yeon is here. Hello.
**Park Ga-yeon:** Yes, hello. My name is Park Ga-yeon.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** The two of you are a couple, by the way.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Freedivers are rare, but a couple who are freedivers is even rarer. How many couples are there?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** I think there are about three couples.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** In the whole country.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** There's one in the Philippines, one in Egypt, and us.
**Park Ga-yeon:** Ah, who's in Egypt? Oh, the instructor. Yes.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You're the only one in the country...
**Park Ga-yeon:** Well, there must be some.
**Park Ga-yeon:** But there's another couple in Dahab, Egypt, and another in Bohol, the Philippines.
**Park Ga-yeon:** They live there and run freediving shops.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Dahab is a famous place for diving.
**Park Ga-yeon:** Yes, that's right. So the couple has already made a home there and is living there.
**Park Ga-yeon:** As far as I know, there is no other couple in Korea that goes to competitions together and trains for freediving together.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Let's say you're the only one in the country.
**Park Ga-yeon:** Oh, it's an honor.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Now that I hear it, you're the only ones in the country.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** We have a rare couple here. I have to ask this first.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** How did the two of you meet?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** At that famous place in Egypt, Dahab.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Dahab?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** There was a Blue Hole, so I went there to train and work as an instructor.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** What year was it?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** In 2016. I lived there for a while.
**Park Ga-yeon:** I was a traveler at the time. I had planned to travel for about a year.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Backpacking?
**Park Ga-yeon:** Yes, backpacking. Freediving was something I only knew from the movie *The Big Blue*. And I wasn't even going to go to Dahab, but my plans changed.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Plans change when you travel.
**Park Ga-yeon:** Yes, so I thought I'd stay in Dahab for about two weeks, and I got a place to stay, and he was living in the house across from me.
**Park Ga-yeon:** There were more Korean travelers in Dahab than I expected. There were many long-term travelers.
**Park Ga-yeon:** One of them was this man.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** This man? This man was living there. Then, had you ever tried diving itself?
**Park Ga-yeon:** No, I couldn't even swim.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You couldn't even swim?
**Park Ga-yeon:** Yes, so I didn't even think about learning freediving, but the instructor here kept telling me to learn it because I would like it.
**Park Ga-yeon:** I asked him if I could learn it even if I couldn't swim, and he said I could.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** A diver who can't even swim.
**Park Ga-yeon:** But he said if you can snorkel with a mask, snorkel, and fins, you can learn to freedive. So I just went in without knowing how to swim, and I floated quite well. So I started learning.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** That's quite reckless.
**Park Ga-yeon:** I learned from this instructor.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Ah, you met as teacher and student.
**Park Ga-yeon:** There was no other Korean instructor besides Jang Ji-hoon. The terminology was difficult, and I thought I'd die if I learned in English.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** So you first met as an instructor and a student who couldn't even swim.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Then you should have just taught her.
**Park Ga-yeon:** That's why I confessed.
**Park Ga-yeon:** I thought I couldn't confess because he was my teacher, so I confessed.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You liked the teacher at first.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** At what point did you start to like him?
**Park Ga-yeon:** Actually, I liked him before I learned freediving, but I was a traveler and I had to leave.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** He was the guy next door.
**Park Ga-yeon:** We hung out together.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You met while traveling, and you were hanging out happily.
**Park Ga-yeon:** But I thought it was a one-sided crush, but it turned out to be a mutual crush.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** I liked her from the beginning too.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You should have said it first!
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Well, she was a traveler, so I couldn't say anything.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** I've heard too many details. So you stayed there?
**Park Ga-yeon:** Everyone we hung out with left one by one. I was there for two weeks, but it became two months, and then three months.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Because there was a man you liked. It's getting long. At what point and how did you confirm each other's feelings?
**Park Ga-yeon:** Well, the people we hung out with all left, and it was just the two of us, so people started teasing us. "What's going on between you two? Why are you always together?"
**Park Ga-yeon:** But we didn't deny it.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** What did Park Ga-yeon say first?
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Tell the truth.
**Park Ga-yeon:** I don't remember.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** What did she say?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** We went up to a stone mountain together.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** A stone mountain?
**Park Ga-yeon:** I think I just said I liked him.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** I've heard all the stories I didn't want to hear.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Actually, I liked her from the beginning too.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You should have said it first!
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Well, she was a traveler, so I couldn't say anything.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** I've heard too many details. So you stayed there?
**Park Ga-yeon:** At my age, why would I have a one-sided crush? So I was going to go to the Philippines to learn freediving more, after I stopped traveling, but after we confirmed our feelings for each other, we stayed in Dahab.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You didn't train for a single day.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You couldn't even swim, but you liked the man, and as you were freediving together, you became a pro.
**Park Ga-yeon:** Yes, that's right. I became an instructor. I trained for about a year and learned how to swim.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Can you swim now?
**Park Ga-yeon:** Yes, I can now.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You learned to dive first, then you learned to swim.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Now, Jang Ji-hoon, how did you become a diver? This rare freediver.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** In 2013, there was a very famous freediver named Guillaume Néry. He was a world champion.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** A documentary?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** I saw a video of him diving into the Blue Hole without breathing, and I became very curious.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** What were you doing before that?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Before that, I was an office worker.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** An office worker.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** I was doing AS service for office equipment.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You were doing office equipment AS, and then you became very curious. There's no middle ground in your life.
**Park Ga-yeon:** But he was born by the sea and grew up by the sea. He grew up in Mokpo.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** I was born by the sea too.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** I loved the sea so much that I went out to the sea every day.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** I did too. But I didn't become a diver. I'm afraid of the water. But you learned to swim naturally, and you learned to dive and skin dive naturally.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** But I couldn't skin dive. I just splashed around.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Just splashing around by the sea.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** I was confident in swimming. I swam in deep water, and I wasn't afraid of the water. Then I saw that a person could do that, and I went to the Philippines.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** That's unexpected. So you grew up by the sea, you weren't afraid of the water, and you learned to swim naturally. You weren't a competitive swimmer, right?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Just average.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You were just an average office machine AS person. You saw that documentary. "Oh my, I have to do that." You quit everything and went to the Philippines?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** I could only think about that, and there was nothing in between. Yes, that's how it was.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** For people who swam from a young age, the middle ground might be being a competitive swimmer then becoming a diver.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** There was nothing like that.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You are a Korean champion, right?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Yes, that's right.
**Park Ga-yeon:** But the current number one Korean woman freediver was also someone who did editing work, and now she's a very deep-diving athlete.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Book publishing and editing?
**Park Ga-yeon:** Yes, she also suddenly felt a sense of skepticism, went to the Philippines, and became like that. There are many cases of people who worked for large companies and fell in love with freediving and became athletes.
**Park Ga-yeon:** Of course, there are cases of swimmers doing it, but there are many cases where ordinary people encounter freediving and their lives change.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** I don't understand, but since you say so. Then, as soon as you saw that video, you thought, "I have to do that."
**Jang Ji-hoon:** I wanted to try it properly. Just once. I wanted to try going down deep.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You were watching a documentary after work, and you suddenly thought of that.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** I ordered snorkeling equipment right away and went out to the sea. "Oh, it's not working."
**Kim Eeo-jun:** What year was that?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** It was 2013.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Without any information?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Without any information. I tried to go in, but it didn't work. What's next? I heard there was a place where I could learn in the Philippines, so I went to the Philippines. After quitting my job.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** One day, after watching a documentary on the weekend, you quit your job and went to the Philippines. You just started like that?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** I wanted to challenge myself. Why was I curious? I wondered what it would feel like to go down 30 meters. So I quit my job and just started. But the center director told me, "I think this really suits you. Why don't you try working here?"
**Kim Eeo-jun:** It suits you. The center director told you to try it. You went to the Philippines alone, without anyone to guide you?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** It was my first trip abroad.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Your first trip abroad? To the Philippines? To learn freediving?
**Kim Eeo-jun:** How many Korean freedivers were there when you went there? In total.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** About five or six people.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You didn't even know there were only five or six people, you just wanted to try it, and you started. Okay. You just went for it. So you tried it, and it suited you?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** There were many parts that suited me.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** What parts suited you?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** When I go underwater, it's quiet.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** It would be quiet.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** It's like being alone.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** If you threw away your job and continued to do it, there must have been something that excited you or moved you. So you thought, "Oh," and kept doing it.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** There's no one around, and being underwater itself suited me well.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** I remember diving about 10 or 15 meters with just a mask when I was young because I liked swimming. Your body keeps floating up, and diving is hard. But for me, that diving was very natural. But when I go down to 10 or 15 meters, my ears start to hurt.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Equalizing. I didn't know that. And it feels good to see the things moving inside. It feels good, but to go further, you can't see the bottom of the sea. It's dark in some cases. It's completely pitch black.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** "That's scary." There was a boundary. Looking back at my childhood memories, that area is unknown and dangerous. But for you, is it peaceful and nice to go where you can't see?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Yes. The more I go, the more I want to go. I'm also curious about what it's like to go further down.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** After going over 50 meters, sunlight doesn't come in. Then you can't see anything. You can't hear anything. Is your heart at peace then?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Sometimes I'm afraid. I worry about coming up. Then that day's diving is a failure. If not, my body becomes very comfortable, and I feel like I'm becoming one with the sea, and I feel like I'm being sucked in.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** From some point.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** That's called freefall, and from then on, you start to freefall. Even if you don't splash around, you just go down?
**Park Ga-yeon:** As the buoyancy decreases, you just go down without doing anything.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** From how many meters?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** It's different for each person because of buoyancy. In my case, I swim down to 20 or 30 meters, and from 30 meters, I freefall.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You just go down?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** I go down to 100 meters.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You're the only one in Korea who has gone over 100 meters, right?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Yes, the first and only one.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** For someone who suddenly started one day, you've done quite well.
**Park Ga-yeon:** But the current number one Korean woman was also an editor, and now she's a very deep-diving athlete. She suddenly felt a sense of skepticism, went to the Philippines, and became like that. There are many cases of people who worked for large companies and fell in love with freediving and became athletes. Ordinary people encounter freediving and their lives change.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** I don't understand, but since you say so. Then, as soon as you saw that video, you thought, "I have to do that."
**Jang Ji-hoon:** I wanted to try it properly. Deeply.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You were watching a documentary after work, and you suddenly thought of that.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** I ordered snorkeling equipment right away and went out to the sea. "Oh, it's not working."
**Kim Eeo-jun:** What's next?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** I heard there was a place where I could learn in the Philippines, so I went to the Philippines. After quitting my job.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** One day, after watching a documentary on the weekend, you quit your job and went to the Philippines.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** I wanted to challenge myself. Why was I curious? I wondered what it would feel like to go down 30 meters. So I quit my job and just started. But the center director told me, "I think this really suits you. Why don't you try working here?"
**Jang Ji-hoon:** It suits you. The center director told you to try it. You went to the Philippines alone, without anyone to guide you?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** It was my first trip abroad.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Your first trip abroad? To the Philippines? To learn freediving?
**Kim Eeo-jun:** How many Korean freedivers were there when you went there? In total.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** About five or six people.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You didn't even know there were only five or six people, you just wanted to try it, and you started. Okay. You just went for it. So you tried it, and it suited you?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** There were many parts that suited me.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** What parts suited you?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** When I go underwater, it's quiet.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** It would be quiet.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** It's like being alone.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** If you threw away your job and continued to do it, there must have been something that excited you or moved you. So you thought, "Oh," and kept doing it.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** There's no one around, and being underwater itself suited me well.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** I remember diving about 10 or 15 meters with just a mask when I was young because I liked swimming. Your body keeps floating up, and diving is hard. But for me, that diving was very natural. But when I go down to 10 or 15 meters, my ears start to hurt. Equalizing. I didn't know that. And it feels good to see the things moving inside. It feels good, but to go further, you can't see the bottom of the sea. It's dark in some cases. It's completely pitch black. "That's scary." There was a boundary. Looking back at my childhood memories, that area is unknown and dangerous. But for you, is it peaceful and nice to go where you can't see?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Yes. The more I go, the more I want to go. I'm also curious about what it's like to go further down. After going over 50 meters, sunlight doesn't come in. Then you can't see anything. You can't hear anything. Is your heart at peace then?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Sometimes I'm afraid. I worry about coming up. Then that day's diving is a failure. If not, my body becomes very comfortable, and I feel like I'm becoming one with the sea, and I feel like I'm being sucked in. From some point. That's called freefall, and from then on, you start to freefall. Even if you don't splash around, you just go down?
**Park Ga-yeon:** As the buoyancy decreases, you just go down without doing anything.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** From how many meters?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** It's different for each person because of buoyancy. In my case, I swim down to 20 or 30 meters, and from 30 meters, I freefall. I go down to 100 meters.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You're the only one in Korea who has gone over 100 meters, right?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Yes, the first and only one.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** For someone who suddenly started one day, you've done quite well.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** I've heard too many details. So you stayed there?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** I reached 100 meters in 2019, but I blacked out on the way up.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Blackout? Losing consciousness on the way up?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Yes, that's right.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** It's not an option, it just happens.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Yes, that's right. I reached 100 meters, but I used too much oxygen on the way up. I reached 100 meters, and I came up, and I've seen many documentaries. When you come up, you have to signal that you're okay. There's a judge. "I'm okay." You do that, and you give the proof that you went down and came up. But before that, my eyes rolled back and I was gone. Then I was pulled up by the safety team. I lost consciousness because of a lack of oxygen. When I woke up, it felt like I was waking up from a dream. So I failed because I lost consciousness on the way up. I just floated up instead of coming up myself.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** What happened after that?
**Park Ga-yeon:** At the time, there were expectations from Korean freedivers. "You're the only one." Everyone he met said, "You're going to 100 meters this time, right?" because it hadn't happened in Korea yet. All Korean freedivers were wanting a 100-meter diver to emerge. "It's only you. You have to do it." But that's related to the mental state. There was another athlete who was diving deep, and he also blacked out.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Both of them reached it, but they used too much energy because they didn't know if the other one would do it. They were nervous and used too much energy.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** So Jang Ji-hoon has the body to go down to 100 meters. Looking at that.
**Park Ga-yeon:** Yes, it's about maintaining that state of mind.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Peace of mind. We both failed, and no one particularly expected us.
**Park Ga-yeon:** And I took a break for about a year. I thought I wouldn't do freediving anymore. We came to Korea after living in Egypt.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Combined with the blackout, I thought I was someone who couldn't go over 100 meters. I was frustrated then. I felt sorry for disappointing others. So I quit freediving. Then we came to Korea. I didn't train for over a year.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Training isn't the important thing. Last year, the World Championship was held, and some sponsors appeared, so the financial burden was reduced. So I thought I should try again.
**Park Ga-yeon:** Last year, we selected a national team for the first time. "Okay, let's try again." So we started again last year. After a break, he went even deeper. His heart had changed.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** How did it change?
**Kim Eeo-jun:** He's the only one who has gone over 100 meters, and I'm the only one who can ask him. How did it change?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** You have to do it without thinking. Doing it without thinking is the best. Because you start to think too much. You get greedy, and you get obsessed with the goal. If you let go of that and focus on the process you're doing now, the result follows. At the World Championship, I didn't do very well at first because it had been a long time.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** The result wasn't very good then.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Rather, a month later, I needed time to adjust to the sea. The water pressure, the feeling of pressure from the water. So it was hard at first. The next day, I went down 95 meters on the first day. "Oh, this is the feeling."
**Kim Eeo-jun:** What feeling?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** The feeling of being completely immersed. No stray thoughts at all, and going down was enjoyable. Not hard, but peaceful. Like being one with the sea.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** So the next day, I challenged 96 meters. And on the third day, I thought, "I can do 100 meters this time," and I challenged it.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You said the record is 102 meters.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** 102 meters was a month later, at another competition. I increased it a little more. Once I broke 100 meters, I could go into the 100-meter range from then on. I can go to 100 meters whenever I want. Easily.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** So it's a matter of the mind. Your body didn't suddenly change in between.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Once you've been to a certain depth, you can go again. It's a matter of the mind. "I don't think I can go." If you think like that, you can't go. The fear disappears. "Can I really do it? Will I have an accident on the way up?" That kind of fear and stray thoughts disappear. Because I've been there.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You think you might die on the way up?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Yes.
**Park Ga-yeon:** But there aren't many cases of people actually dying. Not many, but there are. In a competition a long time ago.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** How do people die?
**Park Ga-yeon:** Oxygen supply to the brain is cut off and they lose consciousness. And after that, they have to wake up. Many people blackout. But since they lose consciousness underwater, their breathing might not return when they come up, or water might get into their lungs.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** At 100 meters, the water pressure is huge.
**Park Ga-yeon:** It's 11 atmospheres. 11 times that of the surface.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Then what happens to the body?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** There's a mammalian dive reflex.
**Park Ga-yeon:** Mammals, when they perceive a situation where they can't breathe, their heart rate drops, and blood gathers in the organs related to life support, like the lungs and the brain. It protects the lungs and gathers blood in the brain for oxygen supply. And the blood vessels in the extremities, like the arms and legs, constrict. Metabolism also drops. So they can hold their breath for a long time.
**Park Ga-yeon:** When they go into the water, the body automatically knows. So for ordinary people, their heart rate drops by about 15%, but for athletes, if their usual heart rate is in the 70s, it might drop to the 40s.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** It beats very slowly.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Very slowly. It's not something I control, but my body reacts.
**Park Ga-yeon:** We're not dolphins or whales. So blood gathers in the organs that need it. The lungs will shrink from the water pressure, but this blood protects the lungs. Instead, it doesn't go to the fingertips well. So when you move while holding your breath, your arms and legs feel very heavy with lactic acid. Athletes overcome that and come up.
**Park Ga-yeon:** Accidents happen on the way up. At the end, when oxygen is low, they usually lose consciousness. They lose consciousness underwater. They might inhale water.
**Park Ga-yeon:** But what's interesting is that not everyone has it, but the airway constricts. That's also a reflex. To prevent water from entering. So when they lose consciousness in the water, their airway constricts, and they can float up without water getting into their lungs. But if that doesn't work well, water gets into their lungs and they might die. They go down and come up knowing that, and fear arises in the process.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** It's different for each person, but various thoughts come to mind.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You don't talk much.
**Park Ga-yeon:** He doesn't usually talk much, but he's talking a lot today.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** When negative emotions arise, I suddenly think, "Why am I doing this?" In the dark sea, swimming down, I think, "Why am I doing this? Can I come back up? My legs hurt so much." Because of the mammalian dive reflex, lactic acid builds up. Like when you run a lot, your legs hurt. But it happens in a short period of time. It's supposed to happen after a long time. Diving 100 meters, it happens even after only 5 meters. If you move while holding your breath, lactic acid builds up quickly in your body. If danger is accompanied, it turns into fear. "I might die like this."
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Fear can arise. When? When I'm at a depth I've never been to before, I think I might blackout on the way up. It's out of my control. And the sea conditions can't always be good, so if there's a strong swell or current, I think, "I might blackout." I've only blacked out once. There were people assisting me.
**Park Ga-yeon:** Even when training, people assisting must be there. You never dive alone. A boat is usually waiting, and there's emergency oxygen.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Park Ga-yeon, who couldn't even swim. What is your record?
**Park Ga-yeon:** My monofin record is 58 meters.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** If someone can swim but has never tried diving, can they go to 58 meters?
**Park Ga-yeon:** I think it would be a bit difficult. Up to 30 meters is possible without special training, but you have to train. Even for 30 meters. It can be dangerous. At the first level, the depth is usually 10 to 12 meters. Then 20 or 30 meters. Up to 30 meters, you need equalizing, which is pressure equalization. You said your ears hurt. It's pressure equalization, and if you're familiar with the technique of blowing air through your nose to push your eardrum, you can go to 30 meters.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Holding your nose.
**Park Ga-yeon:** Your eardrum is pushed in, and you blow air to push it back out.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You keep doing that as you go down?
**Park Ga-yeon:** You have to do it as you go down to avoid pain.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** When you dive?
**Park Ga-yeon:** You hold your nose and keep blowing air as you go down.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Is that how they do it in competitions too?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** In competitions, I don't use a mask. I dive with my bare eyes and use something called a nose clip. It's a clip that pinches your nose. That's a technique. If you're good at that technique from the beginning, you can go to 30 meters.
**Park Ga-yeon:** Like when you fly on a plane. You have to do that while holding your breath underwater. Some people aren't good at it. Anyone can go to about 30 meters. But after that, training is definitely needed.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** What kind of training?
**Park Ga-yeon:** Earlier, I mentioned the water pressure. Lungs shrink. If you move while your lungs are shrunk, your lungs can be damaged. So you need lung adaptation training, equalizing training, and so on to go deeper. There are people with lungs suitable for diving. In Jang Ji-hoon's case, his lungs are very large. An average male's lung capacity is about 4.5 liters, and a lung size of 6 liters is considered large. Jang Ji-hoon's is 7 liters. Large lungs are advantageous.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** It turns out you had large lungs.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** I didn't know that. I saw others diving, and my lungs led me.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You also have to practice holding your breath.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** We do something called dry training out of the water. We practice holding our breath a lot.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** How many minutes can you hold it?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Underwater, I can hold it for 7 minutes.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** 7 minutes? You're a fish!
**Jang Ji-hoon:** When I first started, it was 2 minutes. The condition for the beginner level is 2 minutes.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** It was 2 minutes?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** If you do the breathing method as taught and relax, almost anyone can hold it for 2 minutes.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Really? I tried it in a swimming pool and couldn't even do 1 minute.
**Park Ga-yeon:** Because you haven't learned the breathing method.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** How is the breathing method different?
**Park Ga-yeon:** It's a breathing method to relax. To lower your heart rate.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** How do you do it?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** In my case, I inhale for about 3 seconds and exhale for 6 seconds. If I repeat that for about 2 minutes, my pulse drops, and I'm physically stable. Then, I do a final breath, inhaling as much as possible.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** You do it strangely. Like packing. To get more air in.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** That's a fish. To take in more air. That's what athletes do. Can you do it one more time?
**Kim Eeo-jun:** That's amazing. In addition to the lung capacity you get from normal breathing, you're packing it in.
**Park Ga-yeon:** Yes, it's called packing.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Does that help?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** It helps a lot. Non-athletes also do this final breath, but they don't do packing. This is only possible when the diaphragm is flexible.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Can I control my diaphragm?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** The diaphragm becomes flexible with practice. As the diaphragm goes down, more air enters and the chest cavity expands. We also do diaphragm stretching.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Diaphragm stretching?
**Park Ga-yeon:** In yoga, there's a diaphragm stretch.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** It's not evolved for that purpose, but you're massaging it to make it soft and pushing oxygen into it.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** To go deeper.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Can Park Ga-yeon also do 7 minutes?
**Park Ga-yeon:** No, I can do about 5 minutes.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** 5 minutes is also a very long time. Then, how long does it take to go down 100 meters and come back up?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** It takes 3 minutes 10 seconds to 3 minutes 30 seconds, depending on the athlete.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** It's far.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Which is faster, going down or coming up?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** If it took 90 seconds to go down, it takes 90 seconds to come up too. It depends on the style, but some athletes like to go down fast. Usually, it's better to match them to be more comfortable.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** It's a fundamentally dangerous sport.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You shouldn't do it alone.
**Park Ga-yeon:** Never alone. Even if you don't learn it, it can be dangerous. You must follow the safety rules.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** I'm also curious about this. I saw it in *The Big Blue*, and there was a Russian swimmer-turned-freediver named Natalya Molchanova. She disappeared underwater. The story in *The Big Blue* also ends with him letting go of the rope and going into the water. If I had only seen *The Big Blue*, I would have thought it was a movie, but she also didn't come back from the water.
**Park Ga-yeon:** That's a true story.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** There's also a recent Finnish documentary. About going far under the ice. A Finnish woman went over 100 meters under the ice. I saw that on Netflix. I like these kinds of things.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** But as I was watching this, I wondered about the feeling of becoming one with the sea. I think there were people who felt that and wanted to let go of the rope and go into the water.
**Park Ga-yeon:** There might be. I feel as if I've become one with the sea. The sea accepts me. I feel like I could go into it.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** I haven't felt that.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** He wants to go up and eat pork belly.
**Park Ga-yeon:** I think people who are a bit depressed might feel that way.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** We're talking about becoming one with nature, and you're talking about depressed people.
**Park Ga-yeon:** Please edit that out.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Is there no one who says that? "I felt like I became one with nature at some point."
**Park Ga-yeon:** When I'm doing a freefall, or before a dive, I do a warm-up by holding a rope at 10 to 15 meters and staying still. When I do that, the water feels like it's warmly embracing me. And it's quiet, as he said. You can't hear people's voices, but you can hear the sounds of the sea. There are sounds that fish make. Listening to those sounds, my heart becomes very peaceful. So sometimes I want to stay longer. There's a breathing urge, where you want to breathe after holding it for a long time. Beyond that urge, I want to stay longer because it's so peaceful. It's true.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** There is such a thing.
**Park Ga-yeon:** Even though I have a breathing urge, it's a very peaceful state. My whole body is relaxed. That feeling is so comfortable that I want to stay longer.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** That's when you have to snap out of it. So someone else always has to be next to you.
**Park Ga-yeon:** There are many people who freedive because they like that feeling.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** I've felt it once while warming up too.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Why do you like it? Your wife said she likes becoming one with the water, hearing the fish sounds, and the peacefulness that makes her want to stay longer even though she needs to breathe. Why did you go 100 meters?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** All the tension in my body is released, and I feel like I can find peace in the water.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** A downgraded version of your wife's answer.
**Park Ga-yeon:** But I think he's good at freediving because he's simple. We actually talk about this. For someone like me who is sensitive and has a lot on my mind, I have to struggle to get rid of my thoughts while freediving. But he's a simple person. That's my opinion.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** The better you are at mind control... The better your mind control ability, or because you don't have a mind to control... Either way, the result is that your mind has to be simple.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** I've heard that.
**Park Ga-yeon:** My teacher told me not to think. Freediving doesn't work if you think too much. Look at Jang Ji-hoon.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** I didn't mean to invite you for this, but I wanted to talk about the profound world of freediving, the danger, and the challenge. But you have to have a simple mind. Large lungs and a simple mind. And his lungs are twice the size of others.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** I understand. My curiosity is suddenly disappearing. To stay underwater for 7 minutes, do you have to train a lot?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** I have to. It's simple. When I was training hard, I would wake up in the morning and do that training on an empty stomach.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You shouldn't eat?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** If you eat, the food presses on your diaphragm. So I do about 3 hours of breath-holding training and stretching on an empty stomach.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You wake up every morning and practice not breathing. How do you do that?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** There's something called a CO2 table. It's like an interval, repeating breath-holding for 8 sets. But as the breathing time decreases, it's a method of breath-holding training. And there's an O2 table, where you increase the breath-holding time. It's to build tolerance for low oxygen and tolerance for high carbon dioxide.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** So your body gets used to it. Through that long-term training, the time you can hold your breath in the water increases from 2 minutes to 3, 4, 5, 6, and 7 minutes. You practice enduring the time when the contraction, the breathing urge, comes.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Last year or this year, a world record of 24 minutes was set.
**Park Ga-yeon:** That's after breathing 100% oxygen. Then the breath-holding time becomes much longer. In freediving breath-holding records, you can't breathe 100% oxygen. So the athlete has to be at the competition venue an hour before. In case they breathe it secretly. If that person breathed normal air, it would be much less. The world record is now 11 minutes 35 seconds for static.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** 11 minutes. That's also a fish.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** People who do that only do that category.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** There's a static breath-holding category? Floating in a pool. That's not a sport, that's like a side show.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Fins for both feet, a fin for each foot. Then pull a rope and go down. Then the monofin category, becoming one with nature. Then the depth is much deeper when you have fins, right?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** The world record is 131 meters for fins and 102 meters for no fins. That record isn't being broken. It's a 30-meter difference between no fins and fins.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** It's amazing to go over 100 meters without fins.
**Park Ga-yeon:** The athlete who did 102 meters can't do it again. Just once. No one can break that record.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** When was that record set?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** In 2018.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Jang Ji-hoon, you said there were 5 or 6 people when you started. How many are there now? Enthusiasts or athletes.
**Park Ga-yeon:** We can't even count the enthusiasts anymore.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Now?
**Park Ga-yeon:** There are many scuba diving clubs, but there are also many freediving clubs.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Since when?
**Park Ga-yeon:** As Dahab, Egypt became famous among travelers, many people started learning.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** "Many" means 1,000?
**Park Ga-yeon:** More than 10,000. Nationwide, there are probably more than 10,000 now. In Gapyeong, there's a 26-meter-deep diving pool. On weekends, it's packed with freedivers. Korean people seem to like this freediving.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Park Ga-yeon, although it was because of a man, you fell for freediving itself. Besides the fish sounds and peacefulness, what other charms are there?
**Park Ga-yeon:** I liked other sports too, but for a sport to go beyond one's limits, freediving is a sport where you have to know your limits and yourself well. How your body is, how your heart is, how far you can go. You have to know those things clearly. And it works best when you do.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** It's a meditative sport.
**Park Ga-yeon:** Yes, so it's very different. You shouldn't compete with anyone. If you compete, you can't do it. It's not about competing with someone, but about how much I am. What my heart is like. You have to keep checking that. It's like yoga. Before I learned freediving, I was very sensitive and had a lot of mood swings, but after learning freediving, I've changed as I observe my state. My life has changed.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You've become someone who observes yourself.
**Park Ga-yeon:** Personally, I like that so much that I want to keep doing it until I'm an old lady.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** A sport that trains self-objectification. My state, whether I can do it or not.
**Park Ga-yeon:** "Today, I can't do it." Then you have to know your limits quickly and not be greedy. If you're greedy, you'll definitely get hurt. Because it's directly related to my life, I have to constantly observe myself objectively. "If I go beyond this, I'll have an accident." You have to know that. You draw that line, and that influences my daily life outside the water. So my heart has become much more peaceful.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** I don't expect this kind of answer from Jang Ji-hoon. I'll just ask if he agrees.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** I agree. You change as you freedive. You shouldn't rush in freediving. You'll die. Greedy people can really die.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** How many athletes are there?
**Park Ga-yeon:** It's hard to train in the Korean sea because the depth doesn't come out easily. You have to take a boat far out, and the water is cold and there are currents. The current in the Korean sea is strong. The Jeju sea is usually used, but when it's not good, the current is really strong. So it's hard to train in Korea. So they have to go abroad. To the Philippines or Dahab, Egypt. They have to stay long-term where the water is warm and deep for the record to follow. So compared to the huge freediving population, the number of athletes is not that large. And there's not much prize money for this sport. If the prize money is high, people might dive deeper than they can because of greed.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** People could die while being greedy for prize money.
**Park Ga-yeon:** So they can't offer large prizes. The people who made the competitions know the danger well. So they make less money.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Then it's about honor. If you can't make a living with the sport itself, how do you live as an athlete?
**Park Ga-yeon:** By teaching, or doing other work, or getting sponsorships from equipment companies. Usually, there was almost no cash support, but last year, with the big competition, we received a large amount of support for the first time. But it's not enough to cover all the costs.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** It's because you love doing it. I should help you with some money. You have four Korean records, and you're teaching and saving money, and then you go when you have enough.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** How about abroad?
**Park Ga-yeon:** In France or Italy, it's become a major sport. They do expensive watch commercials and get large sponsorships. Adventurers, people who challenge extremes. But we haven't formed that culture yet. Enthusiasts are here, but the pros who want to participate have to save up their own money and go, and the prize for winning is 2,000 euros.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** That's only for that competition. Usually, they just give equipment. Then the athletes in this world must be very close.
**Park Ga-yeon:** We're close. We cheer for each other, and all the athletes in the world know each other's levels. They worry about each other. Because it's not a competition. Even if you win, there's no prize money. Only famous athletes in France or Italy get sponsors, and everyone else probably trains and competes with their own money. They go when they've saved up 12 million won. Is that the cycle?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** I have some sponsoring companies. Domestic equipment companies. Gear, fins, equipment I need. I receive them as items, and from last year, I started receiving cash for training costs.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** It's probably in the range of a few million won.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** 4 million won. My first cash sponsor. Before that, they just paid for competition entry fees.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** 500 euros. It's more like pocket money. But in Italy, they highly value the challenge of adventure itself. People who go to the bottom with their bare hands. They value them highly. But in other countries, they save up 12 million won and go. "Oh, you're here again? World champion." Everyone is a friend.
**Park Ga-yeon:** Everyone knows Jang Ji-hoon in Korea. And Jang Ji-hoon's wife, Park Ga-yeon. I also go to competitions. So we go together. Sometimes I coach him. Don't let each other float away! My wife teaches and the husband goes to competitions with that money.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** No, that's not it. Our finances are separate.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Park Ga-yeon seems like a good instructor. Jang Ji-hoon doesn't seem like he'd be good at teaching.
**Park Ga-yeon:** So he's doing other work. Something unrelated to diving. He teaches when there's a request.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** I should find you some sponsors. You need 12 million won a year. For about 3-4 months. That would be a lot of help.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** I've watched many documentaries. I thought, "That's amazing. They're fish." And I wondered about their mental state. I have to help you.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** I also wondered about this. Among those who lost their sight, there are people who click their tongues, and the sound hits a wall or object and comes back. They read the topography with that sound. Like a bat using ultrasound. They've developed that ability. But for people who go underwater and hold their breath for 7 or 10 minutes... Through training, you're becoming something between a human and a fish.
**Park Ga-yeon:** We didn't think a human could go this far, but as the records have increased dramatically, we're making the mammalian dive reflex stronger, like a whale or dolphin.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You're training your body to be suitable for diving through the mammalian dive reflex. And the reason you do this despite developing techniques is that you find peace in the water. Many people are attracted to that as a hobby. It's a very inconvenient hobby. And you need a special space. But with over 10,000 enthusiasts, people are attracted to it. But it needs 12 million won.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** It's close to meditation. Meditation, self-objectification, tempo control, and not crossing the line. It's a sport that changes the person. Let's try to find a sponsor. I'll have to do something. I was going to talk about adventure, but I should change it to helping.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** If I want to try it, where should I go first?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** It's right to learn from an instructor.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Where does Park Ga-yeon teach?
**Park Ga-yeon:** Mostly at the diving pool in Gapyeong.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** If someone hears this and wants to learn freediving, and says they want to learn from Park Ga-yeon, the income from that goes to the husband.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Jang Ji-hoon holds all four Korean records. Park Ga-yeon is teaching. But the accounts are separate. If they say they heard it here, the tuition fee is saved for the competition fee. I understand. Does that company still give 4 million won?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** I haven't contacted them yet.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Did you go with this company's logo?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Yes, I went with the logo.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** We'll try to find 4 million won through our show, so put our logo on and go down.
**Jang Ji-hoon:** That's possible.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** Where? On your back? Your chest?
**Park Ga-yeon:** Anywhere you want. Even on the monofin.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** For 4 million won, how many will you put?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Front and back, and on the monofin.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** 4 million won was the only cash sponsorship, including airfare? That's cheap. We'll give 4 million won in cash.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** When is the next competition?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** I'm leaving in August.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** We have to hurry. Philippines?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Cyprus. I'm planning to stay for 3 months.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** You need at least 3 million won a month, so you need 10 million won. Have you saved 10 million won?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Not all of it. I'm saving it bit by bit.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** It's not right that you can't prepare for the competition because of money. This isn't what I intended for this interview, but things happen. Jang Ji-hoon, what is your next goal?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** I was 4th in the world rankings last year. I want to get into the top 10 in total records.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** How much is that?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** About 116 meters.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** 116 meters? How many people on Earth have gone down that far?
**Jang Ji-hoon:** Fewer than 10 people.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** So you want to be in the top 10 in the world. Since you're doing it.
**Kim Eeo-jun:** We've only managed to secure about half. We'll try to do something. I can't guarantee anything. I'll just try. I met the only freediver couple currently in Korea, Jang Ji-hoon and Park Ga-yeon. We'll try to send them to the August competition. Thank you.
**Jang Ji-hoon, Park Ga-yeon:** Thank you.