(Music)
**Speaker 1:** Monthly Kim Eo-jun, I am Kim Eo-jun. "Classic, Mid-air, Unidentified Object." Professor Yoo Kwang-soo is here.
**Speaker 2:** Hello, I'm UFO Yoo Kwang-soo.
**Speaker 1:** Do they call you UFO in the academic world now?
**Speaker 2:** Not even one person. But soon, at an academic conference in November, the president earnestly asked me to give a presentation on how to inherit and expand our classics in a modern way.
**Speaker 1:** You might be kicked out of the academic world.
**Speaker 2:** That will never happen. Anyway, the biggest problem with our classics is that we characterize them, fossilize them, and think about them roughly.
**Speaker 1:** That’s the only way I’ve ever learned it.
**Speaker 2:** Right. Those who have encountered classics through Monthly Kim Eo-jun wonder if they were this interesting. After I started the class this semester, a female student suddenly came to me and asked for an autograph.
**Speaker 1:** Wow!
**Speaker 2:** It’s the first time in my life that I’ve been asked for an autograph at school.
**Speaker 1:** She must have listened to Monthly.
**Speaker 2:** She said she listened to Monthly!
**Speaker 1:** I want to get an autograph too.
**Speaker 2:** So I signed the newly released Monthly Kim Eo-jun Part 1 and gave it to her.
**Speaker 1:** Usually, the person who receives the autograph prepares the book, but the professor was so moved that he prepared the book himself and gave it to her.
**Speaker 1:** What kind of work is it today?
**Speaker 2:** Today, it's about our country's lawsuits and trials.
**Speaker 1:** Oh, I know a little about lawsuits. I’m a quasi-legal person.
**Speaker 2:** I'm going to cover one story related to lawsuits and another one next month.
**Speaker 1:** Is it a trial record or something?
**Speaker 2:** Yes, there's a record of a trial. It’s recorded in the Annals of the Joseon Dynasty. It’s a very important story, so King Jeongjo even ordered to record and inform about this story.
**Speaker 1:** Regarding a certain incident, the King directly ordered to record this trial in detail.
**Speaker 2:** So, I will mainly talk about the records recorded by Yi Deok-mu, who can be called Jeongjo's confidant. He's a famous person. Compared to the Annals of the Joseon Dynasty, Yi Deok-mu's writing contains more about the situation, but the words are the same. What Jeongjo said, what the ministers said, it’s all the same.
**Speaker 1:** Then this isn't a novel, it's a perfect record.
**Speaker 2:** Yes, lawsuit novels are like fables where a squirrel sues someone. This is a real thing and a trial that actually happened.
**Speaker 1:** There must have been a special incident that was worth recording, so the King directly said, "Record the circumstances and the verdict of this case."
**Speaker 2:** Yes, it was a huge thing, and Yi Deok-mu was a great writer. When choosing four writers from the early and late Joseon periods, Yi Deok-mu is included in the late period. His writing is incredibly good.
**Speaker 1:** It's a rare record. A royal reportage. What’s the title?
**Speaker 2:** The title is "Eunaejeon."
**Speaker 1:** I've never heard of it.
**Speaker 2:** Well, you can hear it all at Monthly Kim Eo-jun. It's a story of a woman named Kim Eun-ae, recorded in the form of a biography. By order of Jeongjo.
**Speaker 1:** What kind of incident was it that the King directly said, "Record it in detail!" What kind of incident was it?
**Speaker 2:** There was a woman living in Gangjin. There's no mention of her father, but she lived with her mother. And there was an old woman named An-ssi.
**Speaker 1:** So Kim Eun-ae is the main character, she lives with her mother, and another character is an old woman named An-ssi.
**Speaker 2:** She was a former kisaeng. We've seen many, but this is a real person, so I'll call her the old woman from now on.
**Speaker 1:** Not a successful kisaeng.
**Speaker 2:** But usually, for a kisaeng to be successful, she should become a concubine and live out her old age or save a lot of money, but she couldn't.
**Speaker 1:** Okay, that's the case.
**Speaker 2:** Her personality was fierce, she was good at swearing, and she was rude to people.
**Speaker 1:** A harsh old woman.
**Speaker 2:** In "Jorakdam," there was an old woman who ran a tavern, and she even ran a tavern. This person couldn't even do that. Every time she opened her mouth, she badmouthed others. She was a problematic old woman.
**Speaker 1:** A very rough grandmother.
**Speaker 2:** According to the description, she had a skin disease all over her body and kept scratching, so people didn't like her. She would grab anyone and swear at them. Everyone shook their heads. This is very important. You have to understand this woman's character to understand this whole lawsuit and why Jeongjo told to write this.
**Speaker 1:** The village villain.
**Speaker 2:** This old woman usually borrowed rice and beans from Eun-ae's mother. Fermented soybean paste, salt, these were basics. These are the basics of life in the old days. She borrowed and ate things like that. I lived in the 70s too, but does anyone pay back when they borrow something? They just say they're borrowing it as a social courtesy.
**Speaker 1:** It's just a little bit of welfare.
**Speaker 2:** Right, she just ate it. But Eun-ae's family wasn't rich, so Eun-ae's mother couldn't give it every time.
**Speaker 1:** She didn't give it once, so...
**Speaker 2:** She gave a little bit sometimes. But sometimes she said she didn't have any and couldn't give it. This is always a problem. She wasn't someone who never gave, but since she didn't give once, this old woman completely flipped out. She got angry and said, "Why aren't you giving it! You people!" while holding a grudge.
**Speaker 1:** All the favors she showed before disappeared, and she thought the favors were her right, so she started getting angry.
**Speaker 2:** "What's wrong with that family!" and so on, she vented the humiliation of being rejected with words like that.
**Speaker 1:** A villain.
**Speaker 2:** But in the same village, there's the old woman's sister-in-law's grandson. There was a kid named Choe Jeong-ryeon, about 15 or 16 years old. But he's a kid, but think of him as a young man in his 20s by the standards of that time.
**Speaker 1:** He got married back then.
**Speaker 2:** This old woman gently lures him. She talks to him about lewd lust between a man and a woman and tells him dirty stories.
**Speaker 1:** She lulled and seduced him.
**Speaker 2:** After talking like that, she says, "Hey, you know Eun-ae, right?"
**Speaker 1:** Ah, so she's trying to get revenge now.
**Speaker 2:** Right, right. Since the mother didn't give rice, she's trying to get revenge on the daughter, Kim Eun-ae. "You know Eun-ae, right? How about you get married to someone like Eun-ae?" Then the kid smiles and says, "Eun-ae is beautiful and great, why wouldn't I?"
**Speaker 1:** The old woman is wicked.
**Speaker 2:** "Then it's done. You go around and tell people that you and Eun-ae are in a relationship and like each other. Then I'll definitely make the marriage happen." So she's blocking Eun-ae's marriage path.
**Speaker 2:** "I'll do that," and then, "Right now, I'm dying because of this itchiness all over my body. The doctor says I only need about a thousand coins for medicine. Bring some money. If this work goes well, think about it." "Sure, why would that be a problem?"
**Speaker 1:** She was a person who lived like that.
**Speaker 2:** But one day, this old woman says to her husband, "Oh my, Eun-ae, you know..." She even has to deceive the people close to her.
**Speaker 1:** She started making up rumors.
**Speaker 2:** "Eun-ae, you know Jeong-ryeon, right? She's completely fallen for Jeong-ryeon and asked me to be a matchmaker. I let them meet at our house last time for Jeong-ryeon."
**Speaker 1:** She started making up rumors while lying that they already met.
**Speaker 2:** If you want to deceive, you start with the people close to you. They are truly wicked people. So I explained the character for a long time earlier. "Oh, I let them meet, but Jeong-ryeon was caught by the old woman's husband, and Eun-ae jumped over the fence. Oh my, what should I do?"
**Speaker 1:** It's specific. The details of the lie are important.
**Speaker 2:** When the husband heard this, he said, "Nonsense! The old man knows the old woman's character. And he knows Eun-ae. And he knows Jeong-ryeon is a useless kid. Jeong-ryeon's family is poor, and as for Eun-ae, no matter how much they've declined, aren't they a yangban family? Don't even say such things!"
**Speaker 2:** But the thing about rumors is that they spread through the whole village in an instant.
**Speaker 1:** I know what it is. Starting from high school, people would come to me and say, "Hey, who's meeting whom? Who's dating whom?" Isn't badmouthing the start of rumors? But I've never gone to someone else and said, "He's like that, she's like this." I've never badmouthed anyone in my life. I didn't understand that. I publicize political talk, but since I was young, I've wondered why they come to me and talk about others. Is that fun? But as I get older, the essence and the fundamental emotion of this badmouthing is jealousy.
**Speaker 2:** Exactly.
**Speaker 1:** Exactly. It's about comforting and consoling oneself through the sight of others failing. But there are people with extraordinary rumor-producing power. Those people's way of living in the world is to spread rumors and make the listener an accomplice. So a wicked solidarity is formed. In that way, they destroy the person they aim for. There are people who live like that, and you must never get close to them. Never.
**Speaker 2:** This old woman was a classic example.
**Speaker 1:** An example. So, there's no way she only borrowed from Eun-ae's family. Since Eun-ae's family wasn't rich, she must have borrowed from here and there. People didn't want to get involved with this old woman. They'd rather give her some rice and send her away. But when a family that didn't do that appeared, she got angry.
**Speaker 2:** She had no physical power, no property, and no status, so she destroyed the opponent with this rumor-producing power. Truly wicked.
**Speaker 1:** Truly a bad person. That's why I said, never get close to them. When these people come and tell dramatic stories that satisfy your voyeurism, you become an accomplice together. And then that person runs away, and only the accomplice gets hit. The world works like that. You must never get close to them. Because if I react, they take that reaction somewhere else and sell me.
**Speaker 2:** Exactly. You're exactly right. So, the rumor spread like wildfire, and the path to marriage was blocked.
**Speaker 1:** That was the goal.
**Speaker 2:** So Eun-ae was struggling, but some people said, "Would smoke come out of a chimney if there was no fire? What the old woman said, it must be right." And some said, "Even if it's not true, why would you marry such a noisy woman?" It became like that.
**Speaker 1:** The old woman gains power that way. It becomes power. "Don't mess with me. If you do, I'll bury you with rumors." Later, after some time passed, she'd use "I sent him" as a weapon.
**Speaker 1:** You must never get close to them. It's used as a tool for power struggle in relationships.
**Speaker 2:** She uses it as power within that ecosystem.
**Speaker 1:** Never get close to them. But if you have to meet such a person, there's one way. It's the method I use. The story that comes to you shouldn't go out of your mouth. That's the most important thing.
**Speaker 2:** It's a story that could happen in everyday life.
**Speaker 1:** But it's a very extreme case. A very wicked case.
**Speaker 2:** There was still a person of conviction in that village. A person named Kim Yang-jun stepped up and said, "It's not like that. I'll marry that woman." This is a real person.
**Speaker 1:** Even though such rumors spread, he said, "What are you talking about? I know Kim Eun-ae, she's not that kind of person. I'll marry her."
**Speaker 2:** Good. So they get married. It seems resolved, but this old woman doesn't give up. She's not an ordinary woman.
**Speaker 1:** "They should have failed to marry!" When they married, she thought, "Look at this!" and turned the engine more.
**Speaker 2:** The revenge engine became very strong. New slanders kept spreading and spreading. "Do you know why that man married her?" It's written in the original text that rumors you couldn't even bear to hear came out. "Why would he marry such a woman? That man can't act like a man."
**Speaker 1:** That's what I'm saying!
**Speaker 2:** This man's marriage itself proved that the story about Kim Eun-ae wasn't true. So she had to flip that, so the man had to be strange too. The man also became a target of attack.
**Speaker 2:** "I first promised to be a matchmaker for Jeong-ryeon and tried to get medicine money. But that girl Eun-ae suddenly broke the promise and went to marry someone else. Since I didn't get the medicine money, my illness got worse. This girl Eun-ae is my archenemy." What is this all about?
**Speaker 1:** She did everything she wanted to do, and after the marriage, she said they played around with Jeong-ryeon. Such stories grew, so all the old and young people in the village blinked and wondered what kind of wicked thing that was.
**Speaker 2:** Not because they believed the old woman, but because she told so many people, they must have talked among themselves even without her.
**Speaker 2:** If someone said, "It's not like that," the old woman would run to them and scream about how wicked and vicious Eun-ae was. This is the logic of a comment factory. At first, they'd attack if someone commented that it wasn't true. That's the way. So people in this village, if they tried to defend Eun-ae, she'd say, "You brat, did you also sleep with Eun-ae?" You can't win if she attacks like that. She silenced those who didn't believe it. Two years passed like that.
**Speaker 1:** For two years. Eun-ae lived in a world of malicious comments for two years. It's hell, hell.
**Speaker 2:** One day, Eun-ae finally makes a decision. "You die, I die." Out of resentment, she decided to slice the old woman's flesh piece by piece. This is called "neungji." Precisely, "neungjicheocham." "I must end this old woman." Because she could endure it if it was just her, but it's an insult to her husband and her whole family.
**Speaker 2:** If Eun-ae didn't take revenge when the old woman first did that, and if she had stopped, Eun-ae wouldn't have gone that far. But as you just pointed out, it's not a personal problem anymore, it's expanded to a family problem. It would be a big problem if she even had children. This became so serious and big that it couldn't be overlooked without being resolved.
**Speaker 1:** Seeing as there was an incident, it means she killed her.
**Speaker 2:** Yes.
**Speaker 1:** Did she kill her and run away, or did she stay there?
**Speaker 2:** She stayed there. That's the point. That whole story is written in the Annals of the Joseon Dynasty. She was prepared to die too. That's the key.
**Speaker 2:** Now what? In the early evening, she takes a kitchen knife, tucks it into her waistband under her skirt, and goes to the old woman's house. The old woman was preparing to go to bed, taking off her outer clothes and wearing only a skirt. Eun-ae enters the room with the kitchen knife and glares at the old woman.
**Speaker 1:** A thrilling reportage.
**Speaker 2:** "I'm worse than before. Take this knife!" Eun-ae said.
**Speaker 1:** What's the difference in their height or physique?
**Speaker 2:** You pointed it out exactly. That's the key. Eun-ae is small, and as it appears in the interrogation record later, she's small, fragile, and a child.
**Speaker 1:** The old woman.
**Speaker 2:** This old woman is strong and full of energy, like a strong-boned woman who even fights with men. She has some power. She's not an old woman, but more like a woman in her 40s or 50s. A sturdy woman.
**Speaker 2:** The old woman says, "A skinny and weak thing like you, what are you going to do?" She just thought she was threatening her. She'd been through that many times. "Stab me if you want!" Eun-ae rushed in and brandished the knife, stabbing the old woman in the left neck.
**Speaker 1:** She's attacking with the thought that she'll die too.
**Speaker 2:** The old woman also has a temper. She grabbed Eun-ae's wrist and shook it, but Eun-ae pulled it back and stabbed her somewhere else. A struggle broke out. The interrogation record, like our crime scene investigation today, has it all written down point by point.
**Speaker 1:** CSI.
**Speaker 2:** Where she stabbed, where she stabbed, it's all there. Stabbing the left shoulder... Because she's attacking with two years of resentment and the thought that she'll die here.
**Speaker 1:** She's attacking for her life.
**Speaker 2:** She stabbed her in eight places like that. Without even a chance to wash the blood, she said, "Now I'll go to Jeong-ryeon's house and take care of him too." Since he was the start. Jeong-ryeon must have been asked by the villagers if it was true, and he must have told a flat-out lie. He conspired and backed up the old woman. If she was alone, it wouldn't have had such an impact. "Yes, I had an affair with Jeong-ryeon," and Jeong-ryeon backed it up.
**Speaker 2:** So she's running there covered in blood. But Jeong-ryeon's time to die hadn't come yet, so she meets Jeong-ryeon's mother on the street. The mother cries and begs for his life, so Eun-ae, seeing the mother, who wasn't her target, feels her excitement subside. So she went back home. At that time, Eun-ae was 18 years old.
**Speaker 1:** She went back after the mother begged for his life. She didn't run away, knowing she'd be caught.
**Speaker 2:** Yes. The village head ran to the government office and reported the incident, and the Gangjin magistrate, Bak Je-sun, inspected the scene and the old woman's body. Seeing the situation, which was hard to believe was done by one person, he brought Eun-ae to the office and interrogated her. "Why did you stab the old woman? She was a healthy woman, and you're a weak girl. I can't believe you did it alone, so tell me the truth without hiding anything. Isn't there an accomplice?"
**Speaker 1:** She's so fragile, so someone else must have done it for her. This is nonsense. You might think Joson Dynasty lawsuits were sloppy, but they were quite organized and did everything systematically. They were systematic.
**Speaker 2:** She just said, "No, I did it alone."
**Speaker 1:** "A solo crime."
**Speaker 2:** Eventually, Eun-ae had a board around her neck, wooden shackles on her hands, which were heavy, and leg irons on her feet. She sat in the courtyard, but there was no sign of fear on her face, and she answered the magistrate clearly. I'll read exactly what Eun-ae said.
**Speaker 2:** "If a girl of the inner chamber is slandered, even if her body isn't defiled, it's the same as being defiled. The old woman was originally a kisaeng and slandered a girl of the inner chamber, so can this happen in this world? It was unavoidable that I stabbed the old woman. Even though I am an ignorant girl, if the rumor that I committed murder spreads, the office will surely kill me, so since I killed her yesterday, it's natural that I die today."
**Speaker 1:** "It's natural."
**Speaker 2:** "But the old woman is already dead, and there's no way to prove the crime of slandering others, so please kill Jeong-ryeon too. I took revenge alone after being slandered, so who else would have helped me?"
**Speaker 1:** "There's no accomplice."
**Speaker 2:** The magistrate sighed and inspected the clothes she wore when she killed the old woman. Even though he wanted to let her go in his heart, a murder case cannot be handled alone. If a person dies, it must go up to the King.
**Speaker 1:** There was a three-trial system.
**Speaker 2:** Yes, the three-trial system. It had to go to the Magistrate, then the Governor, then the King. Because it's a murder case, it goes up, and after the officials of the Ministry of Justice discuss it, the King makes the final decision. They didn't take a person's life lightly.
**Speaker 1:** It was very systematic. There was a legal system.
**Speaker 2:** It's definitely going to go up. Okay. He couldn't let her go on his own, so he wrote a report and sent it to the Governor. Governor Yun Haeng-won couldn't judge on his own either because it was a big case. He called and asked again, and Eun-ae gave the same consistent testimony.
**Speaker 1:** Consistent testimony.
**Speaker 2:** She said she did it alone, but this skinny and small girl doing that to a strong person, it makes no sense. The Governor had to send it up, but he hadn't yet. Why? If he sends it up, it's 100% execution.
**Speaker 1:** Death penalty, death penalty.
**Speaker 2:** Both the Magistrate and the Governor wanted to help her. Since it was clear that she was slandered, it's death if it goes up. But then, a great celebratory event happened in the country: Jeongjo's son was born. At such times, there's an amnesty. So he sent the records of the death row inmates' crimes to King Jeongjo at this time.
**Speaker 1:** The Governor was considerate. If I send it now, she might get an amnesty.
**Speaker 2:** So he sent it. Looking at the record, he wrote the words gently too. He was on the girl's side.
**Speaker 2:** The King looked at the record and felt pity and wanted to save her, but due to the importance of the case, he sent it to the Ministry of Justice and had the ministers discuss it.
**Speaker 1:** "Let the Ministry of Justice review it first."
**Speaker 2:** At that time, Chae Je-gong, who was a real person and the Prime Minister during Jeongjo's reign, gathered the results of the discussion and reported. It's all in the Annals. "Even though this incident was out of resentment, since the crime is murder, I cannot dare to ask for a pardon."
**Speaker 1:** "I understand, but since the crime is heavy, execute her." Because this is private revenge that bypasses the law. In a civilized country, revenge is done through the legal system. If private revenge is allowed, each person's emotional judgment becomes the final verdict.
**Speaker 1:** It's biased and dangerous. Most importantly, the final authority of right and wrong must be in the legal system and the King. But private revenge passes that authority. So the ministers naturally said it shouldn't be allowed. That's the safest.
**Speaker 1:** It's safe for them too. Otherwise, they have to take the responsibility.
**Speaker 1:** "Execute her" is the safest answer since it's an established system. It's not like he's dying.
**Speaker 2:** So the subtitle I chose today is "People who don't know incompetence and shame."
**Speaker 1:** "People who don't know incompetence and shame."
**Speaker 2:** People who don't even know that their incompetence is shameful.
**Speaker 1:** There are many such people these days.
**Speaker 2:** No, I'm not trying to say that. Anyway, after it went up to the King, a final decision was made. If she had been executed, this record wouldn't have remained.
**Speaker 1:** The King saved her.
**Speaker 2:** Yes, it's recorded in the Annals. Even Jeongjo's words are there. He said, "If a woman of virtue was slandered as lewd, this cannot be anything but the greatest resentment in the world. Usually, for a woman of virtue like Eun-ae, dying once is not a difficult thing."
**Speaker 2:** She was slandered, right? Then the easiest choice is to commit suicide. "Dying is rather an easy thing. But if this woman only dies, there's no way to prove her innocence, so she carved the flesh of that old woman and proved to all the people in the village that she wasn't defiled."
**Speaker 1:** Many women committed suicide in the Joseon Dynasty saying they were wronged.
**Speaker 2:** So he talks about cases in China. Because he needs to have authority. He talks for a while about someone who was born where and did what in China, and how she'd be praised as a woman of virtue. And then he brings in a Korean case.
**Speaker 2:** "In the old days, there was a girl in the Haeso region who committed murder, and it was similar to this case. At that time, the Governor asked for a pardon, and unlike now, the previous King accepted it and even commended her."
**Speaker 1:** He's listing precedents.
**Speaker 2:** Since he's the Chief Justice now.
**Speaker 2:** "As soon as that girl came out of prison, matchmakers flocked like clouds with a lot of money to marry her, and eventually she became the wife of a yangban. Doesn't this story still pass down? Now, Eun-ae endured the resentment and got married, but the slander didn't stop, and eventually she decided to resolve that resentment, so isn't this an even more difficult thing for a woman?"
**Speaker 1:** "The woman in the precedent committed murder before marriage, and the Governor asked to let her go. This girl tried to live after marriage but it continued for two years." He's talking like that.
**Speaker 1:** "It's a more serious situation, but she endured for two years." He's talking very logically. Jeongjo studied a lot.
**Speaker 2:** "Now, if we don't release Eun-ae, how will we enlightenment the public morals and the people's hearts? Therefore, I intend to pardon her." And he lists other cases. "That was also to enhance the morality of human relations and value spirit and integrity. Pardoning Eun-ae now comes from the same intention, so record Eun-ae and this case in documents and distribute them so people know the outline."
**Speaker 1:** So, a person at the top of a system that can't allow private revenge allowed private revenge.
**Speaker 2:** Just now, I skipped a case and said, "Record someone's case together." That's a man's story. A murder case of a man named Sin Yeo-cheok. He judged two cases together.
**Speaker 1:** "This case is also in the same vein."
**Speaker 2:** Yes, that story is also recorded in the Annals. There are men in this one. It's complicated, so I'll just call them older brother and younger brother.
**Speaker 1:** There were an older brother and a younger brother.
**Speaker 2:** While the older brother and his wife were working in the field, the younger brother was guarding the house. After they came back from work, the wife was looking through the grain chest and grumbled that two measures of rice and wheat were missing.
**Speaker 1:** "The younger brother was at home, but the wheat is gone! Something strange is happening." "Did you take it, or did you not catch the thief?"
**Speaker 2:** Then the older brother scolded the younger brother. "You stole my food, so aren't you a thief? Tell the truth!" He scolded his younger brother.
**Speaker 1:** "Did you take it?"
**Speaker 2:** But this younger brother was sick and lying in bed, so he stayed home instead of going to work. He was so wronged when he heard it. "Brother, can you do this to me over two measures of wheat?"
**Speaker 1:** He could have taken two measures of wheat.
**Speaker 2:** He probably did, according to the interrogation record. So as he was crying, the older brother said, "The thief is crying!" and as written in the original text, he took a pestle and hit the younger brother's back of the head.
**Speaker 1:** With a pestle.
**Speaker 2:** People in their 20s and 30s these days might not know. It's a bat. It's thicker than a baseball bat.
**Speaker 1:** A baseball bat with two ends.
**Speaker 2:** He hit the younger brother's back of the head with that?
**Speaker 1:** He'd die!
**Speaker 2:** So when the younger brother was dying, the neighbors swarmed in and said, "Stop, stop! What's this!" and tried to stop him. A neighbor named Jeon Hu-dal said in a kind way, "In the old days, they said they'd share even a bowl of grain, but you're doing this because your brother took some wheat?"
**Speaker 1:** Then the older brother rushed to that person and kept swearing. The older brother himself was a rogue.
**Speaker 2:** So he went home to avoid him, but our main character today, Sin Yeo-cheok, who heard the story... He's a neighbor, and he heard it and his face turned red. "Doing that to his brother over two measures of rice? And he even behaved badly to people who tried to stop him? That guy is not a human child." That's what's written in the original text.
**Speaker 2:** So he ran to the older brother's house, grabbed his topknot, and said, "Is a measure of wheat so precious that you fight with your brother? You hit your sick brother with a pestle and made him die, are you still a human child? You're worse than a beast! You can't be called a human anymore." He said something like that.
**Speaker 1:** "You brat, what do you care if I hit my brother!"
**Speaker 2:** As he shouted and rushed at Sin Yeo-cheok, Sin Yeo-cheok kicked him.
**Speaker 1:** He kicked him.
**Speaker 2:** He was hit in the stomach and crawled away, but couldn't get up.
**Speaker 1:** Intestinal rupture.
**Speaker 2:** He died the next day. He became a vigilante of sorts in the village. But the younger brother hit with the pestle didn't die.
**Speaker 1:** He didn't die.
**Speaker 2:** But the older brother who was kicked died. So they had to report to the office. Sin Yeo-cheok was taken to the office. So the King gave a long explanation about this too, and said to pardon both of them.
**Speaker 1:** He looked at what values they did it for.
**Speaker 1:** Wow. But the reason I chose the subtitle "People who don't know incompetence and shame" is that the core of the Eun-ae case isn't Eun-ae. Who's the problem? The Magistrate and his people.
**Speaker 1:** Because the villagers all knew that Eun-ae wasn't that kind of person. What's more important is that the old woman An-ssi's misdeeds were so noisy that it lasted for two years. What were the Magistrate and his people doing during that time?
**Speaker 1:** Public power was absent.
**Speaker 1:** And what the Magistrate and his people should have done is, unlike now, to enlightenment the public morals and etiquette. If there's an affair, adultery, or a fight between brothers, the person who intervenes and resolves it is the Magistrate.
**Speaker 1:** Now it's a civil case, so the parties should make it an issue and go to court, but back then, the office naturally had to do it. So, they neglected the work they should have naturally done for two years and left a woman named Eun-ae in pain. They didn't even try to call Eun-ae or the old woman and mediate.
**Speaker 1:** When brothers were fighting, where were the constables? The older brother is trying to kill his younger brother with a pestle. What the King wanted to say is this: "You brats! Because you didn't do what you should have done, the Eun-ae case and the Sin Yeo-cheok case happened! But why do you only care about that and ignore the original problem, you fools!" He probably wanted to say that.
**Speaker 1:** I see what you mean. This is a story about Jeongjo.
**Speaker 1:** Yes, it's a story about Jeongjo. Because the King thought about what justice was. For a King, "execute her" is the safest and easiest conclusion. Protecting the legal order is also important. And his authority is also important. He's not getting praised for saving those two people. He was an intellectual King. He thought deeply about what justice was and what the people were. And then he reached his own conclusion. And then he widely announced why he reached such a conclusion. "The role of public power wasn't done properly here. Because of that gap, they had to solve it privately. So this story is important, so record it in detail and let everyone know."
**Speaker 1:** He was an intellectual King. When we hear the words "morals and enlightenment," it's just words to us, but for the local officials, it's words that make their spines chill. "What did you do?" That's what he's saying.
**Speaker 1:** That point is brilliant. The lives of two ignorant people were nothing to the King. But he deeply considered whether those two people should live or die, and what justice the King should choose.
**Speaker 1:** Since he's a person trained intellectually, he's truly a great person. And he's maintaining his authority in front of the ministers. "Look at the precedents. I've looked them all up, you brats!"
**Speaker 1:** "Pardon them!" There's a sexy part. His grandfather Yeongjo sent his father to a rice chest and let him die. And this person's life was turbulent. He became King after all kinds of hardships. Even after he became King, assassins broke into the palace twice in the year of his accession and the year after.
**Speaker 1:** So he's a person who understands and embraces the position and perspective of the weak. He's 100% empathetic.
**Speaker 1:** Usually, Kings talk shortly and the ministers talk long. "I permit it." That's most of the Annals because they don't know much.
**Speaker 1:** But in the part I read today, it's all explained in detail in the Annals. This person saw his father die in a rice chest when he was in his teens, was kicked out of the palace, and his path to becoming King was blocked. He could have died.
**Speaker 1:** He survived and appointed people from Seoul and even told ordinary people to do business in the market. He was a King who knew the position of the weak.
**Speaker 1:** He had experience and he knew. That's why he could make such a verdict. Jeongjo is the best!
**Speaker 1:** We can see what kind of person Jeongjo was through this.
**Speaker 1:** So, the reason I titled it "People who don't know incompetence and shame" is that if he's this good, he can be the President.
**Speaker 1:** He has his own thoughts. You can't do this just by studying a lot. He's intellectual, but he was a person with a clear worldview. Because you'd think a King could do whatever he wanted, but actually he couldn't. This minister is annoying, that minister is annoying, etiquette is this and that...
**Speaker 1:** You know exactly. So they usually just summarized everyone's opinions and said, "I permit it." But here, they gathered, and he said, "No, you brats! I've thought about it deeply, and we should save her! If you have something to say, look, there was this in China, and this in the old days, and this under my predecessor." He lists them all.
**Speaker 1:** "And you say etiquette and morals are important? If you had done your job well, would this have happened? You dogs!"
**Speaker 1:** "Record it, you brats!" There's a lot of swearing in this. "Record it, you dogs! If you had done well, it wouldn't have come to this."
**Speaker 1:** An intellectual. Jeongjo is truly an attractive person. Of all the Kings in the past, there are only two I'd like to meet.
**Speaker 1:** That's impossible, so don't even think about it.
**Speaker 1:** One of them is Jeongjo. I just want to give him a drink. Because only a person like the Professor can see that Jeongjo is great through stories like "Eunaejeon."
**Speaker 1:** The human relations decision wouldn't have been easy. The circumstances are pitiful, but if you save her, everyone will take private revenge. That would have been the safest conclusion, but he flipped it.
**Speaker 1:** An intellectual. A King of Great Learning. Looking at how he said to leave a record, there must be many documents from the Jeongjo period. There's even a collection of Jeongjo's own writings. A King studying this much means he's working very hard.
**Speaker 1:** So I'd say, "You worked hard," and give him a drink.
**Speaker 1:** As a King, he should pay that price. Let's just live well ourselves.
**Speaker 1:** A King doesn't need to think this deeply.
**Speaker 1:** He doesn't need to. It's very attractive, this point. I like Jeongjo.
**Speaker 1:** Please love Jeongjo in the future.
**Speaker 1:** A detailed trial record of a murder case, which the King told to leave, but I found out why the King told to leave it. And I found out that Jeongjo was intellectually attractive. And only UFO Yoo Kwang-soo, who recognized that value... Finished! Thank you.
(Sound of car engine/driving)
(Music fades)