Absolutely! Here is the complete transcript of the audio:
** Speaker 1:**  Monthly Kim Hwan-soo’s Kim Hwan-soo here. Writing tools, the country’s best, the world’s top 5, strict Director Park Jong-jin is here.
** Speaker 2:**  Hello. This is Park Jong-jin.
** Speaker 1:**  There is one announcement. Last time I did pencils, didn’t I? With the consulting of Director Park Jong-jin, I contacted Dong-A Pencil. Cedar wood, 2B, no eraser, clean stamp. And as for basic engraving, I asked Dong-A Pencil if they could make pencils with these conditions. The response was that it’s possible. It’s possible. If this negotiation concludes well, next time, the pencils consulted by Park Jong-jin and planned by Monthly will come out.
** Speaker 2:**  Oh, and I have good news too. What is it? I went out on the broadcast and found the Oxtalky 50. Oh, so your daughter ground the Oxtalky 60 and made it small like this. But somebody who heard that only the Oxtalky 50 was missing on the broadcast said let’s exchange it for the most original one. So I exchanged it for the pencil I have. I brought out a lot of them and told them to choose whatever they wanted. So I finally got my hands on the Oxtalky 50. That person used it when they were in elementary school. It was something they used, so they said let’s change it. I guess my earnestness reached them through the broadcast. They said let’s change it.
** Speaker 1:**  I also received pencils that were mentioned on the broadcast. A whole bunch of Blackwing, Castel 9000, Staedtler came. What is this? A monthly subscriber sent them. I’d like to take this opportunity to say that others can send them as well. Thank you to the sender. Today is a story about ballpoint pens, but before we go in, I’m curious.
** Speaker 2:**  Oh, Charles? You’re quick. I got a lot of calls like that. People were curious. There was a scene in foreign news where Charles III was annoyed when signing documents related to his accession. Clearing the desk and yelling. He pushed away the tray with the pen. First of all, the desk is too narrow to sign. It’s too narrow to sign with a fountain pen. It’s a historic signing of the king’s accession, but I think the protocol officer was inexperienced.
** Speaker 1:**  The signing with the fountain pen didn’t look right. They should have cleared the tray quickly. Maybe it was the signing width of the queen. Maybe they only thought about that much, and if it were the queen, she would have done it elegantly even if there was something like that. But Charles is still inexperienced with that. It doesn't look good.
** Speaker 2:**  Second, he got annoyed. That’s not the same place. It’s a different place. It was the same day, but at a different place, he was annoyed because ink got on him while signing. If you look closely at the screen, Charles passes by without realizing it. But Queen Camilla always takes the pen from Charles and signs. If you look closely, Queen Camilla always uses the pen Charles used. She doesn’t have her own pen? From what I found, she takes the pen Charles signed with. From that, you can see that Camilla supports Charles well. Didn’t Diana do that? There’s not much data on Diana, but I don’t think there’s much about her taking the pen Charles signed with. From that, you can infer the relationship between Diana and Charles.
** Speaker 1:**  I always search regularly to see how those people sign and what pen it is. The queen has a pen she enjoys using the most. It was the Parker 51. The oldest user of the Parker 51 has passed away. As a fellow user of the Parker 51, I express my condolences on the passing of the oldest user. The queen used that Parker 51 a lot, and unusually, she didn't put the clip on the outside like this, but on the inside. There are many things like that.
** Speaker 1:**  Then what kind of fountain pen does Charles III use? Charles III seems to like silver. Silver. When I looked at him in his younger days, he was using a silver Parker fountain pen. There was a pen called Parker Premier that was produced from around 1983 to 1993. He used that, and then he used Montblanc. Montblanc Silver. He used Montblanc Silver for quite a long time.
** Speaker 2:**  But even though it’s a fountain pen his hand is used to, why did ink get on him? In my opinion, someone else must be managing it. He probably doesn't manage the pen himself. If he managed it himself, ink wouldn't get on his hand. Oh, so there’s someone else who manages Charles III’s pen. I think there was at that scene. Since he’s royalty, it’s possible. And if that person was the one who was in charge of Charles’ protocol before, they wouldn't have done that.
** Speaker 1:**  Maybe it was like this. It came out in the foreign news on the day of the funeral. They said they fired 100 employees who were serving Queen Elizabeth all at once. Oh, really? Then my inference has some credibility. Since he’s royalty, there might be someone in charge of writing tools. Since he signs a lot. But the queen’s writing tool was the Parker 51, but Charles III is Montblanc Silver. Montblanc Sterling Silver. Someone who hasn’t handled that didn't manage it properly and handed it over, and he signed and ink got on him and he got annoyed. This! I think that’s what happened.
** Speaker 2:**  And the protocol officer himself couldn't even clear the pen tray. So the person in charge of managing writing tools wasn't skilled. They should have thought about the space, the desk size, and the person in charge didn't know Charles’ size or the pen. That's right. You can understand those two happenings on the same day in different places like that. Director’s inference seems plausible. I only think about that while eating.
** Speaker 1:**  And the relationship with Diana. In the relationship too, Camilla and Diana have different attitudes. Camilla almost always takes and uses it. Taking and using. There are almost no pictures of Diana taking and using it. When I was writing a book in 2018, I searched all of that. But Diana has almost never used the same pen. So in my opinion, such a bad relationship shows in the writing tools too. Oh, Camilla is good with Charles just by looking at the writing tools. She’s the one who supports Charles. The difference between Camilla and Diana through fountain pens. It’s the only theory in the world, right? Well, that's how I figured it out.
** Speaker 1:**  Now let’s move on to ballpoint pens. You said you mastered pencils and fountain pens strictly. I hated ballpoint pens. Because they compete with fountain pens. But as I studied, it was a narrow view. Because while studying ballpoint pens, I solved the parts I couldn't solve in fountain pens. Oh, I thought you went to ballpoint pens after mastering fountain pens. That wasn't it. I realized fountain pens anew through ballpoint pens. So I started studying ballpoint pens strictly again. I studied ballpoint pens again. At first, I kept my distance because it was a competitor of fountain pens. The one that cockily takes on fountain pens. I thought that much. But after finishing fountain pens and moving on to ballpoint pens, I realized fountain pens again through ballpoint pens. So I changed my posture and studied strictly.
** Speaker 1:**  I don’t drive now and take the subway, but when I used to drive, I would sign after putting in gas. Even when I signed, I used a fountain pen. Even when I signed. Even in the old carbon paper days, I used a fountain pen. I don’t hold a ballpoint pen. I don't hold a ballpoint pen. Never. Because it’s a betrayal. Well, of course. But after those years passed, my first misconception was that I had studied everything about fountain pens. Then I should do ballpoint pens. And I studied ballpoint pens, and I realized something I didn't even realize I hadn't solved through ballpoint pens.
** Speaker 2:**  What is it? Fountain pens get smaller and smaller after ballpoint pens come out. Really? Yes. I thought it was to be more compact. Because it’s easy to carry. I thought simply like that, but after studying ballpoint pens, I realized the reason why fountain pens get smaller. Why is that? Ballpoint pens are smaller than fountain pens. The world of writing tools has sets. Ballpoint pens and fountain pens form a pair like this. It’s awkward if the size difference is too big. To match that set beautifully, ballpoint pens have the leadership, so fountain pens get smaller. The fountain pen that came out like that is called Parker 75, and it goes really well with ballpoint pens. So after ballpoint pens come out, fountain pens get one step smaller. I realized that, and later, ballpoint pens lose their position. A period of revival of fountain pens comes. That's the 1980s, and when fountain pens revive, they get stronger. Fountain pens get bigger again.
** Speaker 1:**  The size changes like that? It gets bigger again. With fountain pen centralism. It got smaller because it was convenient to carry, but it gets bigger again. You couldn't understand it. I couldn't understand it before. I couldn't even think about it. But through ballpoint pens, I saw that it changed to a size that goes well with ballpoint pens. But when ballpoint pens lose their position again, fountain pens get bigger. Products start to be composed only of fountain pens without buying ballpoint pens separately, so there's no need to match. We people who study call it the revival of fountain pens in the 1980s. So it escaped the influence of ballpoint pens. Fountain pens sell well on their own. New products coming out at that time were bigger. The nib got bigger too. No need to be limited to the size of ballpoint pens.
** Speaker 2:**  Then what happens? Ballpoint pens get bigger too. Conversely. Conversely this time, the influence of fountain pens went in. So this time, we have to match the set to the fountain pen size. To match the fountain pen size, ballpoint pens got bigger. How interesting is this? This is something only the Director can say in the whole world. Because you can never find out just by studying fountain pens. So I realized that writing tools are something that is given and taken, so they should be studied together. So I studied ballpoint pens strictly. I almost ignored them. Really.
** Speaker 1:**  So let’s go into the results of studying ballpoint pens strictly. There are three factors for the success of an object. This is also something I thought of myself. Director Park’s theory again. First, there must be a new idea. Of course. Second, there must be technology. That too. Third, there must be social interest. People’s interest. You need technology to realize that idea. And if people don't buy it, it’s no use. New products don't always succeed. Those three must be there.
** Speaker 2:**  If we look at the beginning of ballpoint pens, it’s 1888. It’s very early. 1888. 1888 is when, as I said last time, pencils came out with coins. And it’s when practical fountain pens came out. And the person who brought this out at that time, what was he thinking? I want to write where I can't write with a fountain pen. There are places where you can't write with a fountain pen. Like on wood surfaces. Rough. Rough surfaces. The nib breaks. Pencils break too. Pencils can break and be erased. This person seems to have been engaged in leather-related business. Ah, so he needed it, so he made it. On rough surfaces, expensive fountain pen nibs break, and pencils are erased or break.
** Speaker 1:**  But at that time, there were few people interested. Why? People don't know why they need it. Only you need it. This is how it goes. I’m a leather worker. Another thing is that at that time, they couldn't make a round sphere. It has to roll round, so the ball must have no tolerance. They had to make a perfectly round sphere. They didn't have that technology. So they didn't have technology and no interest. After that, ballpoint pen patents keep coming out. Even if they come out, people are not interested. So ballpoint pen ideas came out a long time ago. Similar ideas came out after that, but they didn't get interest. Because why do I need to use a ballpoint pen on rough surfaces?
** Speaker 2:**  But some people keep filing patents. Around the 1930s, someone came out with a revolutionary idea. Who is this person? It’s László Bíró. A Jew living in Hungary. László Bíró. First time hearing that. First time hearing that. This person has a lot of talent. He studied hypnosis and painted. He’s a jack-of-all-trades. But he got hooked on writing tools. He thought about making a really good writing tool. So he filed a patent. In 1938. He’s trying to make a ballpoint pen, but what’s the situation in Europe? War. It’s hard for a Jew to be active. He goes to France. In France too, it’s hard for a Jew to be active. So this person goes to Argentina. And starts making it. So the first of what is called a ballpoint pen is Argentina. Before that, there were only ideas and one or two prototypes. Ideas, patents, and prototypes, but there was almost no full-scale commercialization. Technology was lacking and people were not interested, so not many were made.
** Speaker 1:**  So a Jewish Hungarian moved to Argentina during WWII and commercialized his idea, which is the first. But the technology was a bit lacking. It wasn't perfect. It wasn't perfect. So he improves it once more. So he files a patent in 1943. The second patent. From here, it’s a bit better than the previous ballpoint pen. People start getting interested. Technology works, and around 1940, it’s usable. So a lot of investors gather. One of them, as a partner, supplies it to the British Air Force. Several tens of thousands. They used it, and the US Air Force saw it and liked it.
** Speaker 2:**  The US Air Force saw the British Air Force using it and liked it. The US Air Force is jumping all over the world. They were in Hungary, then went to Argentina, then supplied to the British Air Force, and during WWII, the US Air Force saw it and liked it. At that time, the US was the world’s best in writing tools. The famous Parker. Parker and Sheaffer. But Parker doesn't have a ballpoint pen yet. No ballpoint pen. The Air Force calls the Big Three companies, Parker, Sheaffer, and Eversharp. You guys try making this too. Parker is number one. Number one is conservative. And Parker has the famous Parker 51. It sells well. Why ballpoint pens? Parker isn't really interested. Sheaffer is in a similar situation.
** Speaker 1:**  Eversharp. What kind of company was Eversharp? It was a company that made money with mechanical pencils. A company that made mechanical pencils. You might have heard of Eversharp electronics, which is almost bankrupt now. The chairman of Eversharp electronics filed a patent for mechanical pencils and sold it to the US. That company is Eversharp. So he made a lot of money with that mechanical pencil patent. The first chairman of Eversharp electronics was the person who made the mechanical pencil patent and sold it to Eversharp. Eversharp didn't even have Eversharp as its name before. But after buying that patent, they changed their name to Eversharp. Before that, it was a company that made things like calculators. So this company, unlike Parker or Sheaffer, the founder isn't an engineer or an inventor. It’s a company with a history of buying patents and making a lot of money.
** Speaker 2:**  So when they saw this, what did they think? It’s a new patent. This looks like it’ll make money. And at that time, they were being pushed by Parker and Sheaffer. So they get interested in new writing tools. So Eversharp says we should do this. And when they looked into it, someone had already bought the North American patent. Who bought it? The pencil company that made the Blackwing I mentioned last time, Eberhard Faber. That company has the patent. The Argentine ballpoint pen patent North American sales rights were held by the pencil company. The pencil company also wants to do something new. So Eversharp says let’s do it together. So the pencil company and the mechanical pencil company joined forces. It could be called a consortium, and there are many stories about this person. There are many rumors. Anyway, they joined forces. They joined forces and decided to sell ballpoint pens after making them, so they advertised a lot. Our ballpoint pen is coming out! They advertised a lot. They thought it would be a hit once it came out. They already had the patent.
** Speaker 1:**  But does the world work as planned? Someone who is still criticized in the writing tool world appears. A villain of the writing tool world. In the writing tool world, they criticize this person first. Such a person appears. Who is it? Milton Reynolds. You must remember the name. Milton Reynolds. You must remember Milton Reynolds. The Hitler of the writing tool world? Maybe more than Hitler. Hitler, his end was miserable. But this person’s end wasn't miserable. Why is he hated? He has a bit of a gambler’s temperament. He failed in business several times and then succeeded again, earned a lot today and lost it all tomorrow. And then he saw the ballpoint pen. He saw it at some jewelry store. He saw the ballpoint pen. What is this? Instinctively, this person thought this would make money. The war is almost over. 1945. People’s desire for new things will explode. Revenge consumption. He felt it with his animal-like senses.
** Speaker 2:**  So he went to buy the patent. It was sold. The patent was bought in 1944. This person went in 1945. Around May 1945. He was a step late. He was a step late. What does this person do? He buys several ballpoint pens and comes to the US. And he researches things that don't infringe on the patent. As I said before, there were many patents before László Bíró’s patent. He did this and that and brought out a ballpoint pen on October 29, 1945. He didn't advertise much. Who advertised? Eversharp advertised a lot, and in that situation, this person brought out a ballpoint pen. People thought it was the ballpoint pen from that advertisement. At some department store in New York. 10,000 were sold in one day. 10,000 in one day. So while Eversharp and Faber were setting the stage, he suddenly came in and took it all.
** Speaker 1:**  People were waiting for a lot. When it came out, they thought it was that one. October 29, 1945. The war was over. They wanted to buy something. But the ballpoint pen they saw in the advertisement came out. 10,000 in a day at the department store. 10,000 in a day. But at what price did he sell it? He sold it at the price of the Parker 51 at that time. That’s the price of a very high-end fountain pen, $12.50. 10,000. 1 million in three months. It became a huge hit. $12.50 times 1 million. It’s 10 million dollars. At that time. It’s a lot of money even now. It was a huge hit.
** Speaker 2:**  In the meantime, Eversharp, which was preparing, still couldn't produce it. The chairman of Eversharp said something better. Bring out a perfect product. Something better. We have to increase the perfection. He didn't want to disappoint. László Bíró’s ballpoint pen wasn't perfect. He was fixing the weaknesses, and while doing that, he got hit in the back of the head. Six months later, Eversharp’s ballpoint pen comes out. Six months later. Six months is a huge delay. In the meantime, he swept it all away. And after six months, he brought out a new product and dropped the price. He’s a bad guy. He made a lot of money with $12, and then dropped it to $8. How much did Eversharp sell it for? $19. Because of the advertising costs and the patent fees. Nevertheless, Eversharp ballpoint pens sold a bit. People thought a better ballpoint pen came out. They sold it, but inside, they were burning.
** Speaker 1:**  In that situation, in 1946, what happens? Other writing tool manufacturers who benchmarked Reynolds appeared. Seeing Reynolds’ success. Everyone said why not us too. Reynolds actually copied the patent. It wasn't something he researched, but he changed it cleverly and brought it out and it became a hit. Oh, this? It doesn't seem like much technology. They jumped in. Because making ballpoint pens doesn't require gold. Gold goes into fountain pens, so it’s hard to enter. It’s easy to enter. And after the war, there was plenty of precision technology. And social interest. Patents? They thought they could avoid what Reynolds did. Ballpoint pens came out everywhere. So what happens? The quality of ballpoint pens is terrible. Products came out without perfection, so they didn't work after a few days. Low-quality ballpoint pens poured out.
** Speaker 2:**  And Reynolds’ ballpoint pen was gravity type. It had to be done by capillary action, but the gravity type leaks as you use it. So for about eight months, 100,000 Reynolds ballpoint pens were returned. It works well at first. But since it flows from top to bottom, the manual says always keep the pen like this. It keeps flowing, so it’s returned, and the competitors jumped in and dropped the quality. The perception of ballpoint pens was, this is no good. He killed the early life of a writing tool called the ballpoint pen. He took all the money. This person dropped the price once more. Reynolds. So what happens to this? He doesn't have affection for ballpoint pens. He’ll be criticized forever, right? He kept dropping the price, did his last business, and left in the late 40s.
** Speaker 1:**  What should be done about this? He ruined all ballpoint pens. What should be done? Reynolds? We keep criticizing him. Every time a ballpoint pen comes out, Reynolds. We criticize him. In the meantime, it’s a CA ballpoint pen. The Eversharp ballpoint pen is CA. Capillary Attraction. It means capillary action. So they made a ballpoint pen with capillary action. The principle of making ink come out. They kept losing money here. Because the image of ballpoint pens was ruined. So they kept losing money. Nevertheless, some people thought ballpoint pens were the future of writing tools. So ballpoint pens are improved. Because the idea is good. If they do it well, some people thought ballpoint pens could revive. There was such a person.
** Speaker 2:**  Who saves ballpoint pens then? There is a company called Paper Mate. That company increases the ink stability and saves ballpoint pens, increasing sales. They finally made a stable ballpoint pen. Parker was still watching. Parker still hasn't entered. Parker is still cautious. Because Parker 51 is still selling well. Parker says, okay, let it ripen. Ripen. Finally, in 1954, Parker brings out a ballpoint pen. It took a long time. That is the Jotter. Parker Jotter ballpoint pen. I brought it. Oh, here it is. Try pressing it once. You’ve used something like that, right? Yes, I have. It came out in 1954. This model. So it’s almost unchanged. It was already perfected then. Very little has changed. So Parker brought out the ballpoint pen after perfecting it. So they approached it carefully.
** Speaker 1:**  Parker added what to that? Large capacity refill. So they put in a ballpoint pen core that lasts five or six times longer. Another thing is that as the ballpoint pen core comes out, it rotates 90 degrees every time you press it. This? Every time you press it. If you use a ballpoint pen like this, the bottom wears out and the writing quality drops or it splits. They made it four times more. So they put in a lot of capacity, and according to that, this also rotates. 90 degrees each. Then you can use it four times longer. That was made in 1954. So every time you press it now, it’s rotating. You think it’s the same side, but it’s rotated 90 degrees. People don't really know that. General public almost doesn't know.
** Speaker 2:**  Parker added technical perfection and revolutionary ideas. Did the market respond? It sold very well. For the next 30 years, it was the ballpoint pen that fed Parker. As Parker brought out the ballpoint pen, the true ballpoint pen era began. A more important person appears. I call this person the terminator. Completion of ballpoint pens. Marcel Bich. Many new names are coming out. It sounds like a French name. In 1950, you’ve seen this ballpoint pen. Ah, Bic! BIC. Yes, Bic. He brought out the Bic. So this was a person’s name. Originally, it was BICH. He dropped the H and made it BIC. BIC. I used it a lot. Some kids used Monami and some kids used Bic. You had it in your school days too, Director. I used it too. This is the Bic Cristal. This is old, Bic. 1950. So it’s earlier than the Jotter 1954. It’s perfected at a low price. Not only did they perfect it at a low price, they perfected the ballpoint pen world.
** Speaker 1:**  How many of these were sold in a year? They say 25 million were sold. As soon as Bic came out. After a few years, they produced 1 million a day. Cumulative production varies by data, but in 2007, 2008, it’s 100 billion. 100 billion. The one that clearly made the public domain between fountain pens and pencils is the Bic. So this is amazing. The authority on writing tools for 5,000 years. Because it’s been over 5,000 years since letters were created. Sumerians poked clay with reeds, and that was a writing tool. No one could touch it. Writing tools were a sign of authority that you couldn't approach unless you were royalty. Bic made this disposable.
** Speaker 2:**  So it achieved the democratization of writing tools. It broke the authority. It’s a great thing. No one could break it. Parker Jotter wouldn't have done it. Fountain pens were still expensive and not something workers used. But as Bic came out, a disposable ballpoint pen that everyone could use. This is a great thing. So this person, around 1958. Waterman. The company that started fountain pens, Waterman. The biggest company in the world in the early 1900s. Of course, in the 50s, the momentum was lost and it fell a lot compared to Parker or Sheaffer, but in a symbolic sense, the father of fountain pens, Waterman. He bought it. Acquisition! He bought it and closed the door. Why did he close the door? Marcel Bich is a person with some philosophy. I’ve ended the fountain pen era. I’ve removed the authority. You bought it and closed the door?
** Speaker 1:**  He closed the door. He’s a great person. I’m a person who likes fountain pens, but Marcel Bich, who democratized the world of writing tools, is also an attractive figure. He’s a revolutionist of writing tools. Waterman, buy and close the door! I’ll end the era of fountain pens. You see the removal of authority as that. You bought it and closed the door? He closed the door. He’s a great person. It’s like the French Revolution where Louis XVI was sent off. That’s what it seems like. Buying and closing the door. There are Parker and Waterman dynasties, and I bought and closed the Waterman dynasty. You can see it like that. It’s a revolution. And another thing is that as he entered the US, he lowered the price more. At first, where did Bic come out? France. It started in France, and it also dominated the market after coming to the US.
** Speaker 1:**  The feeling when first using a Bic, everyone must be the same. It glides well. It glides well on paper. It writes well, and the writing distance is very long. Monami couldn't follow that feeling then. What we call ballpoint pen poop. Every ballpoint pen has poop, but this has less poop. Right. Why is that? This person, Bich, developed a very good ink. But he developed it in the 1950s. Whose patent did he use? László Bíró’s patent. So the father of ballpoint pens is László Bíró. But that person ended at being an engineer. But this person, what did he do? He achieved the democratization of the world of writing tools. It’s a great thing.
** Speaker 2:**  So Parker Jotter is also a 1954 product, and it’s almost the same now. And this Bic is also used now, and it’s a 1950s product. Ballpoint pens were perfected in the 1950s. Ballpoint pens were perfected in the 1950s. And since I brought it, this is the 75. Compare the size with that Parker ballpoint pen. They are similar. So it got smaller. Ballpoint pens have the leadership. If you look at the core, you’ll understand. The ballpoint pen got smaller than the Jotter. Compare it. This ballpoint pen name is? It’s the Parker 75 ballpoint pen. This is the Parker 75 fountain pen. After the Jotter, the Parker 75 ballpoint pen came out, and because it was an era led by ballpoint pens, the fountain pen also got smaller. Almost the same. I found that out while studying ballpoint pens.
** Speaker 1:**  Then what year is this? The 75 started in 1963. Parker ballpoint pens are doing well. I’ve never used a Parker ballpoint pen, but I’ve matched it to the best. How? That refill, a German one will be in it, not Parker’s. Ah, that standard has almost dominated the world. The standard has been unified worldwide. You put in the core the Director likes. This is not Parker’s core. Where is this core from? Germany. Germany is good with cores. Because Germany was immersed in fountain pens, they entered the ballpoint pen market late. So there are no famous ballpoint pens in Germany. Instead, they go with cores. What is this German core? Schneider. You haven't heard of it. Schneider makes cores diligently. There are some disposable fountain pens, but core business is probably the biggest. It glides well. It glides well. It’s perfectly matched. Jotter is original and? I changed that too. Parker’s original is more stiff. More stiff. It glides well. It glides like a fountain pen. This is Schneider? Schneider refill. The shape is the Parker ballpoint pen shape. The shell is Parker. The core is Schneider. The standard matches perfectly. That's how you use it. It’s fun.
** Speaker 2:**  It’s not as noble as fountain pens, so I changed the clothes and? It’s good. This is a ballpoint pen that glides well. The writing tool genes are flowing in you. Don't deny it. When is a ballpoint pen annoying? I think it’ll glide this much and wrote, but sometimes it glides more. It glides more or less. Because of the resistance, you have to give it a bit more strength to complete the letter. It’s annoying then. I really can't use ballpoint pens. Fountain pens are better, so my handwriting is a bit better. Oh, I haven't seen a ballpoint pen this smooth. The handwriting is beautiful. It would be good to use when signing.
** Speaker 1:**  Later, a ballpoint pen that glides smoother than that comes out. Where do we go next? We’ve seen up to Bic. Democratization has been achieved. Ballpoint pens were in everyone’s hands. After that, another one appears. So as the Jotter came out, it reached a somewhat high-end ballpoint pen. There is something called action and reaction. Democratization was achieved, right? There will be a desire for high-end items. That is the Cross ballpoint pen. I haven't heard of this either. Cross? I brought it. See. It’s pretty. It’s a twist type. You should focus on it being a twist type. Cross. It looks slim and pretty. It’s quite heavy. How is it? Does it feel high-end? It’s thick. It’s slim but very thick.
** Speaker 2:**  So the world is always filled without gaps. If there’s a desire for high-end, someone tries to fill it. This writes beautifully. The friction with the paper is just right. I used that for almost 30 years. Without losing it. It’s the oldest among the ballpoint pens I have. Does it come out for 30 years? I changed the core. I bought several cores 30 years ago. I’m still using those. Not today’s cores. From 30 years ago. Not today’s cores, but from when I bought it, I’ll use this until whenever, so I bought a lot of cores. The ones from then. Today’s cores are a bit looser. The writing feeling. I don't like it. So I’m still using those old cores. If the writing glides too fast, the writing flows away. It catches the writing so it doesn't flow.
** Speaker 1:**  Try the Parker Jotter now. But it shakes. Because it’s a button type, it shakes. Because it’s not completely fixed in the hole. It shakes. Right, it shakes a bit. We can't stand that. We can't stand it shaking while writing. So the Parker is a button type, so as it comes out from the hole and goes back in, there’s a tolerance. Between the entrance and the core. There’s a gap. And the mechanism behind it that catches it, it doesn't rotate if it matches perfectly, so there must be a gap to rotate and come out. So it shakes. I can't stand this. I can't use it. It’s annoying. Most people can't feel it. No, it’s very hard. In our writing tool world. It’s very hard. You can't forgive shaking. There must be a comfort that doesn't shake. It’s felt. It’s felt in the Director’s hand.
** Speaker 2:**  And among the button types, the Parker is a good one. Try another similar button type later. It shakes immensely. Think about Monami. It shakes when you press it. We can't call it Monami because it’s our country. Anyway, button types have mechanical limitations. Design. But try that. Ah, the Cross is a twist type, so it fills the entrance tightly. It fills it tightly until it comes out. So there’s no need for a gap. It doesn't shake. I can't feel both shaking. This is not even 0.001mm. No, no. This doesn't shake at all. This doesn't shake at all.
** Speaker 1:**  Does this Cross become a hit as soon as it comes out? It became a hit as soon as it came out. That’s also around 1954. It’s a contemporary of the Jotter. The world of ballpoint pens was finished in the early to mid-50s. A democratized one came out, a mid-range one came out, and a high-end one came out. At what price did it come out then? It must have come out at the price of a fountain pen. So it filled the gap of the dark age of fountain pens. As high-end ballpoint pens came out in the market, fountain pens went into hiding. Because this gives a writing feeling close to a fountain pen. And it doesn't flow. Fountain pens need to be refilled after a week. You don't have to refill it. You can use it for several years. It doesn't get on your hands. It must have been revolutionary then. The era of fountain pens is over.
** Speaker 2:**  But it wasn't. Humans are not such simple animals. Humans. How long does the heyday of ballpoint pens last? Until the 1980s. In the 80s, socially, the oil shock passes. Oil shock. So the Yuppie culture appears in the US. Yuppie, right. A young generation that wanted to use high-end products. So from the 1980s, Cross sales start to decrease. And in the fountain pen world, those quick-witted people thought, is our dark age ending? Ballpoint pens came out in the 50s and swept until the 80s, so fountain pens got smaller according to ballpoint pens, and in the 80s, the Yuppie generation, which has economic power and likes high-end products, appeared. YOLO. Something like that. That generation appeared and looked for the fountain pens their fathers or grandfathers used. They wanted something cool. Everyone else uses ballpoint pens, but I don't use Cross. Fountain pens are it. Suddenly, from the 80s, fountain pens started to sell again. It’s interesting.
** Speaker 1:**  I can't finish studying no matter how much I do. The study of writing tools has a 5,000-year history. How interesting would it be? As ballpoint pen sales decreased, a new product came out in the fountain pen world and sold. Then fountain pen sizes started to get bigger. Now they don't have to be sold as a set with ballpoint pens, so fountain pens showed their presence and got bigger. Cross also brought out big ballpoint pens. Cross too. They followed because it didn't sell. This Cross is really slim. A bigger one came out. During the heyday of ballpoint pens, portability was emphasized and they got smaller. Fountain pens also got smaller. As the fountain pen era returned, ballpoint pens got bigger. How interesting. It’s interesting. So ballpoint pens got bigger.
** Speaker 2:**  So fountain pens appeared in the 80s and revived and lasted 30 years. I think it’s the end now. Fountain pens are nearing the end. I’m worried. The enemy of fountain pens this time is not ballpoint pens. It’s smartphones. Smartphones. That makes sense. I hate smartphones the most. It’s not that I hate them, I’m afraid. Smart writing tools like Apple Pencil. My daughter uses that. The daughter who grinds pencils. The daughter without affection for writing tools. Right. She had an iPad since she was born. She uses that. Every time I see it, I ask, is it good? It doesn't even have a writing feeling. Is it good? She just ends it there. She’s afraid to answer. If she says it’s good, she doesn't want to hear it. I really hate smart writing tools. I’ve tried using them too, but they don't have the feeling of friction with paper.
** Speaker 1:**  But as a fountain pen enthusiast, if I were to defend fountain pens, human memory is best when all five senses are used together. Writing, hearing the scratchy sound, feeling the texture, when all five senses are felt, people become smarter. That’s true. If you compare the brain of a person typing on a keyboard and a person writing with a pencil, the pencil one is active all over. So I tell them to write directly with writing tools. How smart would I be then? But this is a joke. As smart writing tools come out, writing by hand decreases. But I think smart pens have their own domain, and writing tools will continue to survive. That’s the answer.
** Speaker 2:**  When ballpoint pens appeared, did fountain pens disappear? Don't worry too much. I’m worried because in the last few years, I’ve become interested in writing tools again. After doing everything on PC, I suddenly started looking for fountain pens and using pencils again. A principle of trying to keep some balance keeps working, but I’m a bit anxious because I love them so much. But it’s like this. When I saw, has a proper smart writing tool come out now? When ballpoint pens first came out, they copied the shape of fountain pens. After some time, ballpoint pens found their own identity and the cap disappeared. In the 60s, because ballpoint pens were so powerful, a fountain pen without a cap comes out. A fountain pen without a cap? Yes, this is a fountain pen. It’s a button type like a ballpoint pen. It’s a copy. Because ballpoint pens were so powerful. Let’s copy the strengths of ballpoint pens. There was such a time. Capless. No cap.
** Speaker 1:**  This is really my first time seeing this. It comes out well. I made it come out well. It’s popular recently. It came out in the 60s. Popularity started recently. Rather. Now the leadership struggle is not one-sided. It comes out really well. I made it come out well. How? Just by looking at it, it comes out well. It glides. Where is this from? Japan. Developed in Japan. Very Japanese. A bit sleek? Fountain pens have a cap even if it’s a bit inconvenient, and the dignity comes from there. It looks like a fountain pen, but a head pops out when you press a button. Sleek. But I don't hate it. Because I have all kinds of writing tools. I never speak ill of fountain pens. Any fountain pen. I don't do fountain pen reviews. They are all pretty. How can I talk about weaknesses? I’ve never done it.
** Speaker 2:**  Why did that come out? It’s the influence of ballpoint pens, right? Then were ballpoint pens finished with Parker Jotter, Bic, and Cross? No. I have to talk about one more thing. I was talking about smart writing tools before, Apple Pencil. What is the shape of Apple Pencil? It hasn't worn its own clothes yet. The shape of Apple Pencil is just like a pencil. It hasn't developed yet. It hasn't found its own unique shape yet. There was a time when ballpoint pens were like that, copying fountain pens. That time hasn't come yet. So I’m relieved.
** Speaker 1:**  In the history of writing tools, until a unique design is perfected. What was the shape of fountain pens at first? It was the shape of a pencil. Then they got their own look. Ballpoint pens were at first the shape of fountain pens. Then they got their own look. Smart writing tools now look like pencils. I’m relieved for now. Then, the fourth and last one that marked an era for ballpoint pens. Low-viscosity ballpoint pens. What is that? Try it. It glides more. Slim and oh, it glides very well. Immensely. That’s a low-viscosity ballpoint pen. The viscosity has decreased. So viscosity in ballpoint pens is high. The higher the viscosity, the more stiff it is. The feeling of sticking to the paper. It takes a lot of strength to roll that ball if the viscosity is high. But the viscosity was lowered.
** Speaker 2:**  The contact with the paper is small. The writing distance will be shorter. Because it flows a lot. Even with the same ink, it’s used up quickly. But in the old days when the writing distance was long, you used one of those in a day. People’s writing amount has decreased, so low viscosity is enough. The writing distance is only about 500m. This Bic is 2km. That Jotter will be 7km, 8km. This is only 500m? 500m. But it glides smoothly. So instead of filling a whole page, they started using writing tools for just a few lines. Look at how Blackwing was highlighted again. When the writing amount is small, it was highlighted amazingly. That timing also appears in ballpoint pens.
** Speaker 1:**  When did low viscosity appear? 2008, 2006. In the history of ballpoint pens, this is another technical turning point. Go to the biggest stationery store in Korea, Kyobo Hottracks. All ballpoint pens are low viscosity now. Contact is small so it can be stiff, but they made a lot of ink come out to make it glide smoothly. Low-viscosity ballpoint pens. Modern ballpoint pens. In the Director’s view, the final evolution of ballpoint pens is low viscosity. Low viscosity. But I don't like it. Ballpoint pens should have the feeling of ink sticking thickly to the paper and gliding. For our generation. But today’s generation started with low-viscosity ballpoint pens, so they can't use old ballpoint pens. They say their hands hurt. Hands hurt. My daughter says her hands hurt. She doesn't even touch old ballpoint pens.
** Speaker 2:**  I like this the best. Parker 75 with Schneider core. Or Parker Jotter. Inevitably, I’m in the same era. This is the feeling. This looks the most high-end, and let me show you another one. This ballpoint pen. Even prettier. It’s similar to Cross. Almost the same. This glides less. The feeling of gliding fits me. Parker 75 ballpoint pen with Schneider core, this combination is the best. Schneider company is in trouble. A core that only enthusiasts enjoyed? In trouble.
** Speaker 1:**  So you only need to know four turning points for ballpoint pens. Those four are it. Others are all derivatives. There are thousands of ballpoint pens, but it ends with those. They are all derivatives or just different shells. Technically, Parker Jotter is the most revolutionary. Press, and it rotates 90 degrees every time you press. And they made this type first. It’s still maintained. They set the standard for large capacity refills. The ballpoint pen I personally like the best is this. Colani ballpoint pen. It’s German, and uniquely, you don't press the head, but pull the side to make the core come out. This looks unique. It’s discontinued. I’ve collected a lot.
** Speaker 2:**  Was it made by a person named Colani? It’s probably Luigi Colani. A great industrial designer. So it’s comfortable for the hands even when used for a long time. It’s unique. It’s triangular. A friend who went to Brazil left it with me. He said he’d come back after succeeding. But he left it. He was a ballpoint pen enthusiast in Korea. A fellow writing tool enthusiast. I’m going to Brazil and I’ll come back after succeeding, but he hasn't come back. I don't think he can come back. So I’ve kept this ballpoint pen forever. It was that person’s favorite ballpoint pen, but he gave it to me. I can't do with just one.
** Speaker 1:**  I went to a stationery store in Japan once. I asked if they had this ballpoint pen. The owner said they had it. But they liked it too much to sell. They liked it too much to sell. Known among writing tool enthusiasts. Oh, is that so? We understand. We understand that feeling. Since they like it. I turned around and walked about 100m, and the lady called me. I went back and she said you look like you like this ballpoint pen more than I do. Only for such people. Look at those enthusiasts. That desperate look. It hurts. You’ll probably like it more than I do. I’ll sell the ballpoint pen. Giving it only to such a person. So I bought that ballpoint pen at the original price without a premium. And I got that ballpoint pen again a few years later. So I went to Japan. To give it. Wow!
** Speaker 2:**  The door was closed. I got it with difficulty, so I’ll give it back to you. I went. That’s how it is. Thanks to you, I enjoyed this ballpoint pen a lot, so now I’ll give it back to you. I got another one. I wanted to give it as a present. Among enthusiasts of that level, that’s the spirit. You went to Japan just for that? I went to give that present for a day, but the door was closed. It would have been a great story there too. So I kept asking in Japan and they said the door is still closed. Is another store there? No. The door is just closed. I’m curious. Curiosity. The hearts of stationery people are one in the world. The world is one. The world is one. There was such a time.
** Speaker 1:**  Lastly, the Director’s favorite ballpoint pen was Colani. Colani Number 1. There are enthusiasts who love Colani in the world of writing tools. They are true nerds. If this broadcast goes out, the premium will go up. How much is this? The white one is about $30, and the red one is $150. How much did I buy it for in Japan? 5,000 won. The premium was already ten times higher, but she only took 5,000 won. Looking at my eyes, she thought I’d like it more than she did. I’ll give it to you at the original price. I’ll sell it at the original price. And I’ll pay back later. I went like that, but the door was closed. There is such a world. I can't go that far. I brought a pencil today. It’s a hard-to-find pencil. What did I say I liked? During the pencil time, oh, this pencil writing feeling is really good. Princeship. So I searched all through the warehouse.
** Speaker 2:**  What year is this? It’s not 100 years, but it must be over 70 or 80 years. 70 or 80 years. I can't sharpen this. It was already sharpened then. I’m giving you half of what I have. You don't have to give me this much. Just one. Because I can't reach that level. I’m not qualified to have that much, so don't give it. So the Director searched all over and thought I should give this. That’s the heart of these writing tool people. Come in. To our writing tool world. You have the writing tool genes. I have that. Expensive or not, the friction with the paper when I write, the resistance coefficient, when that fits my heart perfectly. Try this too. This is also a ballpoint pen I like. Four-color ballpoint pen. It’s a rotating color one. That too has differences between East and West. When you see the clip from the front, the one on the right is number one. This? Blue. Blue is number one in Europe. In our country or this side, number one is black.
** Speaker 1:**  So the preferred color is different. That’s very good. For a rotating button type ballpoint pen, it’s very solid. I like it best. Bic made it. Bic. Most of them are made overseas. Only that is made in France. He has affection for it. Since the original Bic is French. Only that is made in France. He has a lot of affection. Four-color ballpoint pen, but it’s a common model. The original Bic has the most identity. If you want to have a Bic ballpoint pen, having that is most fitting for the identity. Okay. That’s still made in France. Only that. It has the most original Bic identity. And focus on the blue color on the right of this head. Check that. That’s made in Europe.
** Speaker 2:**  Next, for ballpoint pens, Parker Jotter, and Cross is another ballpoint pen that marked an era. Then Colani is from Germany. For geometric design and perfection and uniqueness, Colani. Colani. This is what enthusiasts love very much. Colani. The core is Schneider. It goes like that. Writing tools are finished with this, right? There is also paper. Paper! Paper is no joke. In my case, I’ve even made paper. Our country’s Hanji, I’ve tried making that too, and I’ve looked for parchment, and papyrus. Paper contains a vast culture. The story that appears as it goes East and West is quite a lot. A history of over 2,000 years. Have you ever tried getting paper and writing with your favorite writing tools? Of course. I try everything. And King Sejong was an amazing paper nerd. Let’s do that next time. Okay. Today, let’s end with ballpoint pens. Next time, paper, inkstone, brush, ink, let’s do that. Younger brothers. Right. It’s interesting. That’s interesting too. The Director must have studied paper strictly too. Of course. Our country’s Hanji was highly regarded in China too. Since Goryeo. Silla’s white paper was very good. Is it really true? Is it really true? I have to check strictly. I checked strictly. So I looked at the Annals of the Joseon Dynasty. Paper stories come out a lot. Sejong really liked paper. Next time, paper, inkstone, brush, ink, which are the four friends of the study. We can do that. Today we’ll end here. Thank you. Thank you.