The transcription of the provided audio file is as follows:
(Car starting sounds)
**Kim Eo-jun**: This is Kim Eo-jun from the end-of-the-month Kim Eo-jun. We've heard about North and South Pole, Everest, Bering Strait, Greenland polar expeditions. We've heard about non-motorized yacht world circumnavigation maritime expeditions. We've heard about aviation expeditions crossing the Himalayas in a hang glider, cave explorations, and recently we met Jang Ji-hoon, the only person in Korea who holds the 100-meter free diving record. Jang Ji-hoon broke the Korean record at an international free diving competition with the support of end-of-the-month Kim Eo-jun and wearing the end-of-the-month Kim Eo-jun logo. (Applause and cheers) So, to celebrate Jang Ji-hoon's new Korean record, we've invited a bunch of amateur free divers in their 30s who think "I can do it too." Hello.
**Guests**: Hello.
**Kim Eo-jun**: I invited amateur free divers in their 30s who have been diving for less than two years. Let's start with Oh Ye-seon, a nurse at a university hospital with two years of experience.
**Oh Ye-seon**: Yes, hello. (Applause) I clapped for myself.
**Kim Eo-jun**: And office worker Hong Min-ji.
**Hong Min-ji**: Yes, nice to meet you. (Applause)
**Kim Eo-jun**: Hong Min-ji has been doing it for a year and a half.
**Hong Min-ji**: Yes, about a year and a half.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Park Min-joo, who used to be a shopping mall MD.
**Park Min-joo**: Oh, hello. (Applause)
**Kim Eo-jun**: 10 months of experience.
**Park Min-joo**: Yes, 10 months.
**Kim Eo-jun**: And office worker Kim Geun-ho.
**Kim Geun-ho**: Yes, I'm Kim Geun-ho. Hello. (Applause)
**Kim Eo-jun**: 1 year and 5 months of experience.
**Kim Geun-ho**: About that much.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Office worker Han Gyu-beom. 10 months of experience.
**Han Gyu-beom**: Yes, that's right. (Applause)
**Kim Eo-jun**: For your information, the introductions are in order of experience. Han Gyu-beom is Park Min-joo's boyfriend.
**Park Min-joo**: Ah, yes. (Laughter)
**Kim Eo-jun**: So the speaking time for the couple will be combined. Let's start from here. Everyone is in their 30s and busy with daily life. How did you get into this useless sport of diving deep into water, which doesn't help your life at all? From Oh Ye-seon.
**Oh Ye-seon**: I saw people free diving in Ulleungdo on the show '2 Days & 1 Night', and I suddenly had the urge to try it.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Without any prior information? Did you swim before?
**Oh Ye-seon**: I can't swim. I still can't swim, and I have no connection to the sea at all. I wasn't born near the sea, and no one in my family is a haenyeo (female diver). But I suddenly wanted to do it after seeing it on TV.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Why did you want to do it?
**Oh Ye-seon**: I still don't know. So I thought I'd just get a taste and went for a one-day experience.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Did you search the internet for a place?
**Oh Ye-seon**: Yes, I searched the internet for a place and a teacher I wanted, still not knowing why. I met my current teacher and went for the experience, and it suited me well.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Even though you can't swim?
**Oh Ye-seon**: I can't even float, but I'm good at sinking.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Sinking is quite painful.
**Kim Geun-ho**: It is. Sorry.
**Kim Eo-jun**: That was out of the blue.
**Kim Geun-ho**: Out of the blue, yes.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Hong Min-ji.
**Hong Min-ji**: Yes, I'm Hong. I did Pilates for a long time on weekdays while working.
**Kim Eo-jun**: What does that have to do with this?
**Hong Min-ji**: Oh, please listen to the end. I've been working a lot of overtime lately, to the point where I couldn't even go to Pilates. My neck and back hurt, so I was looking for an exercise that wasn't too strenuous or stressful.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Did your day and night switch?
**Hong Min-ji**: No, I'm just a normal 9-to-6 office worker, but I had a lot of overtime for a long time. I'd eat dinner and work until 1 AM, making reports. That kind of life continued.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Are you related to the president?
(Laughter)
**Hong Min-ji**: So I wanted something on the weekends that wasn't too hard on my body. Coincidentally, a junior from university was an instructor. I saw her Instagram and thought, "I should just do it." I've liked water since I was a kid. I thought I could use my body freely in the water. That's how I started.
**Kim Eo-jun**: It's not like it's not strenuous to go deep into the water.
**Hong Min-ji**: But at that point, I didn't even think about going deep. I just realized I was going deep as I did it.
(Laughter)
**Kim Eo-jun**: You didn't even know it was a sport where you go deep.
**Hong Min-ji**: I just wanted to roll around freely in the water. My joints hurt, you know? You shouldn't overdo it.
**Kim Eo-jun**: You didn't know anything. And Park Min-joo, who's only been doing it for 10 months.
**Park Min-joo**: Yes, I'm Park. My boyfriend actually has a severe phobia of water.
**Kim Eo-jun**: A water phobia, even?
**Park Min-joo**: Truly. To what extent? We've been together for 7 years.
**Kim Eo-jun**: You've been together for too long.
**Park Min-joo**: We've never even been to a valley in those 7 years because he's so afraid of water.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Wait, Han Gyu-beom.
**Han Gyu-beom**: Yes, I'm Han.
**Kim Eo-jun**: So you can't swim and you're afraid of water so you don't go near it?
**Han Gyu-beom**: Yes.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Why would someone who's so afraid of water do this?
**Park Min-joo**: Last year, out of the blue, he said he wanted to go to a valley. So we went once, and then he said he wanted to try snorkeling.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Suddenly?
**Park Min-joo**: Yes, suddenly. So we bought snorkeling gear and went to Janghohang.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Suddenly, for someone who can't swim?
**Park Min-joo**: Yes, really. We went there, and two women wearing really pretty fins were going into the water. We were just using these 30cm yellow fins...
**Kim Eo-jun**: They looked cool.
**Park Min-joo**: We were using those, and those two women had these long fins. He was like, "What's that?" He's really afraid of water, but he got curious.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Let's hear the boyfriend's version.
**Han Gyu-beom**: What did I see? Last year, I enjoyed watching a YouTuber called 'Valley is Gyul Gyul'.
**Kim Eo-jun**: You were getting vicarious satisfaction.
**Han Gyu-beom**: I was watching him and getting vicarious satisfaction. Then one day, I also wanted to be free in the water.
**Kim Eo-jun**: When did your water phobia start?
**Han Gyu-beom**: When I was young, I almost drowned...
**Oh Ye-seon**: No way! You wouldn't be here.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Usually, there has to be a trauma like that.
**Han Gyu-beom**: I swallowed a lot of water. Since then, I had a phobia. But watching that YouTuber, I got that desire.
**Kim Eo-jun**: You wanted to overcome it.
**Han Gyu-beom**: Yes, I had that desire, so I said let's go play.
**Kim Eo-jun**: How deep was the valley?
**Park Min-joo**: Knee-deep. (Laughter)
**Kim Eo-jun**: You didn't even go into the water! Even at knee-deep, you were screaming. Shouldn't you go to a hospital for that?
**Han Gyu-beom**: So I just went to play once. It was so much fun. After 20 years, I finally went into a stream at knee-depth and was screaming with joy. I had a primary victory. I succeeded in contacting water. Then I wanted to play more in the water, and I found out many people do snorkeling.
**Kim Eo-jun**: You skipped a lot. From a knee-deep stream straight to snorkeling?
**Han Gyu-beom**: So I wanted to go to Janghohang, the mecca of snorkeling. I just blindly went. I really have no foundation. I skipped everything. I blindly bought snorkeling gear, a mask, and a life jacket and went.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Even though you'd never been in the water before, you bought the gear.
**Han Gyu-beom**: I just went to the sea. I almost died then. But I got hooked on the water.
**Kim Eo-jun**: You saw a new world. Not those women.
**Han Gyu-beom**: I'd been afraid all my life, went to a knee-deep stream, and then straight to the sea. I was scared, but the view was so beautiful that I just lost my mind. But then I saw those long fins.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Those looked cooler. This whole process of deciding seems a bit lacking. Afraid for 20 years, then a stream, then snorkeling, then straight to free diving.
**Han Gyu-beom**: There was no middle ground.
**Kim Eo-jun**: "Let's learn that"?
**Park Min-joo**: Yes, my boyfriend, who was so afraid of water, suggested we do free diving first.
**Kim Eo-jun**: The first two people are also absurd. You're even more absurd.
**Han Gyu-beom**: Like I said, I really wanted to go into the water. I wanted to overcome it.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Do you two know how to swim?
**Han Gyu-beom**: I liked it.
**Park Min-joo**: I've just started learning.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Just started learning. And Kim Geun-ho?
**Kim Geun-ho**: Yes.
**Kim Eo-jun**: How did you start?
**Kim Geun-ho**: I have a story too. I also had a water phobia since I was young. When my family found out I was free diving, they were amazed because I wouldn't even go near water.
**Kim Eo-jun**: All of you should have gone to a hospital.
**Kim Geun-ho**: When I was very young, I fell into a valley.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Just like Han Gyu-beom.
**Kim Geun-ho**: And when I came to, there were 10,000 won and 5,000 won bills all over the tent...
**Kim Eo-jun**: Why the money?
**Kim Geun-ho**: My father jumped in with his wallet still on him to save me.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Drying out the money. It's important. Drying the son and the money.
**Kim Geun-ho**: Anyway, since then, my intelligence dropped a bit, but it's okay. (Laughter) One joke worked. So I lived with that phobia. I didn't go near water, so I didn't think about it.
**Kim Eo-jun**: You unconsciously avoided water.
**Kim Geun-ho**: Right. Even seeing the Han River made me feel a bit scared. But one day in my 20s, I went on a working holiday to Australia. I went on a Great Barrier Reef tour and tried an experience dive.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Another person who skipped learning to swim for 20 years and went straight to diving.
**Kim Geun-ho**: You have to do the famous tours when you're there. I tried the experience dive. I couldn't do it. My fear came back. I was really scared. But I paid a lot of money.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Money is important.
**Kim Geun-ho**: Right. Suddenly I thought of the tent, and thought, "I paid for this, I have to do it." So I forced myself. It was good, it was fun.
**Kim Eo-jun**: You overcame it because of the money.
**Kim Geun-ho**: It was great. So when I came back to Korea, I learned scuba diving and got my license.
**Kim Eo-jun**: You got your license?
**Kim Geun-ho**: Open water. I learned scuba diving properly.
**Kim Eo-jun**: So you overcame it.
**Kim Geun-ho**: But it didn't feel overcome. I was still really scared.
(Laughter)
**Kim Eo-jun**: You have the license but you're still scared.
**Kim Geun-ho**: Usually, a tank has 200 bar, and most people use it for about 20 minutes. But I was so excited, I used it all in 10 minutes.
**Kim Eo-jun**: You were hyperventilating because you were scared.
**Kim Geun-ho**: Yeah, so I'd show the instructor, and he'd be like, "Why are you using air so fast?" I thought it was because I'm big, but it was because I couldn't relax. Hyperventilation.
**Kim Eo-jun**: So you went in with gear, but the phobia wasn't gone.
**Kim Geun-ho**: It wasn't the right sport for me. I got the license and never went diving again.
**Kim Eo-jun**: These guys are strange. You got the license and never used it, so why free diving?
**Kim Geun-ho**: An older brother I know became an instructor. He said he'd give me a discount. In the end, it's about money.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Discount!
**Kim Geun-ho**: So I did it, and strangely, it went well.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Better than with a tank? What about the phobia?
**Kim Geun-ho**: I forgot about it. This sport, even though you don't have gear, I can just go in. Of course, I wasn't good from the start. I don't think that either. But somehow, I was the best among the students. I even became like the class president.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Then the people you met there must have thought you never had a phobia and were naturally good.
**Kim Geun-ho**: They probably think I'm naturally good.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Did you figure out why this works when other things didn't?
**Kim Geun-ho**: My guess is, since I was the class president, a sense of responsibility?
**Kim Eo-jun**: That has nothing to do with free diving. Why did you fall for this, Hong Min-ji?
**Hong Min-ji**: There's a meditation effect.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Meditation effect.
**Hong Min-ji**: We're always running our brains at full power. But when you do this, you have to use your brain less. In fact, you stop thinking altogether because you're trying to survive. You only focus on surviving, so you forget things like "I have to prepare this for my meeting later." You just forget everything and focus on enduring.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Because it's an activity tied to survival, you focus solely on that.
**Hong Min-ji**: You cast everything else aside. You just forget. You lose yourself. I'm an MBTI 'J', very 'J'. I'm always planning. My mind is busy, moving fast. But when I'm in the water...
**Kim Eo-jun**: You forget it all.
**Hong Min-ji**: Because I can put it all down. I think that's why I keep doing it.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Are you addicted?
**Hong Min-ji**: He mentioned 'water뽕' (water high). When I see water, I want to go in. It draws me in. And you know, hotel pools, people used to go there to take photos. Now, I don't even look at shallow pools. They're useless.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Useless?
**Hong Min-ji**: Right? It has to be at least 5 meters. But even 5 meters is too shallow now. I agree. That's just how it became. I think everyone agrees.
**Park Min-joo**: Actually, this is a sport that's hard to even consider starting.
**Kim Eo-jun**: There's a barrier to entry.
**Park Min-joo**: Right. You think you need to be a good swimmer, you need training, you need a lot of gear, and it's scary. But that's also part of the charm. "I do this. I went this deep." The satisfaction Hong Min-ji mentioned, and the feeling of people saying "Wow, you're amazing."
**Hong Min-ji**: If it was gym-going, you wouldn't have called us. You called us because we do this. Why are these people going so deep? It's useless.
**Kim Geun-ho**: I thought I might eventually get some media attention.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Jang Ji-hoon, who holds the only 100m diving record in Korea, also suddenly thought, "This is what I should do," and quit his job.
**Kim Geun-ho**: He quit his job to do it. He didn't do it before. These people have no foundation.
**Kim Geun-ho**: You find out very quickly. If you try an experience dive and you can't do it, you'll never do it.
**Kim Eo-jun**: He quit his job and then started, not the other way around. That's amazing.
**Kim Geun-ho**: There are people like that.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Han Gyu-beom, who had a severe phobia, you probably couldn't dive at first. How can you dive if you're afraid of water?
**Han Gyu-beom**: At first, it was really scary. We were training in a 5-meter pool, and we had to go down holding a rope. The moment I dipped my face in, I came right back up. I was so scared.
**Kim Eo-jun**: The moment you grabbed the rope?
**Han Gyu-beom**: The moment I put my face in, it was so scary. Plus, I couldn't swim. Having my whole face submerged in water was terrifying. At that point, judging by the situation, I should have quit.
**Kim Geun-ho**: There are people like this too. Let me rephrase.
**Kim Eo-jun**: How did you overcome it?
**Han Gyu-beom**: I think it was my will to be free in the water. I overcame the fear with will. I kept doing it, and bit by bit, it got better.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Why do you keep doing it, now that you've overcome it?
**Han Gyu-beom**: Like Hong Min-ji said, when I'm in the water, it's time for a conversation with myself. Only with myself.
**Kim Eo-jun**: What kind of conversation?
**Han Gyu-beom**: (Laughter) It's like meditation. I cast aside all stray thoughts, let everything go, and meet my inner self.
**Kim Eo-jun**: I asked about the content of the conversation!
**Han Gyu-beom**: "Gotta endure 5 more seconds..." Like that.
**Han Gyu-beom**: And when you're in the water, looking up at the surface is so beautiful. Pools are beautiful, but in the sea, the sunlight piercing through the surface is truly beautiful.
**Kim Eo-jun**: It gives you a fantasy-like feeling of being in an unrealistic space.
**Han Gyu-beom**: That ecstasy is so beautiful. That's why I keep doing it.
**Oh Ye-seon**: It's like a zero-gravity space. People who free dive call it 'water뽕'. I hated that word at first. "Why use such a word?" But later, I was saying "I think I'm on a water high." If I have even a bit of free time in my schedule, I'm like, "I should go diving."
**Kim Eo-jun**: Water zombies. So you only hang out with people like that? In that tank? Do they all say similar things?
**Kim Geun-ho**: Most people probably think similarly. We use similar terms, too. Like "Equalizing isn't working." The way we explain things is very similar.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Let's move on to the next step. To go deep, you need to train to adjust the pressure. That's called equalizing, pinching your nose...
**Oh Ye-seon**: I can equalize without using my hands. BTV technique.
**Kim Eo-jun**: BTV?
**Oh Ye-seon**: I move my eustachian tube directly to open it up, and it equalizes.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Without pinching your nose and blowing?
**Oh Ye-seon**: Yes, I do it without my hands.
**Kim Eo-jun**: How?
**Oh Ye-seon**: I move the muscles inside my ears. Some people have sensitive nerves for that. I didn't know I was doing it. When I was young and had ear infections, my ears would feel blocked, so I think I was doing Frenzel then. I hated my ears being blocked, so I'd always blow...
**Kim Eo-jun**: You used to do it with your hands, but then you moved certain facial muscles...
**Oh Ye-seon**: I move them inside, and I hear a clicking sound. Click, click, click. Then I can equalize without my hands. It's much more comfortable when diving because it saves oxygen.
**Kim Eo-jun**: It's possible?
**Kim Geun-ho**: Wow, really? But I'm similar. My ears used to get blocked easily since I was young.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Everyone's the same!
**Kim Geun-ho**: Right. I'm like that too. My ears get blocked easily. So in the 63 Building elevator, they'd say, "Gulp to clear your ears." At that time, I wondered why I had to swallow.
**Kim Eo-jun**: You were already doing it unconsciously.
**Kim Geun-ho**: I was equalizing, not knowing that's what it was. When I started learning, I was like, "Oh, this is it?" Then I heard "You're a genius at equalizing."
(Laughter)
**Kim Geun-ho**: That feeling of being good! That's important. "I'm a genius." This really suits me, and I got even more addicted.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Hong Min-ji.
**Hong Min-ji**: BTV is for people who are really good or lucky. Most people are recommended the Frenzel technique.
**Kim Eo-jun**: How do you do Frenzel?
**Hong Min-ji**: You pinch your nose and use pressure. Luckily, I could do that right away. I've always liked water.
**Han Gyu-beom**: Some people can't do it for months. It took me almost 7 or 8 months.
**Kim Eo-jun**: How do you know if it worked?
**Han Gyu-beom**: The instructor says "Oh, it worked."
**Kim Eo-jun**: How does he know what's happening in your ear?
**Han Gyu-beom**: He sees my movements. "Oh, you're doing it." These muscles move. The neck muscles have to move. (Shows)
**Kim Eo-jun**: Like a fish. The throat is pulsing.
**Kim Geun-ho**: What the host mentioned about pinching your nose and blowing is the Valsalva technique. But that uses abdominal pressure, which is disadvantageous for diving.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Ah, I see.
**Kim Geun-ho**: So without using abdominal pressure, you use the pressure from the root of your tongue to open the tube. That's the Frenzel technique.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Sorry, I'll explain for the listeners who might be confused. There are four main equalizing techniques. The most basic is swallowing (Toynbee). Then Valsalva. Pinching your nose and blowing with your gut. That's what people do on planes. But that uses too much oxygen and energy in the water. So the most common is Frenzel. You lock the system here... (Shows) You use the glottis... You lock the glottis... You use the air in the sinuses to open your ears.
**Kim Eo-jun**: How does that happen?
**Kim Geun-ho**: Put the tip of your tongue between your teeth and gums. Then do this. (Makes a sound)
**Oh Ye-seon**: It's hard to feel in the air, you can feel it better in the water. You have to do it in the water.
**Kim Eo-jun**: But for some people it's quick, for others it takes a long time. Park Min-joo liked water but it took 7 months.
**Park Min-joo**: Yes, and even now I'm not perfect, so I mix it with Valsalva. We call it 'Valenzel'.
**Kim Eo-jun**: What's the fourth one?
**Kim Geun-ho**: BTV. Doing it without hands.
**Kim Eo-jun**: People who are born with it. Like telekinesis, doing it without hands.
**Kim Geun-ho**: Out of 100 people, how many?
**Oh Ye-seon**: About 0.1% or 0.01%? People born with it. They say there aren't many. But for me, if the conditions are good, BTV works up to 10 or 12 meters. But deeper than that, it doesn't.
**Kim Eo-jun**: You're a 10-meter guy.
**Oh Ye-seon**: Yes. I'm up to 30 meters.
**Kim Eo-jun**: She's the best. 2 years experience. I'll defer to you. Park Min-joo liked water but it took 7 months. You didn't like water and couldn't swim, how long did it take?
**Han Gyu-beom**: It took me about 4 months. I worked really hard. I did it on my way to work, in the bathroom... I kept practicing. To the point where my nose got sore and I had to apply Vaseline.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Why was it sore?
**Han Gyu-beom**: Because I had to keep pinching and releasing it. My nose was sore.
**Kim Geun-ho**: I can see your fingerprints on your nose. I have a habit of throwing things out. Sorry.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Basically, if you can't do this, you can't go into the water.
**Kim Geun-ho**: Right. If equalizing doesn't work, the quality of free diving drops significantly.
**Kim Eo-jun**: What happens if you go in without it?
**Kim Geun-ho**: It's so painful you can't go in. Because of the pressure imbalance.
**Oh Ye-seon**: Free diving starts with equalizing.
**Kim Eo-jun**: You were always afraid of water but "free diving starts with equalizing." First, you have to match the pressure. Next, you have to hold your breath for a long time. How do you practice that?
**Oh Ye-seon**: You have to do a lot of dry training.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Dry training?
**Oh Ye-seon**: CO2 training. Training outside the water. Mental control is important. Lowering your heart rate.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Where and how do ordinary people do that?
**Hong Min-ji**: My diving center has many regular training sessions. We do something called a CO2 table. It's to build tolerance for carbon dioxide. It's like a timetable tailored to your body. You keep cycling through it. A professional instructor must be with you for safety. If you're going back and forth 50 meters, you wait 60 seconds, go and come back. Wait 50 seconds, go and come back. Wait 40 seconds... You gradually reduce the time you can breathe.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Does the time you can hold your breath really increase?
**Oh Ye-seon**: It really does. I used to hate holding my breath. We call it 'static'. To get my master's license, the requirement is 3 minutes 30 seconds. I couldn't get past 3 minutes. It was so hard. "Why can't I do what everyone else does?"
**Kim Eo-jun**: Not everyone does it.
**Oh Ye-seon**: But I'm an equalizing genius! "I equalized so well, why can't I do static?" So I started practicing on my own. Before bed, I changed the lights in my room to blue.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Everyone is crazy.
**Oh Ye-seon**: But I slept so well! I'd fall asleep doing static.
**Kim Eo-jun**: You'd fall asleep while practicing holding your breath?
**Oh Ye-seon**: I'd set it for 1 minute, relax for 1 minute 30 seconds, hold for 1 minute. Relax for 1 minute 15 seconds, hold for 1 minute.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Relaxing means breathing.
**Oh Ye-seon**: Yes, relaxing is breathing. But I relaxed too much and fell asleep.
**Han Gyu-beom**: It's a common experience. I do dry CO2 training too, and I often fall asleep while relaxing.
**Kim Eo-jun**: It lowers your heart rate, so it has a relaxing effect.
**Oh Ye-seon**: Your parasympathetic nervous system activates, and you fall asleep.
**Kim Eo-jun**: You've reached the point where it borders on sleep.
**Oh Ye-seon**: But it really helps. I increased my time to 4 minutes 11 seconds. I hit my personal best recently.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Not a pro, but 2 years of practice and you reached 4 minutes?
**Park Min-joo**: 4 minutes? Did you die? That's a eulogy.
**Kim Eo-jun**: What's everyone else's record?
**Hong Min-ji**: It's been a while for me, but it was 3 minutes 23 seconds.
**Kim Eo-jun**: 3 minutes. Park Min-joo?
**Park Min-joo**: 2 minutes 4 seconds.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Why so short? You said you liked water.
**Park Min-joo**: I'm a bit scattered. When I dip my face in, my mind starts looking for things. Like, "I should count the mold on the pool floor from here to here." My mind is busy.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Mold?
**Park Min-joo**: Counting the mold on the bottom. To forget that I have to hold my breath, I look for something to focus on. But that consumes too much oxygen. I'm using my brain too much.
**Kim Eo-jun**: What about the boyfriend?
**Han Gyu-beom**: 3 minutes.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Kim Geun-ho?
**Kim Geun-ho**: 3 minutes 28 seconds.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Peace of mind is important here.
**Kim Geun-ho**: Right. The moment you lose it, the relaxation is gone. If you start feeling anxious, your time drops significantly.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Jang Ji-hoon said the same thing. How to find a stable psychological state? When you become one with the water, you can go deep and stay longer. You're all looking for that moment of becoming one with the water.
**Oh Ye-seon**: Everyone has their own way. Finding the method that works for you is important.
**Kim Eo-jun**: What's your method?
**Oh Ye-seon**: Now I don't think about anything. But before, I'd think about my work routine at the hospital.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Thinking about something to forget the pain.
**Park Min-joo**: I think of song lyrics. Just one song.
**Kim Eo-jun**: You all do strange things.
**Oh Ye-seon**: At first, focusing helped me do well. But as I went on, my static time didn't increase. Concentrating on one thing is nothing compared to clearing your mind. So I started meditating. They said it helps a lot. I'm not a fan of meditation, I can't stay still. But it helped. This sport is very dependent on your psychological state. That makes it more charming.
**Hong Min-ji**: Right, a mental sport.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Kim Geun-ho seems like he'd be weak at mental sports. Too many thoughts. What's your maximum depth?
**Oh Ye-seon**: 26 meters.
**Kim Eo-jun**: For those who haven't learned, how deep can they go?
**Park Min-joo**: If equalizing doesn't work, even 5 meters is hard.
**Kim Eo-jun**: I'm a good swimmer. I could easily go down and back in a 5-meter pool when I was in my 20s.
**Hong Min-ji**: You must have been doing BTV. You're born with it. Or it wasn't really 5 meters.
**Kim Eo-jun**: I know that much! Today's concept is "I can do it too." How deep do beginners go? What difficulties do they face?
**Kim Geun-ho**: If you can equalize, anyone can go 5 or 10 meters. It's the ear pain that stops people. But that can take months. Then it's about holding your breath.
**Kim Eo-jun**: So 26 meters.
**Oh Ye-seon**: 33 meters.
**Kim Eo-jun**: 26m, 33m. Ordinary people can't do that even with equalizing because they can't hold their breath. Park Min-joo?
**Park Min-joo**: 12.6 meters.
**Kim Eo-jun**: She has too many thoughts. Equalizing was slow too. Han Gyu-beom?
**Han Gyu-beom**: 22 meters.
**Kim Eo-jun**: See? It has nothing to do with whether you could swim or were afraid of water.
**Kim Geun-ho**: I'm at 34.3 meters. I touched the bottom of Deep Station.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Deep Station?
**Kim Geun-ho**: It's the deepest pool in our country, in Yongin. It's called Deep Station.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Touching that bottom is a milestone.
**Kim Geun-ho**: He's doing his master's. I'm SSI level 2. Equivalent to AIDA 3. Intermediate.
**Kim Eo-jun**: What's AIDA?
**Kim Geun-ho**: A license organization.
**Kim Eo-jun**: There's AIDA, PADI, SSI... How many are there?
**Kim Geun-ho**: Quite a few. They're all international licenses. About 4 or 5 major ones. People usually ask if you're level 2 or 3.
**Kim Eo-jun**: What's intermediate?
**Hong Min-ji**: For PADI Advanced Free Diver, level 3, you have to go past 20 meters. Depth-wise. And hold your breath for about 2 minutes 30 seconds.
**Kim Eo-jun**: For someone like Han Gyu-beom, who couldn't swim and was afraid, how long to reach that level?
**Han Gyu-beom**: Some people do it in 3 or 4 months. For someone like me who had to work for it, it might take a year.
**Kim Geun-ho**: Eventually, you get there with effort. No one fails. Even me, it took 7 months, but I did it.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Even with counting mold and not practicing.
(Laughter)
**Park Min-joo**: It doesn't work well the day after drinking.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Why not?
**Park Min-joo**: Your capillaries are blocked... something about bleeding... it just doesn't work. Pressure adjustment is hard. They tell you not to drink before diving. And no caffeine. It increases your heart rate. No chocolate, no dairy.
**Kim Eo-jun**: This is related to heart rate and blood vessels. Blood oxygen concentration. I'll ask Jang Ji-hoon about that.
**Kim Eo-jun**: How did you overcome the fear?
**Oh Ye-seon**: Going in often is the answer. That's the biggest thing. To go 26 meters, the deep cylinder starts from 10 meters. Passing through that was so scary. Once I was so scared I threw off my mask and came up.
**Kim Eo-jun**: That's even scarier! You can't see anything.
**Oh Ye-seon**: I was going to die. It was a primal fear. But then I'd think, "Why am I doing this? Why am I suffering like this?" It's like going into a dark jar in the sea. The color changes suddenly.
**Kim Eo-jun**: You can see the bottom, and then suddenly you can't. It gets dark.
**Oh Ye-seon**: Right. And when the water temperature changes, fear hits you. I tried not to overcome it at first because it was scary. "I'll just go this far." But as I did it, I wanted to reach that point to say I do free diving.
**Kim Eo-jun**: So how did you overcome it?
**Oh Ye-seon**: I just went often. There was no other way but to get used to it.
**Kim Eo-jun**: So anyone can do it. No special talent needed. Now, gear. First, why a wetsuit?
**Oh Ye-seon**: Body temperature. It's cold deep down. And in water, you lose heat 25 to 30 times faster than in air.
**Kim Geun-ho**: It's in the textbook.
**Kim Eo-jun**: The speed of heat loss is fast. If you get hypothermia and start shivering, you can't stay calm. So you wear a suit for temperature. Is it warm?
**Oh Ye-seon**: Yes, you don't feel the cold at all in the sea. It's amazing.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Is there a specific free diving suit?
**Oh Ye-seon**: Yes, there is.
**Kim Eo-jun**: What about sizes?
**Oh Ye-seon**: There are many. Most people get custom-made suits.
**Kim Eo-jun**: How much?
**Hong Min-ji**: Mine was over 500,000 won. About 550,000 won.
**Oh Ye-seon**: Usually starts from 300,000 to 400,000 won. Cheap ones are 300,000 won. There are even 100,000 or 200,000 won ones.
**Kim Eo-jun**: What's the difference with expensive ones?
**Oh Ye-seon**: Flexibility. It's much more comfortable.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Expensive ones are 700,000 to 800,000 won. That's not too bad.
**Oh Ye-seon**: And pools rent them out now, so you don't necessarily need one to learn.
**Kim Eo-jun**: But you have to buy the gear first. Gear high! Hobbies are about gear. You have to buy it and touch it and think "When can I use this?" You know what I mean!
**Kim Geun-ho**: Right, gear is a big part of it.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Does the suit cover your whole body?
**Oh Ye-seon**: Not hands and feet. Your face is out, of course.
**Kim Eo-jun**: What about people who aren't a standard size?
**Kim Geun-ho**: If you go where I recommend, they have up to 65 sizes. Give me a call.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Next, goggles.
**Hong Min-ji**: We call them masks. They're different from normal goggles because they cover your nose. You have to equalize, so it has to be soft and flexible around the nose.
**Kim Eo-jun**: How much?
**Park Min-joo**: Cheap ones are around 100,000 won. It depends on the material, glass or plastic.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Glass would be more expensive.
**Park Min-joo**: High-strength glass.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Expensive ones?
**Park Min-joo**: Around 200,000 or 300,000 won. 150,000 won.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Suit 700,000, mask 300,000. Next, snorkel.
**Han Gyu-beom**: You use it while relaxing on the surface before you go in. You face the water and relax.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Next, fins. Long fins.
**Oh Ye-seon**: Cheap ones are about 200,000 won. Expensive ones are around 1 million won.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Those are more expensive.
**Oh Ye-seon**: Good ones are made of carbon. Light and powerful. Great propulsion. They're bouncy. There are mono-fins (one piece) and bi-fins (two pieces). Pros use mono-fins.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Most people use bi-fins. So for under 2 million won, you can get good gear. That's cheap for a gear-heavy sport. You can buy it all online.
**Oh Ye-seon**: It's cheapest through an instructor.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Any other gear?
**Kim Geun-ho**: A computer. A diving computer that tracks depth.
**Kim Eo-jun**: A watch?
**Kim Geun-ho**: Why call it a computer? It's not just for time.
**Han Gyu-beom**: It's a Garmin Descent... Should I not say the brand?
(Laughter)
**Kim Eo-jun**: Are you worried it'll sell too well? Anyway, a watch. In this world, it's a computer. It syncs with an app, so it shows where I dived, how many times, how deep, and the temperature.
**Kim Eo-jun**: An Apple Watch does more than that, but we call it a watch. I can't win this argument. Anyway, a computer. They were using it before these fancy apps came out, so they called it a computer. Suit, fins, snorkel, computer. Anything else?
**Oh Ye-seon**: A lanyard. It's like a lifeline. In the sea, we use a buoy. We drop a rope from the buoy to practice depth. You tie yourself to that so you don't get swept away by the current. Most important gear in the sea.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Doesn't the buoy get swept away too? How do you fix the buoy?
**Han Gyu-beom**: There's a fixed buoy. Or it's connected to the bottom. Sometimes we use a heavy lead weight. Or sometimes the buoy just drifts, and a boat stays nearby.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Do you dive without it?
**Hong Min-ji**: For 'fun diving', looking at things underwater.
**Kim Eo-jun**: 'Fun' diving. (Laughter) You use strange terms. How is it different from snorkeling?
**Hong Min-ji**: Snorkeling is just on the surface. Breathing through the snorkel. With a life jacket. You can't go down with a life jacket.
**Kim Eo-jun**: So you go to the sea. For people who can't swim, it's impossible.
**Han Gyu-beom**: You can do it if you have fins. Fins are powerful, they overcome the current. You feel like a swimmer. The suit provides buoyancy too. You might not know how to swim, but with training and gear, you're like a pro.
**Kim Eo-jun**: You learned free diving without learning to swim. And you're swimming in the sea with a suit and fins?
**Han Gyu-beom**: Yes, in the water.
**Kim Eo-jun**: What about on the surface?
**Han Gyu-beom**: You can just float. Because of the suit's buoyancy. We set it for neutral buoyancy at 10 meters.
**Oh Ye-seon**: With the suit and a weight belt. You wear lead on your waist. So at 10 meters, you neither float nor sink.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Your lungs are full. 'Full-lung'. (Laughter)
**Oh Ye-seon**: You find the right balance for yourself. You keep adding weight until you're neutral at 10 meters.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Neutral buoyancy isn't a hard concept. You don't float or sink at 10 meters.
**Han Gyu-beom**: You have to find that. So at the surface, you float.
**Kim Eo-jun**: So there's no fear of drowning.
**Han Gyu-beom**: If you wear fins! I can't swim, so fins give me confidence. Confidence that I won't die.
**Kim Eo-jun**: You really need to see a doctor. You wear fins even on land? For confidence?
**Han Gyu-beom**: They're that powerful. I'm also not a good swimmer, but with fins, I feel like a pro. One kick and you're gone. It's anyone's sport. And you get addicted.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Addicted to 'no thoughts', 'conversation with yourself'. Many reasons. So you only hang out at the pool, then eventually go to the sea?
**Guests**: Yes.
**Kim Eo-jun**: You like the dark sea where you can't see the bottom?
**Oh Ye-seon**: I like it more. Passing through that dark cylinder in the pool. After overcoming that fear, it's gone.
**Han Gyu-beom**: I'm still scared, but I enjoy it.
**Kim Eo-jun**: I was curious about that because I've felt it. It's scary. Warm here, cold there.
**Oh Ye-seon**: It's scary, but curiosity is bigger. "I want to go down there."
**Kim Eo-jun**: It's scary for someone who hasn't swum in the sea. But you're saying anyone can do it. And you must go with a buddy.
**Hong Min-ji**: Buddy system. Always. Anything can happen underwater. You could black out. Your buddy has to save you.
**Kim Eo-jun**: In that sense, it's a very safe sport. So you'll keep looking for places abroad? Pools are always the same. There, it's just about training to go deeper and hold your breath longer. You want to use that ability in the sea.
**Hong Min-ji**: Ultimately, we want to be natural sea divers, not just pool divers.
**Kim Eo-jun**: How is it different from the pool?
**Oh Ye-seon**: Meeting marine life, fish. And the sea has its own sound. Snap, pop, pop. It feels like the water is embracing me.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Go to a hospital!
**Oh Ye-seon**: Really. It feels like the water is warmly hugging me. I feel like a fish.
**Hong Min-ji**: The scene keeps changing. Fish aren't always in the same place. I went to the East Sea recently. The weather wasn't great, so visibility was poor. But there were so many fish! Baby pufferfish! That's the joy of sea diving.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Did you eat the pufferfish? No, the scenery changes. Are there major spots in Korea?
**Kim Geun-ho**: Ulleungdo is the best. So clear and clean. Visibility is great. Lots of fish.
**Oh Ye-seon**: It's great, but getting there is so hard. 3 hours on a boat, the seasickness is no joke.
**Kim Eo-jun**: I don't want to know about that. Ulleungdo is famous. Any others?
**Han Gyu-beom**: Janghohang, Gallamhang in Gangwon-do. Goseong, Ayajin, Songjiho.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Clear water and lots of life. What about abroad?
**Hong Min-ji**: So many. I went to Saipan in August. Tinian Island. A 10-minute flight on a small plane. The water is 'Pong-ta' color.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Pong-ta?
**Hong Min-ji**: The ice cream. Soda color. (Shows a photo)
**Kim Eo-jun**: I've never eaten that. Pass. (Laughter) Sky blue.
**Hong Min-ji**: Emerald green. It's beautiful.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Like toilet bowl cleaner?
(Laughter)
**Kim Eo-jun**: You went there just for free diving.
**Hong Min-ji**: To feast my eyes. I only went with my boyfriend. He doesn't free dive.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Then he's not a buddy.
**Hong Min-ji**: Right, so I only stayed in shallow water.
**Kim Eo-jun**: You broke the rule! Where's your buddy?
**Hong Min-ji**: Sorry.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Why doesn't he learn? It'd be good to do it together.
**Hong Min-ji**: He's going to start next year. He felt helpless just staying on the surface while I was down there.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Why next year? Do it now.
**Hong Min-ji**: He's doing tennis. It's not even that great of a sport!
(Laughter)
**Kim Eo-jun**: You'd want to do it together.
**Kim Geun-ho**: Soul buddy.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Han Gyu-beom started because of another woman.
**Han Gyu-beom**: No, absolutely not.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Think back. Those two women. Did they only wear bikinis? Anyway, what's your goal?
**Oh Ye-seon**: I started because of Ulleungdo, and after going there, I felt a bit empty. Like, "What now?" I've improved a lot, so I'm thinking of trying for an official record.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Free diving makes you feel that. "Can I go deeper? Can I get a record?" The sense of accomplishment is big.
**Oh Ye-seon**: "I did it! Again!" It's addictive. No one thinks "I should enter a tournament" after a year of tennis or golf.
**Kim Eo-jun**: But this makes you think that way.
**Oh Ye-seon**: Many people come because of photos, but then they get serious.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Hong Min-ji.
**Hong Min-ji**: I want to keep breaking my personal record. And keep it as a lifelong hobby. It's not a competition with others.
**Kim Eo-jun**: A competition with yourself.
**Hong Min-ji**: Tournaments are unique too. It's not just about winning. Even if someone only goes 10 meters, if they achieve what they said they would, they get a white card. It's very charming. Achieving that record gives you confidence in daily life.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Park Min-joo hasn't reached that point yet.
**Park Min-joo**: I've only done 12 meters. I want to start AIDA 3 this year. And go abroad for fun diving next year.
**Kim Eo-jun**: You've been together for 7 years?
**Park Min-joo**: Yes.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Time to break up. Kim Geun-ho, what about your girlfriend?
**Kim Geun-ho**: I don't have one. Don't ask.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Oh Ye-seon, what about your boyfriend?
**Oh Ye-seon**: He's not a fan. He tells me to only do it as long as it's not dangerous.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Strange. Usually, people get curious and follow.
**Oh Ye-seon**: I like enjoying it alone. We've been together for 5 or 6 years. Time to break up.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Hong Min-ji, you've known him a long time but only recently started dating.
**Hong Min-ji**: Those couples don't last long. (Laughter) Everyone is losing something here. I'm the only one staying the course.
**Kim Eo-jun**: It's portrayed as very romantic in movies. Don't do that too much. Han Gyu-beom, why is it good to do it together?
**Han Gyu-beom**: I need a long time to relax. Before going in, I need to lower my heart rate. It takes me a while. But when I'm with Min-joo, I feel more supported and relaxed than with other buddies.
**Park Min-joo**: Since it's always a buddy system, it's like going on a date.
**Kim Eo-jun**: But Oh Ye-seon doesn't want to.
**Oh Ye-seon**: I like it alone. Not disappointed at all. It's better. New opportunities arise. (Laughter)
**Kim Eo-jun**: Hong Min-ji saw him diving and wanted to learn. Do you want to learn together?
**Hong Min-ji**: We promised to get married. So he'll have to do it.
**Kim Eo-jun**: When did you promise?
**Hong Min-ji**: In Saipan.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Cut that out. Was there a proposal?
**Hong Min-ji**: Yes. Is that too much TMI?
**Kim Eo-jun**: When is the wedding?
**Hong Min-ji**: Not set yet.
**Kim Eo-jun**: You have to do it to know. Let's finish up. None of you are athletes, none had special training, none were good swimmers. But after seeing someone do it, you jumped in. What do you want to say to people who are hesitant?
**Oh Ye-seon**: Just come. Try it once and see if it suits you. I'm telling everyone around me.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Some people get hooked after one try.
**Kim Geun-ho**: Right. Like I said, you find out quickly. Most people get hooked.
**Han Gyu-beom**: Just come to the water. It changes everything. No one who sees that beautiful sight can resist.
**Park Min-joo**: I'm trying to recruit everyone. I even pay for their experience dive!
**Kim Eo-jun**: Why go that far?
**Park Min-joo**: It's so much fun, I want to share it.
**Kim Geun-ho**: I recommend it to everyone too. Not sure why.
**Hong Min-ji**: I only recommend it to those who really want to do it. It takes a lot of time. It's far, you have to pack a lot of gear. If you're going to do it, do it right. If you're hesitant, just don't do it.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Cut that out too.
**Kim Geun-ho**: There's a brand called Cressi. Their YouTube ad is very fantasy-like. I send the link to everyone. "This is how you should dive."
**Kim Eo-jun**: Lastly, the cost.
**Oh Ye-seon**: Initial cost is 100,000 won for an experience dive.
**Han Gyu-beom**: Usually 50,000 to 100,000 won.
**Hong Min-ji**: Up to level 3, excluding gear, it cost me about 1 million won.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Less than I thought. What about pool fees?
**Oh Ye-seon**: 5-meter pool is about 20,000 won. 25,000 won. Some are 5,000 won.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Deeper ones?
**Oh Ye-seon**: There are two. K-26 in Gapyeong and Deep Station in Yongin. Gapyeong is 33,000 won weekdays, 55,000 won weekends. Yongin is 44,000 won and 66,000 won.
**Kim Eo-jun**: That's the entrance fee.
**Oh Ye-seon**: For 3 hours. Instruction is separate.
**Kim Eo-jun**: So you pack your gear and drive there. Alone?
**Hong Min-ji**: I go with buddies from the center, or meet them there.
**Kim Eo-jun**: What does the buddy do while you're diving?
**Oh Ye-seon**: They watch from above. To see if you're okay.
**Kim Eo-jun**: They only watch that person. If you're going 30 meters, they follow you down to 20 meters. They come up with you because blackouts happen most often near the surface.
**Kim Eo-jun**: You have to save them if they lose consciousness. They're on standby, watching. When you come up, you make eye contact.
**Kim Geun-ho**: That's when sparks fly! (Laughter)
**Kim Geun-ho**: But it's hard to see their eyes. And it's a bit burdensome if they keep staring. I'm embarrassed to show my raw self.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Overcome that first!
**Kim Geun-ho**: Right.
**Kim Eo-jun**: But you come up making eye contact. "You're alive, I'm alive." Checking each other. Sparks could fly. It's romantic.
**Han Gyu-beom**: Actually, it's just awkward.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Maybe you didn't like her. (Laughter) Some people do fall in love. You have to give people some hope! This is a very charming sport. It's not as well-known in Korea, and the barrier to entry isn't that high. Anyone can do it. You can even date. That's the point of today's broadcast. Anyone can do it. Even Oh Ye-seon, me, Kim Geun-ho... Even Park Min-joo and Han Gyu-beom!
**Han Gyu-beom**: Soul buddy.
**Kim Eo-jun**: Don't say that. It's scary. Very dangerous. (Laughter) Thank you for being here today.
**Guests**: Thank you.
(Outro music)