Transcribed from the audio:
**Kim Eo-jun:** Hello, I'm Kim Eo-jun. Monthly Kim Eo-jun, classic edition. Master Cho Yoon-beom is here. Hello.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Long time no see. Glad to see you.
**Kim Eo-jun:** And our graduate, Master Kim Ka-ram.
**Kim Ka-ram:** Hello.
**Kim Eo-jun:** We had a recording schedule before. Master Kim Ka-ram went to Paris, and Master Cho Yoon-beom went through the water pipe works.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Yeah, the water pipe at home suddenly burst...
**Kim Eo-jun:** Urgent call? It's more urgent than going abroad. So, where did Master Kim Ka-ram go?
**Kim Ka-ram:** I only went to Paris. I had some schedules for next year and other things to settle.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Performance schedules?
**Kim Ka-ram:** Probably.
**Kim Eo-jun:** In Europe?
**Kim Ka-ram:** Yes.
**Kim Eo-jun:** How about Master Cho Yoon-beom?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** I got a call from Czechia recently. They asked if I could perform there next year.
**Kim Eo-jun:** From Czechia? Why?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** I wonder.
**Kim Eo-jun:** With the team?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Our Quartetto Fantastico team isn't confirmed yet.
**Kim Ka-ram:** The response might be late because the director of the Korean Cultural Center in France is currently vacant.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** It seems the whole world is vacant right now. Is it because our President is busy?
**Kim Eo-jun:** It fits. A lot of things are vacant. Let's talk about music. Who are we talking about today?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** We talked about Mendelssohn before. We'll talk about Schumann, who was one year younger and a close friend of Mendelssohn.
**Kim Eo-jun:** My understanding of people is very shallow, you know.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** After hearing the name?
**Kim Eo-jun:** I decide after hearing the name or seeing one photo. I looked up Schumann's photo once. He looks like a Greco-Roman wrestler.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** It's been a long time since I heard 'Greco-Roman'. Like during the LA Olympics.
**Kim Eo-jun:** He looks bulky and rugged. This guy must have lived a hard life.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** His life itself was very difficult.
**Kim Eo-jun:** I'm all about looks, you know. So his face is unusual. He has muscles on his face. Gloomy muscles.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** That's right.
**Kim Eo-jun:** I've said all I know. Finish!
**Cho Yoon-beom:** He was actually a very struggling person emotionally. He ended up in a mental hospital and died there.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Then it's understandable he has facial muscles.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** He spent his whole life fighting, and things rarely went as he wished. Mendelssohn was very famous back then, while Schumann was treated like a supporting character.
**Kim Eo-jun:** What is Schumann famous for, primarily?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Musically, his short piece 'Träumerei' is very famous.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Träumerei?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** You'll recognize the melody if you hear it. It's called 'Träumerei', meaning a small dream. Some people mistake it for 'Echo of Troy' (Troy-merai).
**Kim Eo-jun:** Troy's echo?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** 'Echo of Troy' from Roman times. But if you look closely, it's 'Träumerei'. (Troy-mer-ai).
**Cho Yoon-beom:** People kept reading it that way. Not 'Echo' but 'Merei'. I used to do that too.
**Kim Eo-jun:** It's easy to get confused. Only the order of 'L' and 'NG' is swapped.
**Kim Ka-ram:** In German, 'Traum' means dream. Adding 'ei' makes 'Träumerei', something small, precious, and cute.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Our Master Kim Ka-ram has deep knowledge, maybe because she graduated. 'Echo of Troy'. Träumerei. Is this his most famous piece?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** It's the most famous, but I'll play it a bit later.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Master, you'll perform it, right?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** She will perform it directly.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Master Kim Ka-ram performs with her facial expressions too. With her expression and shoulder line.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Shoulder line.
**Kim Eo-jun:** When you do a concert, please write that down as a quote from me. 'Performs with expression and shoulder line'.
**Kim Ka-ram:** Masters often leave comments like that.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** A master's comment.
**Kim Ka-ram:** Like being captured by telepathy.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Don't use the full name, just 'Mr. Kim'.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Or 'Monthly Kim'.
**Kim Eo-jun:** People need to see this. See Master Kim Ka-ram's performance with expression and shoulder line. She didn't know herself. I told her. So please quote me. So, 'Echo of Troy'.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Träumerei. Because it's so famous, most people hear this first. So they get the wrong image of Schumann.
**Kim Eo-jun:** They understand him through the image of this piece.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** But the first piece I requested is much more complex. Schumann once said, 'I like playing with forms'. He plays with forms a lot. It's almost excessive. So pianists find Schumann's piano pieces very difficult. It doesn't sound that difficult to listeners, but playing is very hard.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Let's hear it directly from the pianist.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Violinists never properly evaluate Schumann. His true self is all in the piano.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Really?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Yes.
**Kim Ka-ram:** I totally agree. Schumann's father was a bookseller, so he was active as a man of letters from a young age. The expression 'playing with forms' is very accurate. He breaks all existing forms, and there are many characters within. Usually, there's a transition period of a few bars between stories for plausibility, but Schumann doesn't have that. While talking about something, another character suddenly pops out. It happens again and again during performance. Feelings change abruptly without a break. It's emotionally complex and exciting on stage, yet technically difficult.
**Kim Eo-jun:** I don't know what you're talking about.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Simply put, a melody should end, but right before it ends, the next melody pushes in half a beat early.
**Kim Ka-ram:** Exactly.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** There's a lot of that. It's the same for string instruments too.
**Kim Eo-jun:** People who don't know classics won't understand.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** It might be good to hear that hasty melody directly.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Let's try the performance first. It's short. Schumann has three piano sonatas. This is the 'Scherzo' movement from Piano Sonata No. 3.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Sonata No. 3, Scherzo?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** A Scherzo piece sounds like it's bouncing, somewhat grotesque and playful.
**Kim Eo-jun:** 'Jjo' is tasty.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Style is tasty. Scherzo.
**Kim Eo-jun:** I like this. He was emotionally unstable.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Very unstable.
**Kim Eo-jun:** I like this. He composed however he wanted.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** There's no 'I did...'. Right after 'I did...', he goes 'But...'. Always, in every melody.
**Kim Eo-jun:** When Master Kim Ka-ram performs, her expression and posture say, 'Hey you, I'm playing yours now. You composed it like this, right? I'll feel it all.'
**Kim Ka-ram:** There are many pieces that require determination.
**Kim Eo-jun:** It felt like she was fighting with the sheet music.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Fighting with the score is right. You have to approach Schumann with a fighting spirit.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Master Kim Ka-ram usually doesn't show much expression or head movement, but she's fighting with the score now.
**Kim Ka-ram:** Yes, there was some today.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Schumann, you punk! You did it like that again, you punk! Okay! Like that. Like, 'Hey, really...'. 'Bring it on, I'll beat you with my fingers.' I like this. The music lacks introduction, development, turn, and conclusion.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** The turn comes too quickly after the introduction, then it suddenly ends.
**Kim Eo-jun:** I like this.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** What's interesting is Schumann does this in slow music as well as fast music. So the performer doesn't know where to take a breath and struggles.
**Kim Eo-jun:** He seems emotionally unstable. His emotions seem to fluctuate extremely.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** He had bipolar disorder too.
**Kim Eo-jun:** The music is like that. I like it. What was it?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Schumann's Piano Sonata No. 3, the movement called Scherzo.
**Kim Eo-jun:** 'Jjo' Schumann. Do pianists like this piece?
**Kim Ka-ram:** Personally, I like it because it at least has some form. It has some structural beauty. He has many piano works, and some of them are truly... like a whole new world. Crazy.
**Kim Eo-jun:** A flood of emotions.
**Kim Ka-ram:** It's very diverse and abundant. So while playing, personalities I didn't know I had...
**Kim Eo-jun:** Multiple personalities emerge?
**Kim Ka-ram:** Yes, I even face the petty sides within me. On the other hand, I discover, 'Did I have such beautiful emotions inside?'
**Kim Eo-jun:** What kind of emotions?
**Kim Ka-ram:** I'll tell you later when we talk about 'Echo of Troy'.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Echo of Troy. What kind of life did he lead to become like this?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** His father was a bookseller and later a publisher. He grew up as a literary boy, reading tons of books.
**Kim Eo-jun:** He grew up absorbing humanities.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** But he fluctuated. He had an older sister. When Schumann was 15, his sister committed suicide.
**Kim Eo-jun:** That must have been a huge mental shock.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Whether she jumped from a window or into a river isn't well known.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Losing a sibling is different from losing a parent.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** But he experienced both at once. After his daughter died, his father collapsed from shock and died the following year.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Consecutive blows.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** He had many older brothers. Uniquely, he was close to his sisters-in-law. One of them also died suddenly. The woman he liked later became his third sister-in-law. She married his brother. That brother died later. His close sister-in-law died too. His personality completely changed then.
**Kim Eo-jun:** He must have felt a huge sense of loss.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** His father was supportive of his music.
**Kim Eo-jun:** What about his mother?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** His mother was more musically talented, but after the family fell apart, she opposed her youngest son doing music. She wanted him to have a stable job and sent him to law school.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Usually, children form a relationship with their mother like they did with their father. He might not have formed a sufficient emotional bond with his mother. He bonded with his sister or sister-in-law, but they all died.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** He didn't bond well because she was very ill when he was 2 or 3, so he was raised in another house. He grew up at a local grocery store during his infancy, so he was separated from his mother and had little bond with her.
**Kim Eo-jun:** When everyone you bonded with dies at once, your emotional growth can stop at that moment. You stop growing and stay there. Some people live their whole lives like that, like at age 15.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** You could say he stopped there. He changed that much. He started drinking heavily.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Well, one can drink. Some people even become president after drinking.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** That's a problem! Don't drink too much and then come to a sweet-home.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Just compose. Many strange works must have come out.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Great! He was that kind of person. This music also goes up and down, like what we just heard. He must have been lonely.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** He had a unique way of enduring loneliness. He used his imagination. Later, he organized a club. He put famous historical figures he knew on the member list. He played with them, virtually.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Multiple personalities.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** He announced it. 'There are several people inside me.'
**Kim Eo-jun:** He expressed those multiple personalities through music.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** He gave them all names. Characters inside him. Like Eusebius and Florestan.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Do they appear when he writes?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** He wrote under those names. He composed under those names, or used them as titles.
**Kim Eo-jun:** A sensitive literary boy with musical talent. After losing everyone he bonded with around the same time during his growth, he regressed.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** But since he had a strong literary background, he tried to turn that into works. He expressed it through art forms like writing and music.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Among musicians, he's probably recognized as the best writer.
**Kim Eo-jun:** A literary boy who could also perform?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** He was a good performer. He wanted to be a pianist originally.
**Kim Eo-jun:** But with a face like that... I suddenly understand this guy. He was born with artistic sensitivity and delicacy. Then tragedies struck like fate. But looking in the mirror, he sees a Greco-Roman wrestler. In this case, one either can't date at all or becomes extremely obsessed with it.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** It's the latter. He had to fill the void. What's more intense than romance?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** His portrait when he was older is Greco-Roman, but he was quite slender when young.
**Kim Eo-jun:** The frame is there. I think I know what kind of person he was. I'll understand better after hearing the music. So his mother sent him to law school?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Yes, to Leipzig.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Where was he born?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Zwickau.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Zwickau is a small town. Most people wouldn't know it. It was in East Germany. About the distance between Seoul and Daejeon from Dresden. There was a car called Trabant there, the national car of East Germany. Known for extremely poor performance and lowest durability. But the exterior was pretty. Right after the opening of the Eastern Bloc in '90, '91, '92... I went to Dresden and saw the Trabant for the first time. It was so pretty. But the exhaust smoke! I really wanted to buy it. The shape is classic, but the inside is trash. The factory was in Zwickau.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Anyway, he went to Leipzig for university. But he hated law more than anything. There's almost no record of him attending classes. He signed up for lessons instead. He went to a music teacher, asking for piano lessons. There was a very famous teacher then, Friedrich Wieck, who made many people famous. Schumann learned piano under him. While taking lessons, he wanted to become a great pianist, so he used a strange machine on his fingers that was popular then.
**Kim Eo-jun:** A machine?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** A machine made of cigar boxes. Like a pulley, it ties the fingers and has sandbags attached like an IV. He kept lifting his fingers.
**Kim Eo-jun:** For finger training. Like finger dumbbells.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** On the piano, if you don't lift your fingers enough, you accidentally press other keys.
**Kim Eo-jun:** What do you know about piano? Please explain. Finger torture?
**Kim Ka-ram:** We say playing the piano well requires independent muscles for each of the ten fingers. Like athletes, the muscles need training. But the muscles attached to the hands are fine, not large muscles. So we do training to develop those muscles. For example, when I was young, to increase the power of my fingertips, I would put thick English dictionaries in a shoe bag and hang it while practicing.
**Kim Eo-jun:** On your fingers?
**Kim Ka-ram:** No, on my wrists. Then gravity pulls the weight down.
**Kim Eo-jun:** On your wrists?
**Kim Ka-ram:** Yes. In that state, I practiced lifting and lowering my fingers. Not hanging it on the fingers.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** But Schumann hung it on his fingers.
**Kim Eo-jun:** That's too much.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** It wasn't an official method. It was unofficial, like a back-alley method. A back-alley finger dumbbell. He picked it up somewhere. He was doing finger lifts. His teacher saw him practicing like that and told him to stop. 'You'll ruin your muscles.' He did ruin them.
**Kim Eo-jun:** So his career as a pianist ended then?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** He was frustrated. It wasn't like 'you can't play at all', but he gave up on becoming a famous pianist. His finger function declined. He tried rehabilitation, but it didn't work.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Are there people like that among pianists?
**Kim Ka-ram:** Fingers are one thing, but there are things like neck discs. We practice for hours sitting without a backrest, leaning forward. We keep using our bodies, so it's physically demanding. After turning 40, some people can't perform due to physical strain.
**Kim Eo-jun:** But hanging dumbbells on fingers...
**Kim Ka-ram:** That's too much.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** So Schumann's future as a pianist was gone in his early 20s. He and his teacher gave up. The teacher had high expectations at first. He even told Schumann's mother, who was paying for lessons, 'Give him a few years under me, and I can make him an incredible pianist.' He was very confident. He had a reason for that confidence. 'Look at my daughter. She's already a child prodigy.' She was 9. He claimed he could make Schumann like her with his teaching method. But since Schumann ended up like that, the teacher focused all his attention on his daughter. Schumann didn't give up on learning piano, but instead, he started a romance.
**Kim Eo-jun:** With whom?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** First with the housekeeper of that house.
**Kim Eo-jun:** He was open-minded.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** After dating the housekeeper, he dated another student of Professor Wieck.
**Kim Eo-jun:** He started with the housekeeper, so all doors were already open.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** He dated around, then went back to the housekeeper. His final destination was the 9-year-old daughter.
**Kim Eo-jun:** That's child abuse, isn't it?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Years passed and the girl grew up.
**Kim Eo-jun:** When they developed romantic feelings, she must have been 15 or 18.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Still, there was a big age gap. Nine years. When he first came to the teacher's house, she was just a kid.
**Kim Eo-jun:** The age gap isn't much once they're older, but 10s and 20s...
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Her name was Clara Wieck. She later became Clara Schumann. The famous Clara Schumann who appeared in our Brahms and Mendelssohn lectures.
**Kim Eo-jun:** She lived her life as a pianist after that.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Since she was the teacher's daughter, the teacher wouldn't approve.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Especially when he's a Greco-Roman wrestler and his future as a pianist is bleak. I wouldn't give him my daughter.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** He opposed it vehemently. It was no joke. He even set up legal measures. If she married Schumann, she wouldn't inherit anything. But Professor Wieck's opposition had a benefit. He blocked all men approaching Clara. The competitors disappeared. Schumann just had to succeed.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Not everything goes as planned in the world. Especially relationships. He cleared the path, and Schumann just had to walk it. The problem was his remaining path—his major was law.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Who knows what will happen. He hated law so much.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Law was what he hated most, but he turned out to be a legal expert. He thought he could attack his future father-in-law with law. He sued him.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Sued his father-in-law? For blocking the marriage? To allow him to marry her legally?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** He sued him.
**Kim Eo-jun:** What an excessive guy. His whole life has an excessive side.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** First, he sued for defamation. Professor Wieck badmouthed him to stop the marriage. One of the main points was that Schumann drank too much.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Just the mention of alcohol is good lately. It makes me laugh. Should I follow the alcohol poisoning? Memory declines.
**Kim Ka-ram:** Actually, drinking a lot of alcohol damages the frontal lobe.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** If the frontal lobe is damaged, don't you get angry easily?
**Kim Ka-ram:** Yes, and autonomic nervous system control becomes difficult.
**Kim Eo-jun:** You forget what you just said. Yesterday was Armed Forces Day. At the ceremony, the President received a salute and had to give the 'At ease' command. He forgot it. 'Unit, at ease.' He should have done it so the commander could command the whole unit. Otherwise, they have to stay at attention. But he forgot and just blinked. He receiving the salute and then should say 'at ease'. How could he forget that? Looking at Schumann, it must be the alcohol. I'm sure they told him. It's just one step. One. 'Unit, at ease'. Maybe if there were three steps... but just one! Anyway, back to Schumann. He got away with it through law. He claimed there was no evidence of him drinking too much.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Lack of evidence.
**Kim Eo-jun:** There's evidence here, video of what he said! I didn't say it! Back to Schumann. He sued.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** He escaped the alcohol issue through lack of evidence. Then the professor mentioned schizophrenia. 'He used two strange names when writing before. He fluctuates.'
**Kim Eo-jun:** Multiple personalities.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** And that he has no future. Because of his broken finger, he wouldn't earn much money. 'If you want my daughter, you must earn at least this much per month.'
**Kim Eo-jun:** A father could say that. But there's no legal basis.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Eventually, he won the trial and got married, but those words always stayed in his mind. He always thought about it.
**Kim Eo-jun:** What did the daughter see?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** She saw him since she was a kid. Taking lessons in the same house.
**Kim Eo-jun:** All other men were blocked by her father, and she only saw this guy dating.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** And when there's so much opposition, doesn't it create a stubbornness? He's even suing for our love. How much must he love me to go to court?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Clara was actually in a difficult position in the middle. He was suing her father.
**Kim Eo-jun:** No, girls that age aren't in a difficult position. They are moved by the burning love for them, more than their father. Would she have married him if she were in a difficult position?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** She was a kid who traveled abroad and performed, but her father was always next to her.
**Kim Eo-jun:** She must have wanted to escape her father.
**Kim Eo-jun:** She could marry him because of that special situation. The father strictly protected and blocked everything, but the Greco-Roman wrestler broke through. She might have been moved.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Someone helped Schumann win this trial. Professor Wieck's ex-wife.
**Kim Eo-jun:** 'My husband was always like that.' Sounds like a soap opera.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** So when they got married, the father didn't come, but the biological mother did.
**Kim Eo-jun:** So Schumann had a side that appealed to women. The mother-in-law took his side.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Most of his acquaintances were on his side. Their social circles overlapped in the music world, and most supported him. Professor Wieck's personality had some issues too.
**Kim Eo-jun:** He must have had a lovable side. Or triggered protective instincts. Okay, I understand Schumann. So he married Clara.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** After marrying Clara, he simultaneously tried to prove he was a proper person. He tried to get a doctoral degree.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Getting a doctoral degree... Why does it feel so automatic these days? Doctoral degree.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** And he started a magazine. At that time, he wasn't known as a composer or pianist.
**Kim Eo-jun:** A critic?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** He was known as a critic and editor-in-chief of a music magazine. Neue Zeitschrift für Musik. It still exists.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Since he could perform and had musical talent, plus writing skills... He could perform and was a great music critic. He had a standing.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** He saw a performer named Chopin and was amazed, so he wrote a review. He submitted it to another magazine, but the exaggeration was too much. The review was too literary. Like 'God has descended'.
**Kim Eo-jun:** He was being over the top.
**Kim Eo-jun:** I know what kind of person he was.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** For such people, there's a solution. Make your own magazine. If nobody accepts your writing. So he made one. He started making a name for himself as an editor-in-chief.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Now, let's hear 'Echo of Troy'.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Träumerei. It's a collection of small piano pieces called Kinderszenen.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Why childhood?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** He wanted to express childhood scenes. While he was writing this, Clara said, 'I'm under 9 years old, do you see me as a child?' He expressed childhood sensitivity, and just hearing it makes you feel it's truly pure.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Childhood sensitivity... I'll listen and decide with my sensitivity. Small dream, the famous Träumerei.
**Kim Eo-jun:** I know this. This is Schumann. Master, why were you leaning to the left while playing?
**Kim Ka-ram:** I don't know why I do that either.
**Kim Eo-jun:** When she started, her body leaned about 10 degrees to the left. She didn't sit straight, she was crooked.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** You didn't know yourself?
**Kim Eo-jun:** She's not always crooked. She was crooked for this one. For most of the performance, she was leaning to the left.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Because she's a progressive performer.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Is she left-wing?
**Kim Eo-jun:** There were two features this time. One, the harmony changed in the middle, right? She smiled then. Then, what should I say... like nursing?
**Kim Ka-ram:** Right. This is Kinderszenen. A child's dream, not an adult's. A child dreaming while being nursed. I played it with that feeling.
**Kim Eo-jun:** But why did you nurse towards the left? Hearing this, I felt he was a lonely person. It felt sad. Like you said, his emotional growth might have stopped at 15. Regressive sensitivity. That feeling of being comfortable, safe, and surrounded by loved ones back then. He doesn't have that now. So he's lonely and misses it. It was sad knowing that. I think I'm sensitive.
**Kim Ka-ram:** That's right. Schumann found it difficult to interact with others, and the only ones he felt comfortable with were children. He probably wanted to keep going back to himself as a child or a 10-year-old. But he couldn't, so he was lonely. He was left alone in the adult world.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** He originally wanted to do music and grow while being praised. But now he's running a magazine, promoting others. He introduced Chopin and Brahms, but nobody was praising him.
**Kim Eo-jun:** He gave others the praise he wanted to receive.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** He can't perform anyway. He wants to be recognized for composition, but he doesn't get proper recognition.
**Kim Eo-jun:** That 'Scherzo' would have been hard to applaud back then.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** He didn't write things that people would like. When people suggested writing trendy things, he said, 'I can't write that.' Furthermore, his contemporaries considered him very conservative.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Why?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Liszt and Wagner were emerging then. They were the self-proclaimed progressives. 'Music of the future!' But here's a magazine editor-in-chief occasionally composing in the old Beethoven style. They branded him a conservative.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Like a film critic making a short film and people saying he's doing it as a hobby. They accepted him like that. 'Oh, you can write and compose too?'
**Cho Yoon-beom:** But ironically, most of the musicians who attacked Schumann were originally discovered by Schumann's magazine.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Doesn't matter. They were in different classes. They were orthodox musicians, and he was just a critic attached to them. Sideways. Then he wasn't recognized as an orthodox musician, and he was overshadowed by his wife.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** For example, he praised Chopin in his magazine, so Chopin came to see him. He didn't come for the editor-in-chief, but for his wife. 'Oh, this is Clara.' And Liszt, a huge womanizer back then, came and hit on Clara. It caused a rift between Schumann and Liszt. Later, they were on opposite sides: Wagner and Liszt on one side, and Schumann, his friend Mendelssohn, and Brahms on the other. Remember the 100-year war in music history? They were completely split. Schumann was the founder of the Brahms school. Liszt was on the other side. They were already on bad terms because of his wife. Liszt even dedicated a piece to Clara Schumann.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Dedicating it because she wouldn't fall for him. They only knew how to use music, so they dedicated it. It's nothing. I find those 'dedications' funny. They just used what they knew how to do. I look down on 'dedicated to someone' type of things. Who is today's last song dedicated to?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** A song dedicated to his wife.
**Kim Eo-jun:** To his wife? How long after?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** It came out right after they got married.
**Kim Eo-jun:** He dedicated it to himself then. It was originally a song. Schumann successfully married at 30 after winning the trial. For three years after marriage, songs poured out.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Must have been the happiest time in his life.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Uniquely, he dealt with one genre per year. Songs in the first year, symphonies in the second, chamber music in the third. So it's called the Year of Song, Year of Symphony, Year of Chamber Music. He made a songbook called Myrthen. Myrthen is the name of a flower. Used in a bride's wreath. One of the songs there is 'Widmung' (Dedication). Originally a song, but today we'll hear a piano version. Who transcribed it? Liszt. They were still on good terms then. So it's Schumann's melody but has Liszt's flashy piano style.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Master Kim Ka-ram felt it a lot this time.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** It's so cool.
**Kim Eo-jun:** I like this too. The melodies heard in between are Schumann's, and the flashy arpeggios surrounding them are Liszt's style. I feel it through Master Kim Ka-ram. This time, she mostly played in the middle, moving like a pendulum. I felt compassion for Schumann. Like, 'Oh, you felt that way then? Yes, I know. I'll play that for you.' I felt that in her heart.
**Kim Ka-ram:** Thank you. Compassion is the right word. It's one of the happiest moments in his life, and a beautiful melody.
**Kim Eo-jun:** 'I know what that is, so I'll play it for you.' That kind of feeling. Then, at the end, her butt slightly lifted from the chair. About 5cm. She sat back down. Why did you do that?
**Kim Ka-ram:** In music terms, there's 'sforzando'. It means to emphasize that part. There's also 'fortepiano', which means the same thing but requires a different expression. Schumann's difference between the two is very unique. For 'fortepiano', you could emphasize it like 'WAHK!' or like 'WA-AH'. I tried to express it like 'WA-AH'. If you see from the side, you'll understand why I momentarily shifted my weight and sat back.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Fortepiano means making it loud then immediately soft. You can go 'WA-AH' and decrease the volume, but this isn't a string instrument. Once you hit the key, it's done. Key hit, and that's it. So to express that with the body, she did that motion.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Using the whole body to express 'WA-AH'?
**Kim Ka-ram:** Yes, shifting weight slightly. For string instruments, you're still bowing, so loud to soft is possible. For us, it's over after the hit. So I try to put that expression into that moment as much as possible.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Desperate heart. It's like using your body when playing billiards. The ball is already hit, but you move your body to control the direction. Body Shinero. The ball is going, you can't influence it anymore, but you use body Shinero. Blowing energy into it, 'To the left, to the left!' Since I'm putting emotion into it, at least. Is there a term 'body Shinero' in piano performance?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** That's incredible. It's not in the score, but performers interpret it that way. 'This is body Shinero'.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Please add that to the terminology. It hits home. sound is gone, but the heart remains. Putting a curve on the sound. You have to see it all together. And you understand the music after knowing Schumann's story. Without knowing, listening to the music alone is pointless. Those who appreciate it like that are fakes. Not exactly fakes, but we listen more deeply. I understand the music after knowing how Schumann lived and seeing Master Kim Ka-ram's performance. It's heart-wrenching. What happened next?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Liszt transcribed this, right? Liszt came over and said, 'I don't know why people in Leipzig, like Mendelssohn, are so conservative.' The couple got angry and said, 'Let's not see that guy again.' They saw him again later, of course, but they split like that. Schumann went to Düsseldorf. A beautiful place. He spent his later years there. He became the director of the Lower Rhenish Music Festival, which Mendelssohn used to direct. But he was very ill. Not just mentally, but he would shiver and couldn't sleep. Eventually, he said, 'Honey, maybe I should consult a mental hospital.' Clara was shocked. While it was getting worse, he was gone one day while she was out. He had packed his things and jumped into the Rhine. Suicide attempt. A passing sailor saved him. When he came to, he thought, 'What am I doing?' He had moved from the 5th floor to the 2nd floor before, fearing he might jump. Bipolar disorder. He went to the hospital voluntarily. Visitation was forbidden. Especially for his wife, as she was pregnant. Mental hospitals back then were truly inhumane. They couldn't see family. 2.5 years without seeing family. In the hospital, Schumann confessed, 'Actually, when I was young, I slept with the housekeeper at Professor Wieck's and got a disease.' Syphilis. He was treated with arsenic back then. He claimed his depression and physical symptoms started after that treatment.
**Kim Eo-jun:** So after 2.5 years, she came. With Brahms. They were close and stayed so until he went to the hospital. Clara relied on Brahms a lot. After 2.5 years, they came together. Schumann must have sensed it. They left him for a moment to see others, and he was dead when they returned. He died right on the day Clara and Brahms came to visit him after 2.5 years? Right after the visit?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Right after.
**Kim Eo-jun:** They killed him. How could he die on that exact day by coincidence? Clara and Brahms are having an affair. Brahms said he loves her, but she's married. Brahms said he can't betray the teacher who made him famous. Let's settle this. How could he die on the day they visited after 2.5 years?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Clara said in an interview that his last words were 'I know everything'.
**Kim Eo-jun:** He knew about her and Brahms! Musically, it's interpreted as 'I understand how hard it's been for you', but it's BRAHMS! He said 'I know everything' and then they killed him. They probably hesitated after the visit was allowed. 'Let's send him off.' Clara must have suggested it. Brahms might have hesitated, but she's a famous, beautiful pianist, and he's in love. If he comes out, it's over. So they did it?
**Kim Eo-jun:** A visit means he could recover and come out.
**Kim Eo-jun:** There are no hospital records of how he died, right?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** There are various theories, like tertiary syphilis.
**Kim Eo-jun:** They probably made a deal with the hospital. 'Let's say he died of a chronic illness.' I forgot our host used to do political broadcasting. Think about it. What are the odds? Dying on the day of the visit after 2.5 years. The investigation didn't proceed, and the hospital handled it. 'He died of a chronic illness.' The hospital director probably got some money. Doctor, musician, everyone involved. Clara was desperate. What if her husband comes out again? And Brahms is in love with her. So, did they end up together?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** Clara lived for another 40 years.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Where is justice?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** I said Brahms was gaslighted by Clara for his whole life.
**Kim Eo-jun:** I said that without knowing this. Clara manipulated Brahms. Clara was smart. Fighting! Digity and practicality. A smart woman.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** One more thing. She hid the cause of her husband's death for a long time.
**Kim Eo-jun:** She took care of herself and her husband cleanly. But it started with revenge. He imprisoned her when she was young. He took half of her life.
**Kim Ka-ram:** Maybe, because she wanted to escape her father.
**Kim Eo-jun:** She was trapped in the cage of 'Schumann's wife' when she knew nothing. It wasn't happy. For the 2.5 years he was in the hospital, she had no income, so she performed a lot to survive. She solved it economically. She's a person who can survive alone. She didn't want to miss the hard-earned chance.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** If it wasn't a broadcast, I'd go all the way. 'I'll go alone.' Clara performed a lot to earn money during those 2.5 years. In Korea, there's a famous classic club, 'Schumann and Clara'.
**Kim Eo-jun:** How do they understand the relationship?
**Cho Yoon-beom:** A passionate love story. Suing and everything. They probably don't have stories about poison. Our host is the first.
**Kim Eo-jun:** Highly likely poison. I liked the first 'Scherzo'. The music develops unpredictably. I like that, or I fall asleep. And Träumerei. How is Schumann evaluated now among pianists?
**Kim Ka-ram:** We consider him a very attractive composer. His emotions go from one extreme to another. We spend a lot of time alone, so we use music as a mirror to see ourselves. We face the emotions composers hid and express them. Like actors, we immerse ourselves in the music. Then I find things I didn't know I had. Synchronize my feelings. Schumann's music is a monologue, and it's like a play with many roles.
**Cho Yoon-beom:** He had a deep knowledge of literature, so even his love stories aren't simple. You have to look into his life.
**Kim Eo-jun:** I've gone with poison. I'll finish here with the world's first hypothesis. Thank you.